<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <!--forty1-->
    <string name="fortyOne_OLIVERCROMWELL">Oliver Cromwell, the brilliant and inspiring military leader who led the Parliamentary forces to victory in the English Civil War, is the man most responsible for the eventual establishment of parliamentary democracy as the English form of government.
Cromwell was born in 1599, in Huntingdon, England. As a young man, he lived in an England torn by religious dissensions and governed by a king who believed in and wished to practice
    absolute monarchy. Cromwell himself was a farmer and a coun- try gentleman, and a devout Puritan. In 1628, he was elected to Parliament; but he served only briefly, because the following year King Charles I decided to dismiss Parliament and govern the country alone. Not until 1640, when he was in need of money to prosecute a war against the Scots, did the king call a new Parlia- ment. This new Parliament, of which Cromwell was also a member, demanded assurances and protections against a re- sumption of arbitrary rule by the king. But Charles I was unwill- ing to be subservient to Parliament, and in 1642, war broke out between forces loyal to the king and those loyal to Parliament.
Cromwell chose the parliamentary side. Returning to Hun- tingdon, he raised a cavalry troop to fight against the king. Dur- ing the four-year duration of the war, his remarkable military ability won increasing recognition. Cromwell played the leading role at both the critical Battle of Marston Moor (July 2, 1644), which was the turning point of the war, and at the decisive Bat- tle of Naseby (June 14, 1645). In 1646, the war ended with Charles I a prisoner, and with Cromwell recognized as the most successful general on the parliamentary side.
But peace did not come, because the parliamentary side was divided into factions whose goals differed substantially, and because the king, knowing this, avoided a settlement. Within a year, a second civil war had begun, precipitated by the escape of King Charles and his attempt to rally his forces. The outcome of this renewed conflict was the defeat of the kings forces by Cromwell, the elimination of the more moderate members from Parliament, and the execution of the king in January 1649.
England now became a republic (called the Com- monwealth), ruled temporarily by a Council of State, of which Cromwell was chairman. But royalists soon gained control in Ireland and Scotland, and gave their support to the dead kings son, the future Charles II. The result was the successful invasion of both Ireland and Scotland by Cromwells armies. The long series of wars finally ended in 1652 with the complete defeat of the royalist forces.
    Now that the fighting had ended, it was time for the establishment of a new government. There remained, however,
the problem of the constitutional form that government should take. This problem was never to be solved during Cromwells lifetime. The Puritan general had been able to lead to victory the forces that opposed absolute monarchy; but neither his power nor his prestige were sufficient to resolve the social conflicts of his supporters and enable them to agree on a new constitution, for these conflicts were intricately interwoven with the religious con- flicts that divided Protestants from each other, as well as from Roman Catholics.
When Cromwell came to power, all that remained of the Parliament of 1640 was a small, unrepresentative, extremist minority, the so-called Rump. At first, Cromwell tried to negotiate for the holding of new elections. When the negotiations broke down, however, he dissolved the Rump by force (April 20, 1653). From then until Cromwells death in 1658, three different Parliaments were formed and disbanded. Two different constitu- tions were adopted, but neither functioned successfully. Throughout this period, Cromwell ruled with the support of the army. In effect, he was a military dictator. However, his repeated attempts to institute democratic practices, as well as his refusal of the throne when it was offered to him, indicate that dictatorship was not what he sought; it was forced upon him by the inability of his supporters to establish a workable govern- ment.
From 1653 to 1658, Cromwell, under the title of Lord Pro- tector, ruled England, Scotland, and Ireland. During those five years, Cromwell provided Britain with a generally good govern- ment and an orderly administration. He ameliorated various harsh laws, and he supported education. Cromwell was a believer in religious toleration, and he permitted the Jews to resettle in England and to practice their religion there. (They had been expelled from England more than three centuries earlier by King Edward I.) Cromwell also conducted a successful foreign policy. He died in London, in 1658, of malaria. Cromwells eldest son, Richard Cromwell, succeeded him, but ruled only briefly. In 1660, Charles II was restored to the throne. The remains of Oliver Cromwell were dug up and hung from the gibbet. But this vindictive act could not hide the fact that the struggle for royal absolutism had been lost. Charles II fully realized this, and did not attempt to contest Parliaments supremacy. When his successor, James II, tried to restore royal absolutism, he was soon deposed in the bloodless revolution of 1688. The result was just what Cromwell had wanted in 1640, a constitutional monarchy with the king clearly subservient to Parliament, and with a policy of religious toleration.
In the three centuries since his death, the character of Oliver Cromwell has been the subject of considerable dispute. Numerous critics have denounced him as a hypocrite, pointing out that whereas he always claimed to favor parliamentary supremacy, and to be opposed to arbitrary executive rule, he in fact established a military dictatorship. The majority view, though, is that Cromwells devotion to democracy was quite sincere, although circumstances beyond his control sometimes compelled him to exercise dictatorial powers. It has been observ- ed that Cromwell was never devious, nor did he ever accept the throne or the establishment of a permanent dictatorship. His rule was usually moderate and tolerant.
How shall we assess Cromwells overall influence on history? His chief importance, of course, was as a brilliant military leader who defeated the royalist forces in the English Civil War. Since the parliamentary forces had been getting somewhat the worst of it in the early stages of the war, before Cromwell came to the fore, it seems quite possible that their ultimate victory would not have occurred without him. The result of Cromwells victories was that democratic government was maintained and strengthened in England.
This should not be thought of as something that would have occurred in any event. In the seventeenth century, most of Europe was moving in the direction of greater royal absolutism; the triumph of democracy in England was an event running counter to the overall trend. In later years, the example of English democracy was an important factor in the French Enlightenment, in the French Revolution, and in the eventual establishment of democratic governments in western Europe. It is also obvious that the triumph of the democratic forces in England played a vital role in the establishment of democracy in the United States and in other former English colonies, such as Canada and Australia. Although England itself occupies only a- small part of the \vorld, democracy has flowed from England to regions that are not small at all.
Oliver Cromwell would have been ranked higher, except that almost equal credit for the establishment of democratic in- stitutions in England and the United States should be accorded to the philosopher John Locke. It is difficult to assess the relative importance of Cromwell, who was basically a man of action, and Locke, who was a man of ideas. However, given the intel- lectual climate of Lockes day, political ideas closely similar to his would probably have been presented fairly soon, even had Locke himself never lived. On the other hand, had Cromwell never lived, there is a strong chance that the parliamentary forces would have lost the English Civil WaT.</string>
    <!--forty2-->
    <string name="forty2_ALEXANDER_GRAHAM_BELL">Alexander Graham Bell, the inventor of the telephone, was born in Edinburgh, Scotland, in 1847. Although he had only a few years of formal schooling, he was well-educated by his family and himself. Bells interest in the reproduction of vocal sounds arose quite naturally, since his father was an expert in vocal physiology, speech correction, and the teaching of the deaf.
Bell moved to Boston, Massachusetts, in 1871. It was there, in 1875, that he made the discoveries leading to his invention of the telephone. He filed a patent claim for his invention in February 1876, and it was granted a few weeks later. (It is interesting to note that another man, Elisha Gray, had filed a patent claim for a similar device on the same day as Bell, but at a slightly later hour.)
Shortly after his patent was granted, Bell exhibited the elephone at the Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia. His in- vention aroused great public interest, and received an award. Nevertheless, the Western Union Telegraph Company, which was offered the rights to the invention for $100,000, declined to purchase it. Bell and his associates therefore, in July 1877, form- ed a company of their own, the ancestor of todays American Telephone and Telegraph Company. The telephone met with prompt-and enormous--commercial success, and AT&amp;T eventu- ally became the largest private business corporation in the world. (It has since been broken up into several smaller companies.)
Bell and his wife, who in March 1879 owned about 15 per- cent of the shares in the telephone company, seem to have had little idea of just how fantastically profitable the company would be. Within seven months, they had sold the majority of their stock at an average price of about $250 a share. By November, the stock was already selling at $1,000 a share! (Back in March, when the stock was selling at $65 a share, Bells wife had pleaded with him to sell immediately, since she feared the stock would never go that high again!) In 1881, they unwisely sold off one- third of their remaining stock. Nevertheless, by 1883 they were worth about one million dollars.
Though the invention of the telephone made Bell a wealthy man, he never discontinued his research activities, and he suc- ceeded in inventing several other useful (though less important) devices. His interests were varied, but his primary concern always was to help the deaf. His wife, in fact, was a deaf girl whom he had formerly tutored. They had two sons and two daughters, but both boys died as infants. In 1882, Bell became a United States citizen. He died in 1922.
Any estimate of Bells influence rests upon the degree of im- portance one ascribes to the telephone. In my view, this is very great, since few inventions are so widely used and have had such a tremendous impact upon everyday life.
I have ranked Bell below Marconi because the radio is a more versatile device than the telephone. That is, a conversation conducted over the telephone could, in principle, be conducted by radio instead, but there are many situations (such as communication with an airplane in flight), in which a telephone could not possibly replace a radio. Were that the only factor in- volved, Bell would be ranked a lot lower than Marconi. However, there are two other points to be considered. First, although an individual phone conversation could be conducted by radio, it would be extremely difficult to replace our entire telephone system by an equivalent network of radio communica- tion. Second, Bell was the first person to devise a method for reproducing sounds; furthermore, that method was later adapted and utilized by the inventors of the radio receiver, the record player, and various similar devices. I therefore consider Alexander Graham Bell to have been only slightly less influential than Marconi. </string>
    <!--forty3-->
    <string name="forty3_ALEXANDER_FLEMING">Alexander Fleming, the discoverer of penicillin, was born in 1881, in Lochfield, Scotland. After graduating from the medical school of St. Marys Hospital in London, Fleming engaged in im- munological research. Later, as an army doctor in World War I, he studied wound infections, and he noticed that many antisep- tics injured the body cells even more than they injured the microbes. He realized that what was needed was some substance that, while it would harm bacteria, would not be harmful to human cells.
After the war, Fleming returned to St. Marys Hospital. In 1922, while doing research there, he discovered a substance which he called lysozyme. Lysozyme, which is produced by the human body, and which is a component of both mucus and tears, is not harmful to human cells. It destroys certain microbes, but unfortunately, not those that are particularly harmful to man. The discovery, therefore, although interesting, was not of major importance.
It was in 1928 that Fleming made his great discovery. One of his laboratory cultures of staphylococcus bacteria was exposed to the air and became contaminated by a mold. Fleming noticed that in the region of the culture just surrounding the mold, the bacteria had been dissolved. He correctly inferred that the mold was producing some substance which was toxic to the staphylococcus bacteria. He was soon able to show that the same substance inhibited the growth of many other types of harmful bacteria. The substance-which he named penicillin after the mold (penicillium notatum) that produced it-was not toxic to either human beings or animals.
Flemings results were published in 1929, but they did not at first attract much notice. Fleming had suggested that penicillin could have important medical use. However, he himself was unable to develop a technique for purifying penicillin, and for more than ten years the marvelous drug remained unused.
Finally, in the later 1930s, two British medical researchers, Howard Walter Florey and Ernst Boris Chain, came across Flemings article. They repeated his work and verified his results. They then purified penicillin, and tested the substance on laboratory animals. In 1941, they tested penicillin on sick human beings. Their tests clearly showed that the new drug was as- toundingly potent.
With the encouragement of the British and American governments, pharmaceutical companies now entered the field, and rather quickly developed methods for producing large quan- tities of penicillin. At first, penicillin was reserved only for the use of war casualties, but by 1944, it was available for the treat- ment of civilians in Britain and America. When the war ended, in 1945, the use of penicillin spread all over the world.
    The discovery of penicillin greatly stimulated the search for other antibiotics, and that research has resulted in the discovery of many other "miracle drugs." Nevertheless, penicillin remains the most widely used antibiotic.
One reason for its continued supremacy is that penicillin is effective against a very large variety of harmful microorganisms. The drug is useful in the treatment of syphilis, gonorrhea, scarlet fever, and diphtheria, as well as some forms of arthritis, bron- chitis, meningitis, blood poisoning, boils, bone infections,
pneumonia, gangrene, and various other ailments.
Another advantage of penicillin is the wide margin of safety in its use. Doses of 50,000 units of penicillin are effective against some infections; but injections of 100 million units of penicillin a day have been given without ill effects. Although a small per- centage of people are allergic to penicillin, for most persons the
drug provides an ideal combination of potency and safety.
Since penicillin has already saved many millions of lives and will surely save many more in the future, few persons would dispute the importance of Flemings discovery. His exact place- ment on a list such as this would depend, of course, upon how much credit one feels should be allocated to Florey and Chain. I
feel that the bulk of the credit should go to Fleming, who made the essential discovery. Without him, it might have been many years before penicillin was ever discovered. Once he had publish- ed his results, however, it was inevitable that sooner or later im- proved techniques of production and purification would be devised.
Fleming was happily married and had one child. In 1945, he was awarded a Nobel Prize for his discovery, sharing the award with Florey and Chain. Fleming died in 1955.</string>
    <!--forty4-->
    <string name="forty4_JOHN_LOCKE">The famous English philosopher John Locke was the first writer to put together in coherent form the basic ideas of constitutional democracy. His ideas strongly influenced the founding fathers of the United States, as well as many leading philosophers of the French Enlightenment.
Locke was born in 1632, in Wrington, England. He was educated at Oxford University, where he received a bachelors degree in 1656 and a masters degree in 1658. As a young man, he was very much interested in science, and at thirty-six \vas elected to the Royal Society. He became good friends with the famous chemist Robert Boyle, and later in his life became friends with Isaac Newton. He was also interested in medicine, and received a bachelors degree in that field, though he only practiced occasionally.A turning point in Lockes life was his acquaintance with the Earl of Shaftesbury, to whom he became secretary and fami- ly physician. Shaftesbury was an important spokesman for liberal political ideas, and for a while was imprisoned by King Charles II because of his political activities. In 1682, Shaftesbury fled to Holland, where he died the following year. Locke, who because of his close association with Shaftesbury was likewise under suspicion, fled to Holland in 1683. He remained there un- til after Charless successor, King James II, had been removed by the successful revolution of 1688. Locke returned home in 1689; thereafter, he lived in England. Locke, who never married, died
in 1704.
The book that first made Locke. famous was An Essay Concerning
 Human Understanding (1690), in which he discussed the origin, nature, and limits of human knowledge. Lockes views were basically empiricist, and the influence of Francis Bacon and Rene Descartes upon his thought is obvious. Lockes ideas, in turn, influenced philosophers such as Bishop George Berkeley, David Hume, and Immanuel Kant. Although the Essay is Lockes most original work, and is one of the famous classics of philosophy, it has had less influence upon historical developments than his political writings.
In A Letter Concerning Toleration (first published anonymously, in 1689), Locke maintained that the state should not interfere with the free exercise of religion. Locke was not the first Englishman to suggest religious toleration of all Protestant sects; however, the strong arguments he presented in favor of toleration were a factor in the growth of public support for this policy. Furthermore, Locke extended the principle of toleration to non-Christians: " ... neither Pagan, nor Mahometan, nor Jew, ought to be excluded from the civil rights of the commonwealth
because of his religion." However, Locke believed that this toleration should not be extended to Catholics, because he believ- ed that they owed their allegiance to a foreign potentate, nor to atheists. By todays standards, he would therefore be considered very intolerant, but it is reasonable to judge him in relation to the ideas of his own times. In fact, the arguments he presented in favor of religious toleration were more convincing to his readers than the exceptions he made. Today, thanks in part to Lockes writings, religious toleration is extended even to those groups that he would have excluded.
Of still greater importance was Lockes Two Treatises oj Government (1689), in which he presented the basic ideas underlying liberal constitutional democracy. That books in- fluence upon political thought throughout the English-speaking world has been profound. Locke firmly believed that each human being possessed natural rights, and that these included not only life, but personal liberty and the right to hold property. The main purpose of government, Locke asserted, was to protect the persons and property of the subjects. This view has sometimes been called the "night-watchman theory of govern- ment."
Rejecting the notion of the divine right of kings, Locke maintained that governments obtained their authority only from the consent of the governed. "The liberty of man in society is to be under no other legislative power but that established by con- sent in the commonwealth..." Locke strongly emphasized the idea of a social contract. This notion was derived in part from the writings of an earlier English philosopher, Thomas Hobbes (1588-1679). But whereas Hobbes had used the idea of a social contract to justify absolutism, in Lockes view the social contract was revokable:
...whenever the legislators endeavor to take away and destroy the property of the people, or to reduce them to slavery under arbitrary power, they put themselves into a state of war with the people, who are thereupon absolved from any further obedience, and are left to the common refuge which God hath provided for all men against force and violence.
Also, "...there remains still in the people a supreme power to remove or alter the legislative when they find the legislative act contrary to the trust reposed in them..." Lockes defense of the right of revolution strongly influenced Thomas Jefferson and other American revolutionaries.
Locke believed in the principle of separation of powers; however, he felt that the legislature should be superior to the ex- ecutive (and therefore to the judiciary, which he considered a part of the executive branch.) A believer in legislative supremacy, Locke would almost certainly have opposed the right of courts to declare legislative acts unconstitutional.
Though Locke firmly believed in the principle of majority rule, he nevertheless made it clear that a government did not possess unlimited rights. A majority must not violate the natural rights of men, nor was it free to deprive them of their property rights. A government could only rightfully take property with the consent of the governed. (In America, this idea was eventual- ly expressed by the slogan, "No taxation without representa- tion. ")
It is evident from the foregoing that Locke had expressed virtually all the major ideas of the American Revolution almost a century before that event. His influence upon Thomas Jefferson is particularly striking. Lockes ideas penetrated to the European mainland as well-particularly to France, where they were an indirect factor leading to the French Revolution and the French Declaration of the Rights of Man. Although such figures as Voltaire and Thomas Jefferson are more famous than Locke, his writings preceded theirs and strongly influenced them. It therefore seems reasonable that he should precede them on this list.
    </string>
    <!--forty5-->
    <string name="forty5_LUDWIG_VAN_BEETHOVEN">Ludwig van Beethoven, the greatest of all musical composers, was born in 1770, in the city of Bonn, Germany. He exhibited talent at an early age, and his first published works date from 1783. As a young man, he visited Vienna, where he was in- troduced to Mozart; however, their acquaintance was fairly brief. In 1792, Beethoven returned to Vienna, and for a while he studied under Haydn, then the leading Viennese composer (Mozart had died the year before). Beethoven was to remain in
Vienna, at that time the music capital of the world, for the remainder of his life.
Beethovens immense virtuosity as a pianist impressed everyone, and he was successful both as a performer and a teacher. He soon became a prolific composer as well. His works were well received, and from his mid-twenties on, he was able to sell them to publishers without difficulty.
    When Beethoven was in his late twenties, the first signs of his deafness appeared. Not surprisingly, the young composer was deeply disturbed by this ominous development. For a while, he even contemplated suicide.
The years from 1802 to 1815 are sometimes considered the middle period of Beethovens career. During this interval, as his deafness steadily progressed, he began to withdraw socially. His increasing deafness caused people to form the unwarranted im- pression that he was a misanthrope. He had several romantic at- tachments with young ladies, but all appear to have ended unhappily, and he never married.
Beethovens musical output continued to be prolific. As the years went by, however, he paid less and less attention to what would be popular with the musical audiences of his day. Never- theless, he continued to be successful.
In his late forties, Beethoven became totally deaf. As a con- sequence, he gave no more public performances and became even more withdrawn socially. His works were fewer and harder to understand. By now, he was composing primarily for himself
and some ideal future audience. He is alleged to have said to one critic, "They are not for you, but for a later age."
It is one of the cruelest ironies of fate that the most talented composer of all times should have been afflicted with the disability of deafness. Had Beethoven, by a superhuman effort of will, managed to maintain the quality of his compositions despite his deafness, it would have been an inspiring and near-incredible feat. But truth is stranger than fiction: in fact, during his years of total deafness, Beethoven did more than merely equal the level of his earlier compositions. The works that he produced during those last years are generally considered to be his greatest master-
pieces. He died in Vienna in 1827, at the age of fifty-seven. Beethovens large output included nine symphonies, thirty- two piano sonatas, five piano concertos, ten sonatas for the piano and violin, a series of magnificent string quartets, vocal music, theater music, and much more. More important, however, than the quantity of his work is its quality. His works superbly combine intensity of feeling with perfection of design. Beethoven demonstrated that instrumental music could no longer be con- sidered an art form of secondary importance, and his own com- positions raised such music to the very highest level of art.
Beethoven was a highly original composer, and many of the changes that he introduced have had a lasting effect. He expand- ed the size of the orchestra. He extended the length of the sym- phony and widened its scope. By demonstrating the enormous possibilities of the piano, he helped to establish it as the foremost musical instrument. Beethoven marked the transition from the
classical to the romantic style of music, and his works were an in- spiration for much that characterized romanticism.
Beethoven had a very great influence upon many later com- posers, including persons with such diverse styles as Brahms, Wagner, Schubert, and Tchaikovsky. He also paved the way for Berlioz, Gustav Mahler, Richard Strauss, and many others. t seems plain that Beethoven must outrank any other musi- cian on this list. Although Johann Sebastian Bach is almost equal- ly prestigious, Beethovens works have been more widely and fre- quently listened to than Bachs. Furthermore, the numerous in- novations that Beethoven made have had a more profound in- fluence on subsequent developments in music than Bachs works have.
In general, political and ethical ideas can be more easily and clearly expressed in words than in music, and literature is thus a more influential field of art than is music. It is for this reason that Beethoven, though the preeminent figure in the history of music, has been ranked somewhat lower than Shakespeare. In compar- ing Beethoven with Michelangelo, I have been strongly influ- enced by the fact that most persons spend far more time listening to music than they do looking at painting or sculpture. For this
reason, I think that musical composers are generally more in- fluential than painters or sculptors whose eminence in their own field is equivalent. All in all, it seems appropriate to rank Beethoven roughly halfway between Shakespeare and Michelangelo.</string>
    <!--forty6-->
    <string name="forty6_WERNER_HEISENBERG">
In 1932, the Nobel Prize in physics was awarded to Werner Karl Heisenberg, a German physicist, for his role in the creation of quantum mechanics, one of the most important achievements in the entire history of science.
Mechanics is that branch of physics which deals with the general la\vs governing the motion of material objects. It is the most fundamental branch of physics, which in turn is the most fundamental of the sciences. In the early years of the hventieth century, it gradually became apparent that the accepted laws of mechanics were unable to describe the behavior of extremely
minute objects, such as atoms and subatomic particles. This was both distressing and puzzling, since the accepted laws worked superbly when applied to macroscopic objects (that is, to objects which were much larger than individual atoms).
In 1925, Werner Heisenberg proposed a new formulation of physics, one that was radically different in its basic concepts from the classical formulation of Newton. This new theory- after some modification by Heisenbergs successors-has been brilliantly successful, and is today accepted as being applicable to all physical systems, of whatever type or size.
It can be demonstrated mathematically that where only macroscopic systems are involved, the predictions of quantum mechanics differ from those of classical mechanics by amounts which are far too small to measure. (For this reason, classical mechanics-which is mathematically much simpler than quan- tum mechanics-can still be used for most scientific computa- tions.) However, where systems of atomic dimensions are involv- ed, the predictions of quantum mechanics differ substantially from those of classical mechanics; experiments have shown that in such cases the predictions of quantum mechanics are correct.
One of the consequences of Heisenbergs theory is the famous "uncertainty principle," which he himself formulated in 1927. That principle is generally considered to be one of the most profound and far-reaching principles in all of science. What the uncertainty principle does is to specify certain theoretical limits on our ability to make scientific measurements. The implications of this principle are enormous. If the basic laws of physics pre- vent a scientist, even in the most ideal circumstances, from ob- taining accurate knowledge of the system that he is attempting to investigate, it is obvious that the future behavior of that system cannot be completely predicted. According to the uncertainty principle, no improvements in our measuring apparatus will ever
permit us to surmount this difficulty!
The uncertainty principle insures that physics, in the very
nature of things, is unable to make more than statistical predic- tions. (A scientist studying radioactivity, for example, might be able to predict that out of a trillion radium atoms, two million will emit gamma rays during the next day. He is, however, unable to predict whether any particular radium atom will do so.) In many practical circumstances, this is not a grave restric- tion. Where very large numbers are involved, statistical methods can often provide a very reliable basis for action; but where small numbers are involved, statistical predictions are unreliable in- deed. In fact, where small systems are involved, the uncertainty principle forces us to abandon our ideas of strict physical causali- ty. This represents a most profound change in the basic
philosophy of science; so profound, indeed, that a great scientist like Einstein was never willing to accept it. "I cannot believe," Einstein once said, "that God plays dice with the universe." That, however, is essentially the view that most modern physicists have felt it necessary to adopt.
It is clear that from a theoretical point of view the quantum theory, to a greater extent perhaps than even the theory of relativity, has altered our basic conception of the physical world. However, the theorys consequences are not only philosophical.
Among its practical applications are such modern devices as electron microscopes, lasers, and transistors. Quantum theory also has wide applications in nuclear physics and atomic energy. It forms the basis of our knowledge of spectroscopy, and is employed extensively in astronomy and chemistry. It is also used in theoretical investigations of such diverse topics as the proper- ties of liquid helium, the internal constitution of the stars, fer- romagnetism, and radioactivity.
Werner Heisenberg was born in Germany, in 1901. He received a doctorate in theoretical physics from the University of Munich in 1923. From 1924 to 1927, he worked in Copenhagen
with the great Danish physicist, Niels Bohr. His first important paper on quantum mechanics was published in 1925, and his for- mulation of the uncertainty principle appeared in 1927. Heisen- berg died in 1976, at the age of seventy-four. He was survived by his wife and seven children.
In view of the importance of quantum mechanics, the read- er may wonder why Heisenberg has not been ranked even higher on this list. However, Heisenberg was not the only important sci
entist involved in the development of quantum mechanics. Sig- nificant contributions had been made by his predecessors, Max Planck, Albert Einstein, Niels Bohr, and the French scientist, Louis de Broglie. In addition, many other scientists, including the Austrian, Erwin Schrodinger, and the Englishman, P.A.M. Dirac, made major contributions to quantum theory in the years immediately following the publication of Heisenbergs seminal paper. Nevertheless, I think that Heisenberg was the principal
figure in the development of quantum mechanics, and that- even when the credit is distributed-his contributions entitle him to a high spot on this list.</string>
    <!--forty7-->
    <string name="forty7_LOUIS_DAGUERRE">Louis Jacques Mande Daguerre was the man who, in the late 1830s, succeeded in developing the first practical method of photography.
Daguerre was born in 1787, in the town of Cormeilles, in northern France. As a young man, he was an artist. In his mid- thirties, he designed the Diorama, a spectacular array of panora- mic paintings exhibited with special lighting effects. While
engaged in this work, he became interested in developing a mechanism for automatically reproducing views of the world without brushes and paint-in other words, a camera.
His early attempts to devise a workable camera were unsuc- cessful. In 1827, he met Joseph Nicephore Niepce, who had likewise been trying (and up till then with somewhat greater suc- cess) to invent a camera. Two years later they became partners. n 1833, Niepce died, but Daguerre persisted in his efforts. By 1837, he had succeeded in developing a practical system of photography, called the daguerreotype.
In 1839, Daguerre made his process public, without patent- ing it; in return, the French government granted lifetime pen- sions both to Daguerre and to Niepces son. The announcement of Daguerres invention created a great public sensation. Daguerre was the hero of the day and was showered with honors, while the daguerreotype method rapidly came into widespread use. Daguerre himself soon retired. He died in 1851, at his country home near Paris.
Few inventions have as many uses as photography does. It is widely employed in virtually every field of scientific research. It has a wide variety of industrial and military applications. It is a serious art form for some people, and an enjoyable hobby for millions more. Photographs impart information (or misinforma- tion) in education, journalism, and advertising. Because photographs are capable of vividly recalling the past, they have become the most common of all souvenirs and mementos. Cinematography, of course, is an important subsidiary develop- ment that-besides serving as a major entertainment medium-. has virtually as many applications as still photography.
No invention derives entirely from the work of a single man, and certainly, the earlier work of many other men had prepared the way for Daguerres achievement. The camera obscura (a device similar to a pinhole camera, but without any film) had been invented at least eight centuries before Daguerre. In the six- teenth century, Girolamo Cardano took the important step of placing a lens in the opening of the camera obscura. That made it an interesting preliminary to the modern camera; however, since the image it produced had no permanence at all, it can hardly be considered a type of photography. Another important prelimi- nary discovery was made in 1727, by Johann Schulze, who discovered that silver salts were sensitive to light. Although he used this discovery to make some temporary images, Schulze did not really pursue the idea.

The predecessor who came closest to Daguerres achieve- ment was Niepce, who later became Daguerres partner. About 1820, Niepce discovered that bitumen of Judea, a type of asphalt, was sensitive to light. By combining this light-sensitive substance with a camera obscura, Niepce succeeded in making the worlds first photographs. (One that he took in 1826 still ex- ists.) For that reason, some people feel that Niepce should rightly be considered the inventor of photography. However, Niepces method of photography was totally impractical, since it required about eight hours exposure time, and even then resulted in a rather fuzzy picture.
In Daguerres method, the image was recorded on a plate coated with silver iodide. An exposure time of fifteen to twenty minutes was sufficient, which made the method, although cumbersome, of practical utility. Within two years after Daguerre made his method public, other persons proposed a slight modification: the addition of silver bromide to the silver iodide used as a light-sensitive material. This slight change had the important effect of greatly reducing the exposure time need- ed, and thereby making it practical to make portraits by photography.
In 1839, not long after Daguerre announced his invention of photography, William Henry Fox Talbot, an English scientist, announced that he had developed a different method of photography, one that involved making negative prints first, as is done today. It is interesting to note that Talbot had actually pro- duced his first photographs in 1835, two years before the first daguerreotype. Talbot, who was engaged in several other pro- jects, did not promptly follow up his photographic experiments. Had he done so, he would probably have developed a commer- cially feasible system of photography before Daguerre did, and would today be considered the inventor of photography.
In the years following Daguerre and Talbot, there have been enormous improvements in photography: the wet-plate process, the dry-plate process, modern roll film, color photo- graphs, motion pictures, Polaroid photography, and xerography. Despite the many persons involved in the development of photography, I feel that Louis Daguerre made by far the most important contribution. There was no feasible system of photo- graphy before him, whereas the technique that he devised was practical and soon became widely used. Furthermore, his well- publicized invention provided a great impetus to subsequent developments. It is true that the methods of photography that we use today are very different from the daguerreotype method; however, even had none of these later techniques ever been developed, the daguerreotype would provide us with a usable technique of photography.
    </string>
    <!--forty8-->
    <string name="forty8_SIMON_BOLIVAR">
Simon BolIvar is often called "the George Washington of South America" because of his role in the liberation of five South American countries (Colombia, Venezula, Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia) from Spanish rule. Few, if any, political figures have played so dominant a role in the history of an entire continent as he did.
Bolivar was born in 1783, in Caracas, Venezuela, into an aristocratic family of Spanish descent. He was orphaned at the age of nine. During his formative years, Bolivar was strongly in- fluenced by the ideas and ideals of the French Enlightenment. Among the philosophers whose works he read were John Locke, Rousseau, Voltaire, and Montesquieu.
As a young man, Bolivar visited several European countries. In Rome, in 1805, at the top of the Aventine Hill, Bollvar made
his celebrated vow that he would not rest until his fatherland had been liberated from Spain.
In 1808, Napoleon Bonaparte invaded Spain and placed his own brother at the head of the Spanish governlnent. By dislodg- ing the Spanish royal family from effective political power, Napoleon provided the South American colonies with a golden opportunity to strike out for their own political independence.
The revolution against Spanish rule in Venezuela com- menced in 1810, when the Spanish governor of Venezuela was deposed. A formal declaration of independence was made in 1811, and that same year BolIvar became an officer in the revolu- tionary army. But the following year, the Spanish troops regain- ed control of Venezuela. The leader of the revolution, Francisco Miranda, was jailed, and Bolivar fled the country.
The succeeding years witnessed a series of wars, in which temporary victories were followed by crushing defeats. Never- theless, Bolivars resolution never wavered. The turning point came in 1819, when Bolivar led his small, ragtag army across rivers, plains, and the high passes of the Andes in order to attack the Spanish troops in Colombia. There he won the crucial Battle of Boyaca (August 7, 1819), the true turning point of the strug- gle. Venezuela was liberated in 1821, and Ecuador in 1822.
Meanwhile, the Argentine patriot Jose de San Martln had secured the freedom of Argentina and Chile from Spanish rule, and had undertaken the liberation of Peru. The two liberators met in the city of Guayaquil, Ecuador, in the summer of 1822. However, they were unable to agree on a plan for cooperating and coordinating their efforts against the Spanish. Since San Martin was unwilling to engage in a power struggle with the am- bitious Bolivar (which would only have aided the Spanish), he decided to resign his command and withdraw from South America completely. By 1824, Bolivars armies had completed
the liberation of what is now Peru, and in 1825, the Spanish troops in Upper Peru (present-day Bolivia) were routed.
The remaining years of BolIvars career were less successful. He had been impressed by the example of the United States of America, and looked forward to a federation of the new South American nations. In fact, Venezuela, Colombia, and Ecuador had already been formed into a Republic of Greater Colombia, with Bollvar as president. Unfortunately, the centrifugal tenden- cies in South America were far greater than they had been in the North American colonies. When BolIvar convoked a Congress of
Spanish American States in 1826, only four nations attended. In- deed, rather than more nations joining Greater Colombia, the republic itself soon began to break up. Civil war broke out, and in 1828, an attempt was made to assassinate Bollvar. By 1830, Venezuela and Ecuador had seceded. BolIvar, realizing that he himself was an obstacle to peace, resigned in April 1830. When he died, in December 1830, he was discouraged, impoverished, and exiled from his native Venezuela.
Bolivar was clearly a very ambitious man, and under the ex- igencies of the times, he sometimes assumed dictatorial powers. Nevertheless, when it came to a choice, he was willing to subor- dinate his personal ambitions to the public welfare and the ideal of democracy, and he invariably relinquished his dictatorial powers. He was once offered a throne, but declined it. Doubtless, he felt that the name "EI Libertador" (the Liberator),
which had already been bestowed upon him, was a greater honor than any kingly title.
There is no doubt that Bolivar was the dominant figure in the liberation of Spanish America from colonial rule. He pro- vided the ideological leadership for the movement-writing articles, issuing a newspaper, making speeches, and writing let- ters. He was tireless in raising funds to support the struggle. And he was the principal military leader of the revolutionary forces.
Still, it would be a mistake to think of Bolivar as a great general. The armies he defeated were neither large nor well-led. BolIvar himself was not particularly talented in either strategy or tactics. (This is hardly surprising, since he had never received any military training.) But BolIvar made up for all his other shortcomings by his indomitable spirit in the face of adversity.
After each defeat by the Spanish, when others were willing to abandon the fight, Bolivar resolutely reassembled an army and continued the struggle.
In my opinion, Bolivar was far more influential than such fa- mous figures as Julius Caesar or Charlemagne, both because the changes resulting from his career have proven more permanent, and because the regions affected cover a larger area. However, Bolivar has been ranked below Alexander the Great, Adolf Hitler, and Napoleon, since many of the things that those three men did would not have occurred without them, while it is difficult to be- lieve that the South American countries would not eventually have achieved their independence anyway.
The most interesting and significant comparison to make is between Bolivar and George Washington. Like Washington, BolIvar commanded small and poorly-trained armies. Money was short, and it frequently required an inspiring leader to keep the army together at all.
Unlike Washington, Bolivar freed all his own slaves during his lifetime. In addition, by proclamation and by constitutional provision, he actively tried to abolish slavery in the lands he liberated. His attempts were not wholly successful, and slavery still existed in the region when he died.
Bollvar had a complex and interesting personality- dramatic, daring, and romantic. A handsome man, he had numerous love affairs. He was a far-sighted idealist, but had less administrative ability than Washington, and enjoyed flattery more. He was far more ambitious than Washington-to the disadvantage of the regions that he liberated. On the other hand, Bolivar was utterly uninterested in financial gain. He was wealthy when he entered politics, poor when he retired.
The territory that Bolivar freed from colonial rule was con- siderably larger than that of the original United States. Never- theless, it is clear that he is a considerably less important figure than Washington, simply because the United States has played a far more important role in history than the countries liberated by Bolivar.</string>
    <!--forty9-->
    <string name="forty9_RENE_DESCARTES">Rene Descartes, the famous French philosopher, scientist, and mathematician, was born in 1596, in the village of La Haye. In his youth he attended a fine Jesuit school, the College of La Fleche. When he was twenty, he obtained a law degree from the University of Poitiers; however, he never practfced law. Though he had received an excellent education, Descartes was convinced that there was very little reliable knowledge in any field, with the exception of mathematics. Rather than continuing his formal education, he decided to travel throughout Europe and see the world for himself. As his family was well-to-do, Descartess in- come was sufficient to enable him to travel freely.
From 1616 to       Descartes traveled extensively. He serv- ed briefly in three different armies (those of Holland, Bavaria, and Hungary), though apparently he was not involved in any combat. He also visited Italy, Poland, Denmark, and other coun- tries. During these years, he formulated what he considered to be a general method for discovering truth. When he was thirty-two years old, Descartes decided to apply his method in an attempt to construct a comprehensive picture of the world. He then settled in Holland, where he was to live for the next twenty-one years. (He chose Holland because there was more intellectual liberty there, and also because he preferred to be away from the social distractions of Paris.)
About 1629, he wrote Rules for the Direction of the Mind, a book in which his method was outlined. (However, the book is incomplete and was probably never intended for publication; it was first published more than fifty years after Descartess death.) In the years from 1630 through 1634, Descartes applied his method to the study of the sciences. To learn more about anatomy and physiology, he performed dissections. He engaged in major independent research in optics, meteorology, mathematics, and several other branches of science.
It was Descartess intention to present his scientific results in a book to be called Le Monde (the world). However, in 1633, when the book was almost finished, he learned that church authorities in Italy had convicted Galileo for advocating Coper- nicuss theory that the earth revolved about the sun. Though in Holland he was not subject to the Catholic authorities, Descartes nevertheless decided that it would be prudent of him not to issue his book, as in it, he, too, defended the Copernican theory. In- stead, in 1637, he published his most famous work, his Discourse on the Method for Properly Guiding the Reason and Finding Truth in the Sciences (usually abbreviated to Discourse on Method).
The Discourse was written in French rather than Latin, so that all intelligent persons could read it, including those who had not had a classical education. Appended to the Discourse were three essays in which Descartes gave examples of the discoveries he had made by the use of his method. In the first such appendix, the Optics, Descartes presented the law of refraction of light (which had, however, been discovered earlier by Willebrord Snell). He also discussed lenses and various optical instruments; described the functioning of the eye and various malfunctions; and presented a theory of light that is a preliminary version of the wave theory later formulated by Christiaan Huygens. His second appendix comprised the first modern discussion of meteorology. He discussed clouds, rain, and wind, and gave a correct explana- tion for the rainbow. He argued against the notion that heat con- sists of an invisible fluid, and he correctly concluded that heat is a form of internal motion. (But this idea had already been presented by Francis Bacon and others.) In the third appendix, the Geometry, Descartes presented his most important contribu- tion of all, his invention of analytic geometry. This was a major mathematical advance that prepared the way for Newtons in-
vention of calculus.
Perhaps the most interesting part of Descartess philosophy
is the way he begins. Mindful of the large number of incorrect notions that were generally accepted, Descartes decided that in order to reach the truth he must make a fresh start. He therefore begins by doubting everything-everything his teachers had told him, all of his most cherished beliefs, all his commonsense ideas-even the existence of the external world, even his own existence-in a word, everything.
This, of course, leads to a problem: how is it possible to overcome such universal doubt and obtain reliable knowledge of anything? Descartes, however, by a series of ingenious meta- physical arguments, was able to prove to his own satisfaction that he himself existed ("I think, therefore I am"), that God ex- ists, and that the external world exists. These were the starting points of Descartess theory.
The importance of Descartess method is twofold. First, he placed at the center of his philosophical system the fundamental epistemological question, "What is the origin of human know- ledge?" Earlier philosophers had tried to describe the nature of the world. Descartes has taught us that such a question cannot be answered satisfactorily except in conjunction with the question "How do I know?"
Second, Descartes suggested that we should start not with faith but with doubt. (This was the exact reverse of the attitude of St. Augustine, and most medieval theologians, that faith must come first.) It is true that Descartes then proceeded to reach or- thodox theological conclusions. However, his readers paid far
more attention to the method he advocated than to the conclu- sions he reached. (The Churchs fears that Descartess writings would in the end prove subversive were quite justified.)
In his philosophy, Descartes stresses the distinction between the mind and material objects, and in this respect advocates a thoroughgoing dualism. This distinction had been made before, but Descartess writings stimulated philosophical discussion of the subject. The questions he raised have interested philosophers ever since, and have still not been resolved.
Also highly influential was Descartess conception of the physical universe. He believed that the entire world-aside from God and the human soul-operated mechanically, and that therefore all natural events could be explained by mechanical causes. For this reason, he rejected the claims of astrology, magic, and other forms of superstition. He likewise rejected all teleological explanations of events. (That is, he looked for direct mechanical causes and rejected the notion that events occurred in order to serve some remote final purpose.) From Descartess outlook, it followed that animals were, in essence, complicated machines, and that the human body, too, was subject to the ordinary laws of mechanics. This has since become one of the fundamental ideas of modern physiology.
Descartes favored scientific research and believed that its practical applications could be beneficial to society. He felt that scientists should avoid vague notions and should attempt to describe the world by mathematical equations. All this sounds very modern. However, Descartes, though he made observations himself, never really stressed the crucial importance of ex- perimentation in the scientific method. The famous British philosopher Francis Bacon had pro- claimed the need for scientific investigation, and the benefits to be expected therefrom, several years before Descartes. Nor was Descartess celebrated argument, "I think, therefore 1 am," original; it had been stated more than 1200 years earlier (in different words, of course) by St. Augustine. Similarly, Descartess "proof" of the existence of God is merely a variation of the ontological argument first presented by St. Anselm (1033-1109) .
In 1641, Descartes published another famous book, the Meditations. His Principles of Philosophy appeared in 1644. Both were originally written in Latin, but French translations ap- peared in 1647.
Although Descartes was a polished writer, with a charming prose style, the tone of his writings is surprisingly old-fashioned. Indeed, he often sounds (perhaps because of his rationalist ap- proach) like a medieval scholastic. By contrast, Francis Bacon, though born thirty-five years before Descartes, has a quite modern tone.)
As his writings make clear, Descartes was a firm believer in God. He considered himself a good Catholic; however, Church authorities disliked his views, and his works were placed on the Catholic Index of forbidden books. Even in Protestant Holland (at that time, probably the most tolerant country in Europe), Descartes was accused of atheism and had trouble with the authorities.
In 1649, Descartes accepted a generous financial offer from Queen Christina of Sweden to come to Stockholm and become her private tutor. Descartes liked warm rooms, and had always enjoyed sleeping late. He was much distressed to learn that the queen wanted her lessons given at five oclock in the morning! Descartes feared that the cold morning air would be the death of him, and indeed it was: it was not long before he caught pneumonia. He died in February 1650, only four months after arriving in Sweden.
Descartes never married. However he had one child, a daughter, who unfortunately died young. Descartess philosophy was strongly criticized by many of his contemporaries, in part because they felt that it involved cir- cular reasoning. Subsequent philosophers have pointed out many shortcomings in his system, and few people today would defend it wholeheartedly. But the importance of a philosopher does not depend solely on the correctness of his system: of greater significance is whether his ideas-or rather, the ideas that others extract from his writings-prove widely influential. On that basis, there is little doubt that Descartes was an important figure.
At least five of Descartess ideas had an important impact on European thought: (a) his mechanical view of the universe; (b) his positive attitude towards scientific investigation; (c) the stress he laid on the use of mathematics in science; (d) his advocacy of initial skepticism; and (e) the attention he focused on epistemol- ogy.
In assessing Descartess overall importance I have also taken into account his impressive scientific achievements, in particular his invention of analytic geometry. It is that factor which has persuaded me to rank Descartes substantially higher than such eminent philosophers as Voltaire, Rousseau, and Francis Bacon.</string>
    <!--fifty-->
    <string name="fifty_MICHEL_ANGELO">The great Renaissance artist Michelangelo Buonarroti is the outstanding figure in the history of the visual arts. A brilliant painter, sculptor, and architect, Michelangelo left behind an assortment of masterpieces which have impressed viewers for over four centuries. His work profoundly influenced the subse- quent development of European painting and sculpture.
Michelangelo was born in 1475, in the town of Caprese, Ita- ly, about forty miles from Florence. He showed talent at an early age, and at thirteen he was apprenticed to the famous painter Ghirlandaio, in Florence. When Michelangelo was fifteen, he was taken to live in the Medici palace, almost as a member of the family, by Lorenzo the Magnificent, the ruler of Florence, who
    became his patron. Throughout his career, Michelangelos enor- mous talent was obvious, and he was frequently commissioned by popes and secular rulers alike, to design and produce works of art. Although he lived in various places, most of his life was spent in Rome and Florence. He died in Rome, in 1564, shortly before his eighty-ninth birthday. He never married.
Although he was not quite as universal a genius as his older contemporary, Leonardo da Vinci, Michelangelos versatility is still extremely impressive. He was the only artist, in- deed, perhaps the only per- son, ever to reach the highest peaks of achieve- ment in two separate fields of human endeavor. As a painter, Michelangelo ranks
  at or near the very top, both in the quality of his finest work and in the influence he has had upon later painters. The enormous set of frescoes with which he decorated the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel in Rome is justly celebrated as one of the greatest artistic achievements of all time. Nevertheless, Michelangelo considered himself to be primarily a sculptor, and many critics consider him the greatest sculptor who ever lived. His statues of David and of Moses, for ex- ample, and the famous Pieta, are all works of unex- celled artistry.
     Michelangelo was also a highly talented architect. Among his well-known achievements in this field is the design of the Medici Chapel in Florence. For a good many years, he was also the chief architect of St. Peters in Rome.
Michelangelo composed many poems during his lifetime, some 300 of which survive. His numerous sonnets and other poems were not published until well after his death. They pro-
vide considerable insight into his personality, and clearly show that he was a talented poet.
As I have explained in the article on Shakespeare, it is my belief that art and artists in general have had comparatively little influence upon human history and everyday life. It is for that reason that Michelangelo, despite his eminence as an artistic genius, appears lower on this list than many scientists and inven- tors, many of whom are far less famous than he.</string>
    <!--fifty1-->
    <string name="fifty1_POPE_URBAN_II">Not many people today remember Pope Urban II. Yet there have been few men whose impact on human history has been so ob- vious and so direct, for Urban II was the pope whose call for a Christian war to recapture the Holy Land from the Moslems in- augurated the Crusades.
Urban, whose original name was Odo de Lagery, was born about 1042, near the city of Chatillon-sur-Marne in France. He came from a great family of French nobles, and he received a good education. As a young man, he was an archdeacon at Reims. Later, he became successively a Cluniac monk, a prior, and a cardinal-bishop, before his election as pope in 1088.
Urban was a strong, effective, and politically astute pope, but this is not what has earned him a place in this book. The action for which Urban II is principally remembered occurred on November 27, 1095. He had convoked a great church council, held at the city of Clermont in France. There, before a crowd of thousands, Urban delivered what was perhaps the single most effective speech in history-one that was to influence Europe for centuries to come. In his speech, Urban protested that the Seljuk Turks, who were occupying the Holy Land, were defiling the Christian holy places and molesting Christian pilgrims. Urban urged that all Christendom join together in a holy war-a great crusade to recapture the Holy Land for Christianity. But Urban was far too clever to appeal to altruistic motives alone. He pointed out that the Holy Land was fruitful and wealthy-far richer than the overcrowded lands of Christian Europe. Finally, the Pope announced, participation in the crusade would take the place of all penances and assure the crusader of remission of all his sins.
Urbans brilliant speech, which appealed at the same time to his listeners highest motives and to their most selfish ones, aroused passionate enthusiasm in his audience. Before he had finished, the multitude was shouting, "Deus Ie volt!" (God wills it), which was soon to become the battle cry of the crusaders. Within a few months, the First Crusade was under way. It was to be followed by a long series of holy wars (there were eight major crusades and many smaller ones), which took place over a period of roughly two hundred years.
As for Urban himself, he died in 1099, two weeks after the First Crusade succeeded in capturing Jerusalem, but before news of that capture had reached him.
It hardly seems necessary to explain the importance of the Crusades. Like all wars, they had a direct influence upon the participants, and upon the civilian populations caught in their path. In addition, however, the Crusades had the effect of bringing western Europe into close contact with the Byzantine and Islamic civilizations, which at that time were considerably more advanced than western Europe. That contact helped prepare the way for the Renaissance, which in turn led to the full
flowering of modern European civilization.
Pope Urban II is on this list not only because of the enor-
mous significance of the Crusades, but also because it is unlikely that they would have taken place without his inspiration. Ob- viously, conditions were ripe; otherwise his speech would have fallen upon deaf ears. However, to start a general European movement, the leadership of some central figure was needed. No national king could have done it. (Had a German emperor, for example, declared a holy war against the Turks, and led his armies on a crusade, it is doubtful that many English knights would have joined him.) There was only one figure in western Europe whose authority transcended national boundaries. Only the Pope could propose a project for all western Christendom to
engage in, with a hope that large numbers of persons would follow his suggestion. Without the leadership of the Pope, and the dramatic speech which he made, the Crusades, as a mass European movement, would probably never have begun.
Nor were circumstances such that virtually any person holding the papal office would have proposed a crusade to liberate the Holy Land. On the contrary, it was in many ways an impractical suggestion. Most prudent leaders would be very reluctant to make an unusual proposal, the consequences of which were so difficult to predict. But Urban II dared to do so; and by so doing he had a greater and more enduring effect on human history than many far more famous men. </string>
    <!--fifty2-->
    <string name="fifty2_UMAR_IBN_AL_KHATTAB">"Umar ibn al-Khattab was the second, and probably the greatest, of the Moslem caliphs. He was a younger contemporary of Muhammad, and like the Prophet, was born in Mecca. The year of his birth is unknown, but was perhaps about 586.
Umar was originally one of the most bitter opponents of Iv1uhammad and his new religion. Rather suddenly, however, "Umar became converted to Islam, and thereafter was one of its strongest supporters. (The parallel with the conversion of St. Paul to Christianity is striking.) Umar became one of the closest advisors of the prophet Muhammad, and remained so throughout Muhammads life.
In 632, Muhammad died without having named a suc- cessor. Umar promptly supported the candidacy of Abu Bakr, a close associate and father-in-law of the Prophet. This avoided a power struggle and enabled Abu Bakr to be generally recognized as the first caliph (i.e., as the "successor" of Muhammad). Abu Bakr was a successful leader, but he died after serving as caliph for only two years. He had, however, specifically named Vmar (who was also a father-in-law of the Prophet) to succeed him, so once again a power struggle was avoided. Vmar became caliph in 634, and retained power until 644, when he was assassinated in Medina by a Persian slave. On his deathbed, Vmar named a committee of six persons to choose his successor, thereby again averting an armed struggle for power. The committee chose
Othman, the third caliph, who ruled from 644 to 656.
It was during the ten years of Vmars caliphate that the most important conquests of the Arabs occurred. Not long after Vmars accession, Arab armies invaded Syria and Palestine, which at that time were part of the Byzantine Empire. At the Battle of the Yarmuk (636), the Arabs won a crushing victory over the Byzantine forces. Damascus fell the same year, and Jerusalem surrendered two years later. By 641, the Arabs had conquered all of Palestine and Syria, and were advancing into
present-day Turkey. In 639, Arab armies invaded Egypt, which had also been under Byzantine rule. Within three years, the Arab conquest of Egypt was complete.
Arab attacks upon Iraq, at that time part of the Sassanid Empire of the Persians, had commenced even before Vmar took office. The key Arab victory, at the battle of Qadisiya (637) oc- curred during Vmars reign. By 641, all of Iraq was under Arab control. Nor was that all: Arab armies invaded Persia itself, and at the battle of Nehavend (642) they decisively defeated the forces of the last Sassanid emperor. By the time Vmar died, in 644, most of western Iran had been overrun. Nor had the Arab armies run out of momentum when Vmar died. In the East, they fairly soon completed the conquest of Persia, while in the West they continued their push across North Africa.
Just as important as the extent of Vmars conquests is their permanence. Iran, though its population became converted to Islam, eventually regained its independence from Arab rule. But Syria, Iraq, and Egypt never did. Those countries became thoroughly Arabized and remain so to this day. Umar, of course, had to devise policies for the rule of the great empire that his armies had conquered. He decided that the Arabs were to be a privileged military caste in the regions they had conquered, and that they should live in garrison cities, apart from the natives. The subject peoples were to pay tribute to their Moslem (largely Arab) conquerors, but were otherwise to be left in peace. In particular, they were not to be forcibly converted to Islam. (From the above, it is clear that the Arab conquest was more a nationalist war of conquest than a holy war, although the religious aspect was certainly not lacking.)
Umars achievements are impressive indeed. After Muham- mad himself, he was the principal figure in the spread of Islam. Without his rapid conquests, it is doubtful that Islam would be nearly as widespread today as it actually is. Furthermore, most of the territory conquered during his reign has remained Arab ever since. Obviously, of course, Muhammad, who was the prime mover, should receive the bulk of the credit for those developments. But it would be a grave mistake to ignore Umars contribution. The conquests he made were not an automatic con- sequence of the inspiration provided by Muhammad. Some ex- pansionwas probably bound to occur, but not to the enormous extent that it did under Umars brilliant leadership.
It may occasion some surprise that Umar-a figure virtual- ly unknown in the West-has been ranked higher than such famous men as Charlemagne and Julius Caesar. However, the conquests made by the Arabs under Umar, taking into account both their size and their duration, are substantially more impor- tant than those of either Caesar or Charlemagne. </string>
    <!--fifty3-->
    <string name="fifty3_ASOKA">Asoka, who was probably the most important monarch in the history of India, was the third ruler of the Mauryan dynasty and the grandson of its founder, Chandragupta Maurya. Chan- dragupta was an Indian military leader, who in the years subse- quent to the campaign of Alexander the Great, conquered most of northern India, and thereby established the first major empire in Indian history.
The year of Asokas birth is unknown; probably it was close to 300 B.C. Asoka ascended the throne about 273 B.C. At first he followed in his grandfathers footsteps and sought to extend his territory through military action. In the eighth year of his reign, he concluded a successful war against Kalinga, a state on the east coast of India (about where the present state of Orissa is). But when he realized the horrible human cost of his triumph, Asoka was appalled. One hundred thousand persons had been killed, and an even larger number wounded. Shocked and remorseful, Asoka decided that he would not complete the military conquest of India, but would instead renounce all aggressive warfare. He adopted Buddhism as his religious philosophy, and attempted to practice the virtues of dharma, which include truthfulness, mer- cy, and nonviolence.
On a personal level, Asoka gave up hunting and became a vegetarian. Of more significance were the various humane and political policies that he adopted. He established hospitals and animal sanctuaries, mitigated many harsh laws, built roads, and promoted irrigation. He even appointed special government of- ficials, dharma officers, to instruct people in piety and to en- courage friendly human relationships. All religions were tolerated in his realm, but Asoka particularly promoted Bud- dhism, which naturally enjoyed a great increase in its popularity. Buddhist missions were sent to many foreign countries, and were especially successful in Ceylon.
Asoka ordered descriptions of his life and policies inscribed on rocks and pillars throughout his large realm. Many of these monuments survive to the present day. Their geographic distribution provides us \\lith reliable information concerning the extent of Asokas domain, and the inscriptions on them are our main source of knowledge of his career. Incidentally, these pillars are also considered to be superb works of art.
Within fifty years of Asokas death, the Mauryan Empire fell apart, and it was never revived. However, through his sup- port of Buddhism, Asokas long-term influence upon the world has been very large. When he ascended the throne, Buddhism was a small, local religion, popular only in northwest India. By the time of his death, it had adherents throughout India and was spreading rapidly to neighboring countries. More than anyone man, except Gautama himself, Asoka is responsible for the development of Buddhism into a major world religion. </string>
    <!--fifty4-->
    <string name="fifty4_ST.AUGUSTINE">Augustine, who lived during the declining years of the Roman Empire, was the greatest theologian of his era. His writings pro- foundly influenced Christian doctrines and attitudes throughout the Middle Ages, and indeed still have influence today.
Augustine was born in 354, in the town of Tagaste (now Souk-Ahras, in Algeria), .about forty-five miles south of the large coastal town of Hippo (now Annaba). His father was a pagan; his mother a devout Christian. He was not baptized as an infant.
Even in his adolescence, Augustines intelligence was im- pressive, and at sixteen he was sent to Carthage to study. There he took a mistress and had an illegitimate child. At nineteen, he
 decided to study philosophy. He soon converted to Manichaeism, the religion founded about 240 by the prophet Mani. To the young Augustine, Christianity seemed unsophisticated, while Manichaeism appealed to his reason. However, over the course of the next nine years, he gradually became disillusioned with Manichaeism. When Augustine was twenty-nine, he moved to Rome. A bit later he moved to Milan, in northern Italy, where he became a professor of rhetoric. There he became familiar with Neoplatonism, a modified version of Platos philosophy that had been developed by Plotinus in the third century.
The bishop in Milan at that time was St. Ambrose. Augustine listened to some of his sermons, which introduced him to a new, more sophisticated aspect of Christianity. At the age of thirty-two, Augustine was converted, and the one-time skeptic became an ardent proponent of Christianity. In 387, Augustine was baptized by Ambrose, and soon thereafter he returned home to Tagaste.
In 391, Augustine became the assistant to the bishop of Hip- po. Five years later the bishop died, and Augustine, then forty- two years old, became the new bishop of Hippo. He remained at that post for the rest of his life.
Although Hippo was not an important city, Augustines brilliance was so obvious that he soon became one of the most respected leaders in the church. Although he had a weak con- stitution, with the help of stenographers he was able to compose a large number of religious writings. About 500 of his sermons survive, as do more than 200 of his letters. Of his books, the two most famous and influential are The City of God and his Confes- sions. The latter, which is one of the most famous autobio- graphies ever written, was composed when he was in his forties.
Many of Augustines letters and sermons are devoted to refuting the beliefs of the Manichaeans, the Donatists (a schismatic Christian sect), and the Pelagians (another heretical Christian group of the day). His dispute with the Pelagians forms an important part of Augustines religious doctrines. Pelagius
was an English monk who came to Rome about 400, and there expounded several interesting theological doctrines. We are each, Pelagius claimed, without original sin, and are free to choose good or evil. By righteous living and good works, an in- dividual can attain salvation.
Partly through the influence of St. Augustines writings, the views of Pelagius were declared heretical, and Pelagius himself (who had already been banished from Rome) was excom- municated. According to Augustine, all men are stained with Adams sin. Human beings are unable to attain salvation solely through their own efforts and good works: the grace of God is necessary for salvation. Similar ideas had been expressed
previously; however, Augustine amplified the earlier statements, and his writings solidified the Churchs position on these points, which thereafter became fixed.
Augustine maintained that God already knows who will be saved and who will not, and that some of us are therefore predestined to be saved. This idea of predestination was to great- ly influence later theologians, such as St. Thomas Aquinas and John Calvin.
Probably even more important than the doctrine of predestination were St. Augustines attitudes concerning sex. When he converted to Christianity, Augustine had decided that it was necessary for him to renounce sex. (He once wrote, Nothing is so much to be shunned as sex relations.") However, the actual renunciation proved quite difficult for St. Augustine; both his personal struggle and his views on the subject are described at some length in his Confessions. The views he ex- pressed there, because of Augustines great reputation, exerted a strong influence upon medieval attitudes toward sex. Augustines writings also linked together the notion of original sin and sexual desire.
During Augustines life, the Roman Empire was rapidly declining. In fact, in 410, the city of Rome was sacked by the Visigoths under Alaric. Naturally, the remaining Roman pagans claimed that the Romans were thereby being punished for their desertion of their ancient gods in favor of Christianity. St.ugustines most famous book, The City oj God, is in part a defense of Christianity against that charge. However, the book also includes an entire philosophy of history, one that was to have considerable influence upon later developments in Europe. Augustine expressed the view that the Roman Empire was not of any basic importance, nor was the city of Rome, nor any earthly city. What was really important was the growth of the "heavenly city"-in other words, the spiritual progress of mankind. The vehicle for this progress was, of course, the Church. ("There is no salvation outside the Church.") It therefore followed that
    emperors, whether pagan or Christian or barbarian, were not as important as the Pope and the Church were.
Although Augustine himself did not take the final step, the thrust of his argument leads easily to the conclusion that temporal rulers should be subordinate to the Pope. Medieval popes were glad to draw that conclusion from Augustine, and his
doctrines therefore laid the foundation for the long conflict be- tween Church and State that was to characterize European history for many centuries.
Augustines writings were a factor in the transmission of certain aspects of Greek philosophy to medieval Europe. In particular, Neoplatonism strongly influenced Augustines mature thought, and through Augustine it influenced medieval Christian philosophy. It is also interesting to note that Augustine expressed the idea behind Descartes famous statement, "I think, therefore I am," though in different words, of course.
Augustine was the last great Christian theologian before the Dark Ages, and his writings left Church doctrine, in all its major outlines, in roughly the form it was to keep throughout the Middle Ages. He was the most eminent of the Latin Church fathers, and his writings were widely read by the clergy. His views on salvation, sex, original sin, and many other points were correspondingly influential. Many later Catholic theologians, such as St. Thomas Aquinas, as \vell as Protestant leaders such as Luther and Calvin, were strongly influenced by him.
Augustine died in Hippo, in 430 A .D ., in his seventy-sixth year. The Vandals, one of the barbarian tribes which had invaded the disintegrating Roman Empire, were besieging Hippo at the time. A few months later, they captured the town and burned most of it; however, Augustines library and the cathedral escaped destruction.</string>
    <!--fifty5-->
    <string name="fifty5_WILLIAM_HARVEY">William Harvey, the great English physician who discovered the circulation of the blood and the function of the heart, was born in 1578, in the town of Folkestone, England. Harveys great book, An Anatomical Treatise on the Movement of the Heart and Blood in Animals, published in 1628, has rightly been called the most important book in the entire history of physiology. It is, in fact, the starting point of the modern science of physiology. Its primary importance lies not in its direct applications, but rather in the basic understanding it provides of how the human body works.
For us today, who have been brought up with the knowledge that the blood circulates, and therefore take that fact for granted, Harveys theory seems completely obvious. But what now appears so simple and evident was not obvious at all to earlier biologists. Leading writers on biology had expounded views such as: (a) food is turned into blood in the heart; (b) the heart heats up the blood; (c) the arteries are filled with air; (d) the heart manufactures "vital spirits"; (e) blood in both the veins and the arteries ebbs and flows, sometimes going toward the heart and sometimes away.
Galen, the greatest physician of the ancient world, a man who personally performed many dissections and thought careful- ly about the heart and blood vessels, never suspected that the blood circulates. Nor for that matter did Aristotle, though biol- ogy was one of his major interests. Even after the publication of Harveys book, many physicians were unwilling to accept his idea that the blood in the human body is constantly being recir-
culated through a closed system of blood vessels, with the heart supplying the force to move the blood.
Harvey first formed the notion that the blood circulates by making a simple arithmetic calculation. He estimated that the quantity of blood that was ejected by the heart every time it beat was about two ounces. Since the heart beats about 72 times per minute, simple multiplication led to the conclusion that about 540 pounds of blood were ejected each hour from the heart into the aorta. But 540 pounds far exceeds the total body weight of a normal human being, and even more greatly exceeds the weight of the blood alone. It therefore seemed obvious to Harvey that the same blood was constantly recycled through the heart. Having formulated this hypothesis, he spent nine years perform- ing experiments and making careful observations to determine
the details of the circulation of the blood.
In his book, Harvey clearly stated that the arteries carry
blood away from the heart, while the veins return the blood to the heart. Lacking a microscope, Harvey was unable to see the capillaries, the minute blood vessels that transport the blood from the smallest arteries to the veins, but he correctly inferred their existence. (The capillaries were discovered by the Italian biologist, Malpighi, a few years after Harvey died.)
Harvey also stated that the function of the heart was to pump the blood into the arteries. On this, as on every other major point, Harveys theory was essentially correct. Further- more, he presented a wealth of experimental evidence, with careful arguments to support his theory. Though his theory at first encountered strong opposition, by the end of his life it had been generally accepted.
Harvey also did work on embryology, which, though less important than his research on blood circulation, was not in- significant. He was a careful observer, and his book, On the Generation oj Animals, published in 1651, marks the real beginning of the modern study of embryology. Like Aristotle, by whom he was strongly influenced, Harvey opposed the theory of preformation-the hypothesis that an embryo, even in its earliest stages, had the same overall structure as the adult animal, though on a much smaller scale. Harvey correctly asserted that the final structure of an embryo developed gradually.
Harvey had a long, interesting, and successful life. In his teens, he attended Caius College at the University of Cambridge. In 1600, he went to Italy to study medicine at the University of Padua, at that time perhaps the best medical school in the world. (It might be noted that Galileo was a professor at Padua while Harvey was there, although it is not known whether the two ever met.) Harvey received his medical degree from Padua in 1602. He then returned to England, where he had a long and very suc- cessful career as a physician. Among his patients were two kings of England (James I and Charles I), as well as the eminent philosopher Francis Bacon. Harvey lectured on anatomy at the College of Physicians in London, and in fact was once elected president of the College. (He declined the post.) In addition to his private practice, he was for many years the chief physician at St. Bartholomews Hospital in London. When his book on the circulation of the blood was published, in 1628, it made him famous throughout Europe. Harvey was married, but had no children. He died in 1657, in London, at the age of seventy-nine.
    </string>
    <!--fifty6-->
    <string name="fifty6_ERNEST_RUTHERFORD">Ernest Rutherford is generally considered to have been the great- est experimental physicist of the twentieth century. He is the cen- tral figure in our knowledge of radioactivity, and is also the man who originated the study of nuclear physics. In addition to their enormous theoretical importance, his discoveries have had a wide range of important applications including: nuclear weapons, nu- clear power plants, radioactive tracers, and radioactive dating. His influence on the world has therefore been profound, is probably still growing, and will likely be enduring.
    Rutherford was born and raised in New Zealand. He attended Canterbury College there, obtaining three degrees (B. A., M. A., B.Sc.) by the time he was twenty-three. The following year he was awarded a scholarship to Cambridge University in England, where he spent three years as a research student under J. J. Thomson, one of the leading scientists of the day. When he was twenty-seven he became professor of physics at McGill University in Canada, where he stayed for nine years. He went back to England in 1907 to head the physics department at Manchester University. In 1919 he returned to Cambridge, this time as Director of the Cavendish Laboratory, and he remained there for the rest of his life.
Radioactivity had been discovered in 1896 by the French sci- entist Antoine Henri Becquerel, while he was doing some experi- ments with uranium compounds. But Becquerel soon lost interest in the subject, and most of our basic knowledge in the field comes from Rutherfords extensive research. (Marie and Pierre Curie found two more radioactive elements-polonium and radium-but made no discoveries of fundamental importance.)
One of Rutherfords first findings was that the radioactive emissions from uranium consist of two quite different components, which he called alpha rays and beta rays. He later demonstrated the nature of each component (they consist of fast-moving particles) and showed that there is also a third component, which he called gamma rays.
An important feature of radioactivity is the energy involved. Becquerel, the Curies, and most other scientists had thought that the energy had an external source. But Rutherford proved that the energy involved-which was much greater than that released in chemical reactions-was coming from the interior of the individual uranium atoms! By so dOing, he originated the important concept of atomic energy.
Scientists had always assumed that individual atoms were in- destructible and unchangeable. But Rutherford (with the aide of a very talented young assistant, Frederick Soddy), was able to show that whenever an atom emits alpha or beta rays it is transformed into an atom of a different sort. At first, chemists found this hard to believe; but Rutherford and Soddy worked out the whole series of radioactive decays that transform uranium to lead. He also meas- ured the rates of decay and formulated the important concept of "half-life." This soon led to the technique of radioactive dating, which has become one of the most useful of scientific tools, with important applications in geology, archaeology, astronomy, and many other fields.
This stunning set of discoveries earned Rutherford a Nobel prize in 1908 (Soddy later received a Nobel prize also), but his greatest achievement was yet to come. He had noticed that fast- moving alpha particles could go right through a thin foil of gold (leaving no visible puncture!), although they were slightly deflected by the passage. This suggested that gold atoms, rather than being hard, impenetrable objects, like "tiny billiard balls"-as scientists had previously believed-were soft inside! It seemed as if the smaller, harder alpha particles could go right through the gold atoms like a high-speed bullet going through jello.
But Rutherford (working with Geiger and Marsden, two younger associates) found that some of the alpha particles were sharply deflected when they struck the gold fOil; in fact, some even bounced right back! Rutherford, sensing that something important was involved, had the experiment repeated many times, carefully counting the number of particles scattered in each direction. Then, by a very difficult but utterly convincing mathematical analysis, he showed that there was only one way of explaining the experimental results: A gold atom consisted almost entirely of empty space, with almost all of the atoms mass concentrated in a minute "nucleus" in the center! -
At a single blow, Rutherfords paper (1911) shattered forever our common-sense picture of the world. If even a piece of metal- seemingly the solidest of objects-was mostly empty space, then everything which we had regarded as substantial had suddenly dissolved into tiny specks rushing about in an immense void!
Rutherfords discovery of the atomic nucleus is the foundation of all modern theories of atomic structure. When Niels Bohr, two years later, published his famous paper describing the atom as a miniature solar system governed by quantum mechanics, he used Rutherfords nuclear atom as the starting point of his model. So did Heisenberg and Schrodinger when they constructed their more sophisticated atomic models using matrix mechanics and wave me- chanics.
Rutherfords discovery also led to a new branch of science: the study of the nucleus itself. In this field too, Rutherford proved to be a pioneer. In 1919, he succeeded in transforming nitrogen nu- clei into oxygen nuclei by bombarding them with fast-moving alpha particles. It was an achievement to dazzle the dreams of the ancient alchemists.
It was soon realized that nuclear transformations might be the source of the Suns energy. Furthermore, inducing the transforma- tion of atomic nuclei is the key process in atomic weapons, and also in nuclear power plants. Rutherfords discovery has therefore been of far more than academic interest.
Rutherfords larger than life" personality constantly im- pressed those who met him. He was a big man, with a loud voice, boundless energy and confidence, and a conspicuous lack of mod- esty. When a colleague commented on Rutherfords uncanny abil- ity to always be on the crest of the wave" of scientific research, he replied promptly, Well, why not? After all, I made the wave, didnt I!" Few scientists would disagree with that assessment. </string>
    <!--fifty7-->
    <string name="fifty7_JOHN_CAL_VIN">The famous Protestant theologian and moralist John Calvin is one of the major figures of European history. His views on such diverse subjects as theology, government, personal morality, and work habits have, over a period of more than 400 years, influ- enced the lives of hundreds of millions of people.
John Calvin (original name: Jean Cauvin) was born in 1509, in the town of Noyon, in France. He received a good education. After attending the College de Montaigu in Paris, he went to the University of Orleans to study law. He also studied law at Bourges.
Calvin was only eight years old when Martin Luther posted his Ninety-five Theses on the church door in Wittenberg, and thereby inaugurated the Protestant Reformation. Calvin was brought up as a Catholic, but as a young man he converted to Protestantism. To avoid persecution, he soon left Paris, where he had been living, and after traveling about for a while, settled in Basel, Switzerland. There he lived under a pseudonym while he studied theology intensively. In 1536, when he was twenty-seven years old, he published his best-known work, the Institutes of the Christian Religion. This book, which summarized the essential Protestant beliefs and presented them in comprehensive and systematic form, made him famous.
Later in 1536, he visited Geneva, Switzerland, where Pro- testantism was rapidly gaining in strength. He was asked to stay there as a teacher and leader of the Protestant community. But conflicts soon arose between the fiercely puritanical Calvin and the Genevans, and in 1538, he was forced to leave the city. In 1541, however, he was invited to return. He did so, and he became not only the religiOUS leader of the city, but also its effec- tive political leader until his death in 1564.
In theory, Calvin was never a dictator in Geneva: many of the townspeople had voting rights, and much of the formal political authority was held by a council which consisted of twenty-five persons. Calvin was not a member of this council. He was subject to removal at any time (and was, in fact, expelled in 1538) if he did not have the consent of the majority. In prac- tice, though, Calvin dominated the city, and after 1555 he was a virtual autocrat.
Under Calvins leadership, Geneva became the leading Pro- testant center of Europe. Calvin consistently tried to promote the growth of Protestantism in other countries, particularly in France, and for a while Geneva was referred to as the "Protes- tant Rome." One of the first things that Calvin did after his return to Geneva was to draw up a set of ecclesiastical regula- tions for the Reformed Church there. These were to set a pattern for many other Reformed Churches in Europe. While in Geneva,
. Calvin wrote many influential religious tracts, and continued to revise the Institutes of the Christian Religion. He also gave many lectures on theology and the Bible.
Calvins Geneva was a rather austere and puritanical place. Not only were adultery and fornication considered serious crimes, but gambling, drunkenness, dancing, and the singing of ribald songs were all prohibited, and could result in severe punishment. Attendance at church during prescribed hours was required by law, and lengthy sermons were customary.
Calvin strongly encouraged diligence in work. He also encouraged education, and it was during his administration that the University of Geneva was founded.
Calvin was an intolerant man, and those whom he con- sidered heretics received short shrift in Geneva. His most famous victim (there were quite a few) was Michael Servetus, a Spanish physician and theologian who did not believe in the doctrine of the Trinity. When Servetus came to Geneva, he was arrested, tried for heresy, and burnt at the stake (in 1553). In addition, several persons suspected of witchcraft were burnt at the stake during Calvins administration.
Calvin died in Geneva, in 1564. He had married, but his wife had died in 1549, and their only child had died at birth.
Calvins principal importance lies not in his direct political activities, but rather in the ideology he promulgated. He stressed the authority and importance of the Bible, and like Luther, denied the authority and importance of the Roman Catholic Church. Like Luther, St. Augustine, and St. Paul, Calvin held that all men are sinners, and that salvation comes not through good works, but through faith alone. Particularly striking were Calvins ideas on predestination and reprobation. According to Calvin, God -has already decided-and without regard to merit-who is to be saved and who is to be damned. Why, then, should an individual bother to behave morally? Calvins answer was that the "elect" (that is, those persons whom God has chosen to accept Christ and thereby achieve redemption) have also been selected by God to behave righteously. W e are not saved because we do good, but we do good because we have been chosen for
salvation. Although such a doctrine may seem strange to some, there seems little doubt that it has inspired many Calvinists to lead unusually pious and upright lives.
Calvin has exerted great influence on the world. His theological doctrines ultimately gained even more adherents than Luthers did. Though northern Germany and Scandinavia became predominantly Lutheran, Switzerland and the Nether- lands became Calvinist. There were significant Calvinist minor- ities in Poland, Hungary, and Germany. The Presbyterians in Scotland were Calvinists, as were the Huguenots in France and the Puritans in England. Puritan influence in America, of course, has been both long and strong.
Calvins Geneva may have been more a theocracy than a democracy, but the net effect of Calvinism has nevertheless been to increase democracy. Perhaps the fact that in so many countries the Calvinists were a minority made them inclined to favor restrictions on established power; or perhaps the comparatively democratic internal organization of the Calvinist churches was a factor. Whatever the reason, the original Calvinist strongholds (Switzerland, Holland, and Great Britain) became strongholds of democracy as well.
It has been claimed that Calvinist doctrines were a major factor in the creation of the so-called "Protestant work ethic," and in the rise of capitalism. It is difficult to judge the extent to which that claim is justified. The Dutch, for example, were reputed to be an industrious people long before Calvin had ever been born. On the other hand, it seems unreasonable to assume that Calvins firmly expressed attitude toward hard work had no influence upon his followers. (It might be noted that Calvin did permit the charging of interest, a practice which had been con- demned by most earlier Christian moralists, but one that was im- portant to the development of capitalism.)
How high on this list should Calvin be ranked? The in- fluence of Calvin has been confined primarily to western Europe and North America. Furthermore, it is plain that his influence has been sharply declining during the last century. In any case, much of the credit for the existence of Calvinism has already      assigned to earlier figures such as Jesus, St. Paul, and Luther.
Although the Protestant Reformation was an event of great historical importance, it is plain that Martin Luther was the per- son most responsible for that upheaval. Calvin himself was only one of several influential Protestant leaders who arose after Luther. It is therefore quite clear that Calvin must be ranked far below Luther. On the other hand, Calvin must be ranked well ahead of such philosophers as Voltaire and Rousseau, partly because his influence has extended over twice as long a period as theirs, and partly because his ideas have had such a profound ef- fect on the lives of his followers.</string>
    <!--fifty8-->
    <string name="fifty8_GREGOR_MENDEL">Gregor Mendel is famous today as the man who discovered the basic principles of heredity. During his lifetime, however, he was an obscure Austrian monk and amateur scientist, whose brilliant research was ignored by the scientific world.
Mendel was born in 1822, in the town of Heinzendorf, at that time within the Austrian Empire, but now part of Czecho- slovakia. In 1843, he entered an Augustinian monastery in Brunn, Austria (now Brno, Czechoslovakia). He was ordained a priest in 1847. In 1850, he took an examination for teacher cer- tification. He failed, receiving his lowest marks in biology and geology! Nevertheless, the abbot in charge of his monastery sent Mendel to the University of Vienna, where, from 1851 to 1853, he studied mathematics and science. Mendel never did get a regular teachers license, but from 1854 to 1868, he was a substitute teacher of natural science at the Brunn Modern School.
Meanwhile, starting in 1856, he performed his famous ex- periments in plant breeding. By 1865, he had derived his famous laws of heredity and presented them in a paper given before the Brunn Natural History Society. In 1866, his results were pub- lished in the Transactions of that society, in an article entitled "Experiments with Plant Hybrids." A second article was publish- ed in the same journal three years later. Although the Transac- tions of the Brunn Natural History Society was not a prestigious journal, it was carried by major libraries. In addition, Mendel sent a copy of his paper to Karl Nageli, a leading authority on heredity. Nageli read the paper and replied to Mendel, but failed to comprehend the papers enormous importance. Thereafter, Mendels articles were generally ignored and, indeed, almost forgotten for over thirty years.
In 1868, Mendel was appointed abbot of his chapter, and from then on his administrative duties left him little time to con- tinue his plant experiments. When he died, in 1884, at the age of sixty-one, his brilliant research had been nearly forgotten, and he had received no recognition for it.
Mendels work was not rediscovered until the year 1900, when three different scientists (a Dutchman, Hugo de Vries; a German, Carl Correns; and an Austrian, Erich von Tschermak), working independently, came across Mendels Each of the three men had performed his own botanical experiments; each had independently discovered Mendels Laws; each, before publishing his results, had researched the literature and come across Mendels original article; and each carefully cited Mendels paper and stated that his own work confirmed Mendels conclusions. An astounding triple coincidencel Moreover, in that same year, William Bateson, an English scientist, came across Mendels original article and promptly drew it to the attention of other scientists. By the end of the year, Mendel was receiving the acclaim that he had so richly deserved during his lifetime.
What were the facts about heredity that Mendel discovered? In the first place, Mendel learned that in all living organisms there were basic units, today called genes, by which inherited characteristics were transmitted from parent to offspring. In the plants that Mendel studied, each individual characteristic, such as seed color or leaf shape, was determined by a pair of genes. An individual plant inherited one gene of each pair from each parent. Mendel found that if the two genes inherited for a given trait were different (for example, one gene for green seeds and another gene for yellow seeds) then, normally, only the effect of the dominant gene (in this case for yellow seeds) would manifest itself in that individual. Nevertheless, the recessive gene was not destroyed and might be transmitted to the plants descendants. Mendel realized that each reproductive cell, or gamete (cor- responding to sperm or egg cells in human beings) contained only one gene of each pair. He also stated that it was completely a matter of chance which gene of each pair occurred in an in- dividual gamete and was transmitted to an individual offspring.
Mendels laws, although they have been modified slightly, remain the starting point of the modern science of genetics. How is it that Mendel, an amateur scientist, was able to discover those important principles that had eluded so many eminent profes- sional biologists before him? Fortunately, he had selected for his investigations a species of plant whose most striking character- istics are each determined by a single set of genes. Had the
characteristics he investigated each been determined by several sets of genes, his research would have been immensely more diffi- cult. But this piece of good luck would not have helped Mendel had he not been an extremely careful and patient experimenter, nor would it have helped him had he not realized that it was necessary to make a statistical analysis. of his observations. Because of the random factor mentioned above, it is generally not possible to predict which traits an individual offspring will inherit. Only by performing a large number of experiments (Mendel had recorded results for over 21,000 individual plants!), and by analyzing his results statistically was Mendel able to de- duce his laws. It is obvious that the la\vs of heredity are an important addi- tion to human knowledge, and our knowledge of genetics will probably have even more applications in the future than it has had so far. There is, however, another factor to be considered when deciding where Mendel should be placed. Since his discoveries were ignored during his lifetime, and his conclusions were rediscovered independently by later scientists, Menders re-
search might be deemed expendable. If that argument is pushed to its limit, one might conclude that Mendel should be left off this list entirely, just as Leif Ericson, Aristarchus, and Ignaz Semmelweiss have been omitted in favor of Columbus, Coper- nicus, and Joseph Lister.
There are, however, differences between Mendels case and the others. Mendels work was forgotten only briefly, and once rediscovered, quickly became widely known. Furthermore, de Vries, Correns, and Tschermak, though they rediscovered his principles independently, eventually did read his paper and cite his results. Finally, one cannot rightly say that Mendels work would have had no influence if de Vries, Correns, and Tscher- mak had never lived. Mendels article had already been included in a widely circulated bibliography (by W. O. Focke) of works
on heredity. That listing ensured that sooner or later some serious student in the field would come across Mendels article. It might be noted that none of the other three scientists ever claimed credit for the discovery of genetics; also, the scientific principles discovered are universally referred to as "Mendels Laws."
Mendels discoveries seem comparable, both in originality and importance, with Harveys discovery of the circulation of the blood, and he has been ranked accordingly.</string>
    <!--fifty9-->
    <string name="fifty9_MAX_PLANCK">
In December 1900, the German physicist Max Planck startled the scientific world with his bold hypothesis that radiant energy -(that is, the energy of light waves) is not emitted in a continuous flow, but rather consists of small chunks or lumps, which he called quanta. Plancks hypothesis, which conflicted with the classical theories of light and electromagnetism, provided the starting point for the quantum theories which have since revolu- tionized physics andprovided us with a deeper understanding of the nature of matter and radiation.
Planck was born in 1858, in Kiel, Germany. He studied in the Universities of Berlin and Munich, and received his doctors degree in physics (summa cum laude) from the University of Munich when he was twenty-one years old. For a while he taught at the University of Munich, and then at Kiel University. In 1889, he became a professor at the University of Berlin, where he remained until his retirement in 1928, at the age of seventy.
Planck, like several other scientists, was interested in the subject of black body radiation, which is the name given to the electromagnetic radiation emitted by a perfectly black object when it is heated. (A perfectly black object is defined as one that does not reflect any light, but completely absorbs all light falling on it.) Experimental physicists had already made careful measurements of the radiation emitted by such objects, even before Planck started working on the problem. Plancks first achievement was his discovery of the fairly complicated algebraic formula that correctly describes the black body radi- ation. This formula, which is frequently used in theoretical physics today, neatly summarized the experimental data. But there was a problem: the accepted laws of physics predicted a
quite different formula.
Planck pondered deeply on this problem and finally came
up with a radically new theory: radiant energy is only emitted in exact multiples of an elementary unit that Planck called the quantum. According to Plancks theory, the magnitude of a quantum of light depends on the frequency of the light (i.e., on its color), and is also proportional to a physical quantity that Planck abbreviated h, but that is now called Plancks constant. Plancks hypothesis was quite contrary to the then prevalent con- cepts of physics; however, by using it he was able to find an exact theoretical derivation of the correct formula for blac-k body radiation.
Plancks hypothesis was so revolutionary that it doubtless would have been dismissed as a crackpot idea, had not Planck been well-known as a solid, conservative physicist. Although the hypothesis sounded very strange, in this particular case it did lead to the correct formula.
At first, most physicists (including Planck regarded his hypothesis as no more than a convenient mathematical fic- tion. After a few years, though, it turned out that Plancks concept of the quantum could be applied to various physical phenomena other than black body radiation. Einstein used the concept in 1905 to explain the photoelectric effect, and Niels Bohr used it in 1913 in his theory of atomic structure. By 1918, when Planck was awarded the Nobel Prize, it was clear that his hypothesis was basically correct, and that it was of fundamental importance in physical theory.
Plancks strong anti-Nazi views placed him in considerable danger during the Hitler era. His younger son was executed in early 1945 for his role in the unsuccessful officers plot to assassi- nate Hitler. Planck himself died in 1947, at the age of eighty- nine.
The development of quantum mechanics is probably the most important scientific development of the twentieth century, more important even than Einsteins theories of relativity. Plancks constant, h, plays a vital role in physical theory, and is now recognized as one of the two or three most fundamental physical constants. It appears in the theory of atomic structure, in Heisenbergs uncertainty principle, in radiation theory, and in many scientific formulas. Plancks original estimate of its numerical value was within 2 percent of the figure accepted today.
Planck is generally considered to be the father of quantum mechanics. Although he played little part in the later develop- ment of the theory, it would be a mistake to rank Planck too low. The initial breakthrough which he provided was very important. It freed mens minds from their earlier misconceptions, and it thereby enabled his successors to construct the far more elegant theory we have today.</string>
    <!--sixty-->
    <string name="sixty_JOSEPH_LISTER">Joseph Lister, the British surgeon who introduced the use of an- tiseptic measures in surgery, was born in 1827, in Upton, England. In 1852, he received a medical degree from University College in London, where he had been an excellent student. In 1861, he became surgeon at the Glasgow Royal Infirmary, a posi- tion he was to hold for eight years. It was primarily during this period that he developed his method of antiseptic surgery.
At the Glasgow Royal Infirmary, Lister was in charge of the wards in the new surgical block. He was appalled by the high rate of postoperative mortality that occurred there. Serious infec- tions, such as gangrene, were a common aftermath of surgery. Lister tried to       his wards generally clean; however, this did not prove sufficient to prevent a high mortality rate. Many doc- tors maintained that "miasmas" (noxious vapors) about the hospital were the cause of these infections. However, this ex- planation did not satisfy Lister.
Then, in 1865, he read a paper by Louis Pasteur, which in- troduced him to the germ theory of disease. This provided Lister with his key idea. If infections were caused by microbes, then the best method of preventing postoperative infections would be to kill the microbes before they got into the open wound. Using car- bolic acid as a germ-killer, Lister instituted a new set of antisep- tic procedures. He not only cleaned his hands carefully before every operation, but made sure that the instruments and the dressings that were used were also rendered completely sanitary. Indeed, for a while he even sprayed carbolic acid into the air in the operating room. The result was a dramatic drop in postoperative fatalities. During the period 1861-1865, the postoperative mortality rate in the male accident ward had been 45 percent. By 1869, it had been reduced to 15 percent.
Listers first great paper on antiseptic surgery was published in 1867. His ideas were not immediately accepted. However, he was offered the Chair of Clinical Surgery at Edinburgh Universi- ty in 1869, and during his seven-year stay there his fame spread. In 1875, he toured Germany, lecturing on his ideas and methods; the following year, he made a similar tour in the United States. But the majority of doctors were not yet convinced.
In 1877, Lister was given the Chair of Clinical Surgery at Kings College in London, a position that he held for over fifteen years. His demonstrations of antiseptic surgery in London arous- ed great interest in medical circles, and resulted in increased acceptance of his ideas. By the end of his life, Listers principles of antiseptic surgery had won virtually universal acceptance among physicians.
Lister received many honors for his pioneering work. He was president of the Royal Society for five years, and was Queen Victorias personal surgeon. Married, but childless, Lister lived to be almost eighty-five. He died in 1912, in Walmer, England.
Listers innovations have completely revolutionized the field of surgery, and have saved many millions of lives. Not only do far fewer people die today from postoperative infections, but toda;r surgery saves many persons who would be unwilling to undergo operations if the danger of infection were as great now as it was a century ago. Furthermore, surgeons are now able to undertake complicated operations that they would never have attempted in earlier days, when the risk of infection was so great. A century ago, for example, operations that involved opening the chest cavity were not normally contemplated. Although present-day techniques of aseptic surgery are different from the antiseptic methods that Lister used, they involve the same basic ideas, and are an extension of Listers principles.
One might claim that Listers ideas were such obvious cor- ollaries of Pasteurs that Lister is not entitled to any significant credit. However, despite Pasteurs writings, someone was re- quired to develop and popularize the techniques of antiseptic surgery. Nor does the inclusion of both Lister and Pasteur in this book amount to counting the same discovery twice. The applica- tions of the germ theory of disease are of such significance that, even when the credit is divided up, Pasteur, Leeuwenhoek,
Fleming and Lister all are fully entitled to a place on this list. There is another possible objection to Listers being placed so high on this list. Almost twenty years before Lister did his work, the Hungarian doctor, Ignaz Semmelweiss (1818-1865), working in the Vienna General Hospital, had clearly demonstrated the advantages of antiseptic procedures, both in obstetrics and in surgery. However, although Semmelweiss became a professor and wrote an excellent book setting forth his ideas, he was by and large ignored. It was Joseph Lister whose writings, talks, and demonstrations actually convinced the medical profession of the necessity for antiseptic procedures in
medical practice.</string>
    

</resources>