<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <!--twenty1-->
    <string name="twenty1_CONSTANTINE_THE_GREAT">Constantine the Great was the first Christian emperor of Rome. By his adoption of Christianity, and by his various policies encouraging its growth, he played a major role in transforming it from a persecuted sect into the dominant religion of Europe.
Constantine was born about 280, in the town of Naissus (present day Nis), in what is now Yugoslavia. His father was a high-ranking army officer, and Constantine spent his younger days in Nicomedia, where the court of the Emperor Diocletian was situated.
Diocletian abdicated in 305, and Constantines father, Con- stantius, became the ruler of the western half of the Roman Em-pire. When Constantius died the following year, Constantine was proclaimed emperor by his troops. Other generals, however, disputed his claim, and a series of civil wars followed. These end- ed in 312 when Constantine defeated his remaining rival, Max- entius, at the Battle of the Milvian Bridge, near Rome.
Constantine was now the undisputed ruler of the western half of the Empire; however, another general, Licinius, the eastern half. In 323, Constantine attacked and defeated Licinius also, and from then until his death in 337 was sole ruler of the Roman Empire.
It is uncertain just when Constantine became converted to Christianity. The most usual story is that on the eve of the Battle of the Milvian Bridge, Constantine saw a fiery cross in the sky, together with the words "By this sign shalt thou conquer." Regardless of how or when he was converted, Constantine became deeply dedicated to the advancement of Christianity. One of his early actions was the Edict of Milan, under which Christianity became a legal and tolerated religion. The Edict also
provided for the return of Church property which had been con- fiscated during the preceding period of persecution, and it established Sunday as a day of worship.
The Edict of Milan was not motivated by general feelings of religious toleration. On the contrary, Constantines reign may be said to mark the beginning of the official persecution of the Jews that was to persist in Christian Europe for so many centuries.
Constantine never established Christianity as the official state religion. However, by his legislation and other policies, he did much to encourage its growth. During his reign it became obvious that conversion to Christianity enhanced ones prospects for promotion to a high government position, and his decrees gave the Church various useful privileges and immunities. Also, construction of several of the worlds most famous church buildings-such as the Church of the Nativity in Bethlehem, and the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem-was com- menced during his reign.
Constantines role as the first Christian emperor of Rome
    would by itself entitle him to a place on this list. However, several of his other actions have also had far-reaching conse- quences. For one thing, he rebuilt and greatly expanded the old city of Byzantium, renamed it Constantinople, and made it his capital. Constantinople (which is today called Istanbul) was to become one of the great cities of the world; it remained the capital of the Eastern Roman Empire until 1453, and for cen- turies thereafter was the capital of the Ottoman Empire.
Constantine also played a significant role in the internal history of the Church. To deal with a dispute between the followers of Arius and Athanasius (two Christian theologians who had advanced conflicting doctrines), Constantine convoked the Council of Nicaea (in 325), the first general council of the Church. The council, in which Constantine took an active part, resolved the dispute by its adoption of the Nicene Creed, which became orthodox Church doctrine.
More important still was some of his civil legislation. Con- stantine introduced laws which made certain occupations (e.g., butchers, bakers) hereditary. He also issued a decree under which coloni (a class of tenant farmers) were forbidden to leave their land. In modern terms, this decree converted the coloni into serfs, permanently attached to the land. This and similar legisla- tion helped to lay the foundations for the entire social structure of medieval Europe.
Constantine chose not to be baptized until he was on his deathbed, but it is clear that he had been converted to Chris- tianity long before that. It is equally plain that the spiritual con- tent of Christianity had eluded him completely. Even by the standards of the day, he was ruthless and cruel-and not merely to his enemies. For reasons that are unclear, he had his wife and his eldest son put to death in 326.
It might be argued that Constantines adoption of Chris- tianity did not really change the course of history, but merely ratified the inevitable. After all, although the Emperor Diocle- tian (who ruled 284-305) had conducted a vigorous persecution of Christianity, his attempt to suppress the religion was unsuc-cessful, for by that time Christianity was far too strong to be stamped out by even the fiercest measures. When one considers the failure of Diocletians efforts to extirpate Christianity, one suspects that Christianity might eventually have triumphed even without Constantines intervention.
Such speculations are interesting, but inconclusive. It is hard to be sure what might have happened without Constantine. It is quite plain, though, that with his encouragement, Chris- tianity rapidly expanded in both numbers and influence. From the creed of a small minority it became, within a century, the predominant and established religion of the largest empire on earth.
Clearly, Constantine was one of the great pivotal figures of European history. He has been ranked higher than better known figures such as Alexander the Great, Napoleon, and Hitler because-of the enduring influence of his policies.
    </string>
    <!--twenty2-->
    <string name="twenty2_JAMES_WATT">
The Scottish inventor James Watt, the man who is often describ- ed as the inventor of the steam engine, was the key figure of the Industrial Revolution.
Actually, Watt was not the first man to build a steam engine. Similar devices were described by Hero of Alexandria in the 1st century. In 1698, Thomas Savery patented a steam engine that was used for pumping water, and in 1712 an Englishman, Thomas Newcomen, patented a somewhat improved version. Still, the Newcomen engine had such a low efficiency that it was useful only for pumping water out of coal mines.
Watt himself became interested in the steam engine in 1764, while repairing a model of Newcomens device. Watt, although he had received only one years training as an instrument maker, had great inventive talent. The improvements \vhich he made upon Newcomens invention were so important that it is fair to consider W att the inventor of the first practical steam engine.
Watts first great improvement, which he patented in 1769,was the addition of a separate condensing chamber. He also in- sulated the steam cylinder, and in 1782 he invented the double- acting engine. Together with some smaller improvements, these innovations resulted in an         in the efficiency of the steam engine by a factor of four or more. In practice, this increase of ef- ficiency meant the difference between a clever but not really very useful device, and an instrument of enormous industrial utility.
Watt also invented (in 1781) a set of gears for converting the reciprocal motion of the engine into a rotary motion. This device greatly increased the number of uses to which steam engines could be put. Watt also invented a centrifugal governor (1788), by which the speed of the engine could be automatically con- trolled; a pressure gauge (1790); a counter; an indicator; and a throttle valve, in addition to various other improvements.
Watt himself did not have a good head for business. However, in 1775 he formed a partnership with Matthew Boulton, who was an engineer and a very capable businessman. Over the next twenty-five years, the firm of Watt and Boulton manufactured a large number of steam engines, and both part- ners became wealthy men.
It would be difficult to exaggerate the importance of the steam engine. True, there were many other inventions which played a role in the Industrial Revolution. There were developments in mining, in metallurgy, and in many sorts of in- dustrial machinery. A few of the inventions, such as the fly shut- tle (John Kay, 1733) or the spinning jenny (James Hargreaves, 1764) had even preceded Watts work. The majority of the other inventions, however, represented small improvements, and no one of them alone was vital to the Industrial Revolution. It was quite different with the steam engine, which played an absolute- ly crucial role, and without which the Industrial Revolution would have been vastly different. Previously, although some use had been made of windmills and waterwheels, the main source of power had always been human muscles. This factor severely limited the productive capacity of industry. With the invention
    of the steam engine, however, this limitation was removed. Large quantities of energy were now available for production, which accordingly increased enormously. The oil embargo of 1973 made us aware of how severely a shortage of energy can
    hamper an industrial system, and this experience might, in some slight degree, give us an idea of the importance to the Industrial Revolution of W atts inventions.
Aside from its usefulness as a source of power for factories, the steam engine had many other important applications. By 1783, the Marquis de Jouffroy dAbbans had successfully used a steam engine to power a boat. In 1804, Richard Trevithick built the first steam locomotive. Neither of those early models was
    commercially successful. Within a few decades, however, the steamboat and the railroad were to revolutionize both land and water transportation.
The Industrial Revolution occurred at about the same time in history as the American and French revolutions. Though it might not have seemed obvious at the time, today we can see that the Industrial Revolution was destined to have a far greater im- pact on the daily lives of human beings than either of those im- portant political revolutions. James Watt, accordingly, has been one of the most influential persons in history.
    </string>
    <!--twenty3-->
    <string name="twenty3_MICHAEL_FARADAY">This is the age of electricity. It is true that our era is sometimes called the space age and sometimes called the atomic age; however, space travel and atomic weapons, whatever their potential importance, have relatively little impact upon our everyday lives. But we use electrical devices constantly. In fact, it seems safe to say that no technological feature so completely permeates the modern world as does the use of electricity.
Many men have contributed to our mastery of electricity: Charles Augustine de Coulomb, Count Alessandro Volta, Hans Christian Oersted, and Andre Marie Ampere are among the Inost important. But towering far above the others are two great British scientists, Michael Faraday and James Clerk Maxwell. Though the work of the two men was in part complementary, they were in no sense collaborators, and each mans individual achievements entitle him to a high place on this list.
Michael Faraday was born in 1791, in Newington, England. He came from a poor family and was largely self-educated. Ap- prenticed to a bookbinder and bookseller at the age of fourteen, he used the opportunity to read extensively. When he was twen- ty, he attended lectures given by the famous British scientist, Sir Humphry Davy, and was fascinated. He wrote to Davy, and eventually got a job as his assistant. Within a few years, Faraday was making important discoveries of his own. Although he lack- ed a good background in mathematics, as an experimental physicist he \vas unsurpassed.
Faradays first important innovation in electricity was made in 1821. Two years earlier, Oersted had found that the needle of an ordinary magnetic compass would be deflected if an electric current flowed in a nearby wire. This suggested to Faraday that if the magnet \vere to be held fixed, the wire might move instead.
Working on this hunch, he succeeded in constructing an in- genious device, in which a wire would rotate continuously in the vicinity of a magnet as long as an electric current flowed through the wire. In fact, what Faraday had invented was the first elec- tric motor, the first device to use an electric current to make a material object move. Primitive as it was, Faradays invention was the ancestor of all the electric motors in use in the world to- day.
This was a tremendous breakthrough. However, its prac- tical usefulness was limited, as long as there was no method of generating electric currents other than the primitive chemical batteries of the day. Faraday was convinced that there must be some way of using magnetism to generate electricity, and he kept looking for such a method. Now, a stationary magnet will not in-duce an electric current in a nearby wire. But in 1831, Faraday discovered that if a magnet is passed through a closed loop of wire, a curre.nt will flow in the wire while the magnet is moving. This effect is called electromagnetic induction, and the discovery of the law governing it ("Faradays law") is generally considered to be Faradays greatest single achievement.
This was a monumental discovery, for two reasons. First, Faradays law is of fundamental importance in our theoretical understanding of electromagnetism. Second, electromagnetic in- duction can be used to generate continuous electric currents, as Faraday himself demonstrated by building the first electric dynamo. Although the modern electric generators that supply power to our cities and factories are far more sophisticated than Faradays device, they are all based on the same principle of elec- tromagnetic induction.
Faraday also made contributions to the field of chemistry. He devised methods for liquefying gases, and he discovered various chemical substances, including benzene. Of greater im- portance is his work in electrochemistry (the study of chemical effects of electric currents). Faradays careful experiments established the two laws of electrolysis which are named after him, and which form the foundations of electrochemistry. He also popularized much of the important terminology used in that field, such as anode, cathode, electrode, and ion.
It was Faraday who introduced into physics the important idea of magnetic lines of force and electric lines of force. By emphasizing not the magnets themselves but rather the field be- tween them, he helped prepare the way for many advances in modern physics, including Maxwells equations. Faraday also discovered that if polarized light is passed through a magnetic field, its polarization will be altered. This discovery is significant, because it was the first indication that there is a relationship be- tween light and magnetism.
Faraday was not only brilliant, but also handsome, and he was a very popular lecturer on science. Nevertheless, he was modest and singularly indifferent to fame, money, and honors.lIe declined, a knighthood, and also declined an offer to become president of the British Royal Society. He had a long, happy l11ar- riage, but no children. He died in 1867, near London.</string>
    <!--twenty4-->
    <string name="twenty4_JAMES_CLERK_MAXWELL">The great British physicist James Clerk Maxwell is best known for his formulation of the set of four equations that express the basic laws of electricity and magnetism.
Those two fields had been investigated extensively for many years before Maxwell, and it was well known that they were closely related. However, although various laws of electricity and magnetism had been discovered that were true in special cir- cumstances, before Maxwell there was no overall, unified theory. In his set of four short (though highly sophisticated)equations, Maxwell was able to describe exactly the behavior and interaction of the electric and magnetic fields. By so doing, he transformed a confusing mass of phenomena into a single, com- prehensive theory. Maxwells equations have been employed ex- tensively for the past century in both theoretical and applied science.
The great virtue of Maxwells equations is that they are general equations, which hold under all circumstances. All the previously known laws of electricity and magnetism can be derived from Maxwells equations, as well as a large number of other, previously unknown results.
The most important of these new results was deduced by Maxwell himself. From his equations it can be shown that periodic oscillations of the electromagnetic field are possible. Such oscillations, called- electromagnetic waves, when once started \vill propagate outward through space. From his equa- tions, Maxwell was able to show that the speed of such elec- tromagnetic waves would be approximately 300,000 kilometers (186,000 miles) per second. Maxwell recognized that this was the same as the measured speed of light. From this, he correctly con- cluded that light itself consists of electromagnetic waves.
Thus, Maxwells equations are not only the basic laws of electricity and magnetism, but are also the basic laws of optics! Indeed, all the previously known laws of optics can be deduced from his equations, as well as many facts and relationships previously undiscovered.
Visible light is not the only possible type of electromagnetic radiation. Maxwells equations indicated that other elec- tromagnetic waves, differing from visible light in their wavelength and frequency, might exist. These theoretical con- clusions were later spectacularly confirmed by Heinrich Hertz, who was able both to produce and to detect the invisible waves whose existence Maxwell had predicted. A few years later,
Guglielmo Marconi demonstrated that those invisible waves could be employed for wireless communication, and radio became a reality. Today, we use them for television as well.X-rays, gamma rays, infrared rays, and ultraviolet rays are other examples of electromagnetic radiation. All can be studied by means of Maxwells equations.Although Maxwells primary fame rests on his spectacular contributions to electromagnetism and optics, he made impor- tant contributions to many other fields of science, including astronomical theory and thermodynamics (the study of heat). One of his special interests was the kinetic theory of gases. Max- well realized that not all of the molecules of a gas move at the same speed. Some molecules move slowly, some rapidly, some at
    extremely high speeds. Maxwell worked out the formula which specifies (for any given temperature) what fraction of the molecules of a given gas will be moving at any specified velocity. This formula, called "the Maxwell distribution," is one of the most widely used of scientific equations, and has important ap- plications in many branches of physics.·
Max\vell was born in 1831, in Edinburgh, Scotland. He was extremely precocious: when only fifteen years old he presented a scientific paper to the Edinburgh Royal Society. He attended the University of Edinburgh and graduated from Cambridge University. Maxwell spent most of his adult life as a college pro- fessor, his last position being at Cambridge. He was married, but had no children. Maxwell is generally considered to be the greatest theoretical physicist in the whole interval between Newton and Einstein. His brilliant career was ended premature- ly, in 1879, \vhen he died of cancer, shortly before his forty- eighth birthday.</string>
    <!--twenty5-->
    <string name="twenty5_MARTIN_LUTHER">Martin Luther, the man whose defiance of the Roman Catholic Church inaugurated the Protestant Reformation, was born in 1483, in the town of Eisleben, in Germany. He received a good university education, and for a while (apparently at his fathers suggestion) he studied law. However, he did not complete his legal education, but instead chose to become an Augustinian monk. In 1512, he received the degree of Doctor of Theology from the University of Wittenberg, and soon thereafter joined its faculty.
Luthers grievances against the Church arose gradually. In 1510, he had taken a trip to Rome, and had been shocked at the venality and worldliness of the Roman clergy. But the immediate issue that stimulated his protest was the Church practice of sell- ing indulgences. (An indulgence was a remission, granted by the Church, of the penalties for sin; it might include a reduction of the time that a sinner would have to spend in purgatory.) On Oc- tober 31, 1517, Luther posted on the door of the church at Wit- tenberg his celebrated Ninety-five Theses, in which he strongly denounced Church venality in general, and the practice of sell- ing indulgences in particular. Luther sent a copy of his Ninety- five Theses to the Archbishop of Mainz. In addition, the Theses were printed, and copies were widely distributed in the area.
The scope of Luthers protests against the Church rapidly broadened, and he soon came to deny the authority of the Pope, and of general Church councils, insisting that he would be guid- ed only by the Bible and by plain reason. Not surprisingly, the Church did not look kindly upon these views. Luther was sum- moned to appear before Church officials, and after various hear- ing and orders to recant, he was finally pronounced a heretic and an outlaw by the Diet of Worms (1521), and his writings \vere proscribed.
The normal outcome \vould have been for Luther to be burned at the stake. However, his views had found widespread support among the German people, and among quite a fe\v of the German princes. Though Luther had to go into hiding for a period of about a year, his support in Germany was strong enough to enable him to avoid any serious criminal penalties.
Luther was a prolific author, and many of his writings proved widely influential. One of his most important works was a translation of the Bible into German. This, of course, made it possible for any literate person to study the Scriptures himself, without relying on the Church or its priests. (Incidentally, the superb prose of Luthers translation had an enormous influence on German language and literature.)
Luthers theology, of course, cannot be fully described in a short space. One of his key ideas was the doctrine of justification by faith alone, an idea derived from the writings of St. Paul. Luther believed that man was by nature so tarnished with sin that good works alone could not save him from eternal damna- tion. Salvation comes only through faith, and only by the grace of God. If this were so, it was obvious that the Church practice of selling indulgences was improper and ineffective. Indeed, the traditional view that the Church was the necessary mediator be- tween the individual Christian and God was in error. If one followed Luthers doctrines, the whole raison detre of the Roman Catholic Church was wiped out at a stroke.
In addition to questioning the essential role of the Church, Luther also protested against a variety of specific Church beliefs and practices. For example, he denied the existence of purgatory, and he denied that the clergy should be celibate. He himself, in 1525, married a former nun, and they had six children together. Luther died in 1546 while on a visit to his home-town of Eisleben.
Martin Luther, of course, was not the first Protestant thinker. He had been preceded a century earlier by Jan Hus in Bohemia, and by the fourteenth-century English scholar John Wycliffe. Indeed, the twelfth-century Frenchman Peter Waldo might well be considered an early Protestant. But the effect of each of those earlier movements had been basically local. By 1517, however, discontent with the Catholic Church was so com- mon that Luthers words promptly ignited a chain of protests that spread rapidly through a large part of Europe. Luther, therefore, is rightly considered to be the man chiefly responsible for the commencement of the Reformation.
The most obvious consequence of the Reformation, of course, is the formation of the various Protestant sects. While Protestantism is only one branch of Christianity, and not the most numerous branch at that, it still has more adherents than Buddhism, or, in fact, than most other religions.
A second important consequence of the Reformation was the widespread religious warfare in Europe which followed it. Some of these religious wars (for example, the Thirty Years War in Germany, which lasted from 1618 to 1648) were incredibly bloody. Even aside from the wars, political conflicts between Catholics and Protestants were to playa major role in European politics for the next fe\v centuries.
The Reformation also played a subtle but very important role in the intellectual development of western Europe. Before
1517, there had been a single established church, the Roman Catholic Church, and dissenters were branded as heretics. Such an atmosphere was certainly not conducive to independent thinking. After the Reformation, as various countries accepted the principle of freedom of religious thought, it became safer to speculate on other subjects as well.
Another point is perhaps worth noting. More persons on this list come from Great Britain than from any other country. Ger- mans are the next most numerous people. Indeed, the list as a whole is strongly dominated by persons coming from the Protes- tant countries of northern Europe and America. However, one notices that only two of those persons (Gutenberg and Charlemagne) lived before 1517. Prior to that date, most of the persons on this list came from other parts of the world, and the peoples living in what are now Protestant countries made a com- paratively small contribution to human culture and history. This obviously suggests that Protestantism or the Reformation n1ay in some way be responsible for the fact that there have been such a large number of eminent persons from these regions in the last 450 years. Perhaps the greater intellectual freedom existing in these areas has been an important factor.
Luther was not without his faults. Though himself a rebel against religious authority, he could be extremely intolerant of those who disagreed with him on religious matters. Possibly, it was partly due to the example set by Luthers intolerance that the religious wars were far fiercer and bloodier in Germany than they were, say, in England. In addition, Luther was ferociously anti-Semitic, and the extraordinary viciousness of his writings about the Jews may have helped to pave the way for the Hitler era in twentieth-century Germany. Luther frequently stressed the importance of obedience to lawful civil authority. Probably, his principal motivation for this was his objection to the Churchs interfering in civil government. (It should be borne in mind that the Reformation was not just a theological dispute. To a considerable extent, it was a nationalist German revolt against the influence of Rome, and it was partly for this reason that Luther received so much support from Ger- man princes.) Regardless of Luthers intentions, however, his statements seem to have led many German Protestants to accept absolutism in political matters. In this way, too, Luthers writings may have helped prepare the way for the Hitler era.
Some people may question why Martin Luther is not placed even higher on this list. In the first place, although Luther may seem very important to Europeans and Americans, he seems far less important to the inhabitants of Asia and Africa, relatively few of whom are Christians. As far as most Chinese, Japanese, or Indians are concerned, the differences between Catholics and Protestants are quite insignificant. (Similarly, not many Euro- peans are interested in the differences between the Sunni and the Shiite branches of Islam.) In the second place, Luther is a com- paratively recent figure in history, and has influenced a much smaller span of human history than have Muhammad, Buddha, or Moses. Furthermore, during the past few centuries religious belief has been declining in the West, and the influence of religion on human affairs is likely to be far smaller during the next thousand years than it was during the preceding thousand. If religious belief continues to decline, Luther is apt to appear far less important to future historians than he does today.
Finally, one should remember that the religious disputes of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries did not, in the long run, affect as many persons as did the scientific advances which occurred during the same period. That is the main reason why Luther has been ranked behind Copernicus (who was his contem- porary), even though Luther played a larger individual role in the Protestant Reformation than Copernicus played in the scientific revolution.</string>
    <!--twenty6-->
    <string name="twenty6_GEORGE_WASHINGTON">George Washington was born in 1732, in Wakefield, Virginia. The son of a wealthy planter, he inherited a substantial estate when he was twenty years old. From 1753 to 1758, Washington served in the army, taking an active part in the French and In- dian War, and gaining military experience and prestige. He returned to Virginia in late 1758, and resigned his commission. Shortly thereafter, he married Martha Dandridge Custis, a weal- thy widow with two children. (He had no children of his own.)
Washington spent the next fifteen years managing his estates, and did so in a very capable fashion. By 1774, when he was chosen as a delegate from Virginia to the First Continental Congress, he was one of the richest men in the colonies. Washington had not been an early advocate of independence; nevertheless, in June 1775, the Second Continental Congress (of which he was also a member) unanimously chose him to com- mand the Continental armies. His military experience; his wealth and reputation; physical appearance (he was a well-built man, 62" in height) and tough constitution; his administrative talents; and, above all, his determination and strength of charac- ter made him the logical choice for that position. Throughout the war, he served without pay, and with exemplary dedication.
W ashingtons most significant achievements were ac- complished between June 1775, when he took command of the Continental armies, and March 1797, when his second term as President ended. He died at his home in Mount Vernon, Virginia, in December 1799.
Washingtons position as the predominant figure in the establishment of the United States of America derives from three important roles which he played.
First, he was the successful military leader in the American War of Independence. It is true that Washington was by no means a military genius. Certainly, he was not remotely in the class of generals such as Alexander the Great or Julius Caesar, and his ultimate success seems to have been due at least as much to the astonishing incompetence of the British commanders who opposed him as to his own abilities. Nevertheless, it should be remembered that several other American commanders were severely defeated, while Washington, though he suffered several small defeats, managed to prosecute the war to a successful con- clusion.
Second, Washington was the president of the Constitutional Convention. Although Washingtons ideas did not playa major role in shaping the American Constitution, his support, and the prestige of his name, played a major role in the ratification of that document by the state governments. There was, at the time, considerable opposition to the new Constitution, and had it not been for Washingtons influence, it is far from certain that it would have been adopted.
In the third place, Washington was the first President of the United States of America. The United States was fortunate in- deed in having as its first president a man of the caliber and character of George Washington. As can be seen from the history of many South American and African nations, it is all too easy for a new nation-even if it starts out with a democratic constitution-to soon degenerate into a military dictatorship. While Washington was a firm enough leader to keep the new na- tion from disintegrating, he had no ambition to hold power in- definitely. He did not wish to be either a king or a dictator, and he set a precedent for the peaceful relinquishment of power-a precedent which has been followed in the United States to this day.
George Washington was not as original and incisive a thinker as some of the other American leaders of the day, such as Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, Alexander Hamilton, and Benjamin Franklin. Nevertheless, he was far more important than any of those more brilliant men; for Washington, both in war and in peace, supplied the vital ingredient of executive leadership, without which no political movement can succeed. Madisons contribution to the formation of the United States of America was important; Washingtons was well-nigh indispen- sable.
George Washingtons place on this list depends to a large ex-tent on ones view of the historical importance of the United States of America. An impartial estimate of that importance is naturally difficult for a contemporary American to make. Although the United States attained, in the mid-twentieth cen- tury, a position of military strength and political influence even greater than that possessed by the Roman Empire at its height, its political power may not endure as long as Romes did. On the other hand, it seems clear that several of the technological developments achieved in the United States will be considered of great significance by other cultures and in other times. The in- vention of the airplane, for example, and the landing of men on the moon represent achievements that past ages have dreamed about, and it seems inconceivable that the invention of nuclear
weapons will ever be deemed an unimportant development. Since George Washington is the American political figure who roughly corresponds to Augustus Caesar in Rome, it seems reasonable to rank him fairly close to Augustus on this list. If Washington has been ranked somewhat lower, it is principally because the period of his leadership was so much briefer than that of Augustus, and because so many other men (such as Thomas Jefferson and James Madison) also played important
roles in the formation of the United States of America. However, Washington ranks higher than such figures as Alexander the Great and Napoleon because his accomplishments have been so much more enduring.</string>
    <!--twenty7-->
    <string name="twenty7_KARL_MARX">Karl Marx, the principal originator of "scientific socialism," was born in 1818, in the town of Trier, Germany. His father was a lawyer, and at seventeen Karl entered the University of Bonn to study law himself. Later, however, he transferred to the University of Berlin, and he eventually was awarded a Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Jena.
Marx then turned to journalism, and for a while he was the editor of the Rheinische Zeitung in Cologne. But his radical politi- cal views soon got him into trouble, and he moved to Paris. There he met Friedrich Engels, and the close personal and political friendship they formed was to endure for the rest of their lives. Though each wrote several books in his own nmne, their intellec-tual collaboration was so close that their combined output can rea- sonably be treated as a single joint achievement. Indeed, Marx and Engels are being treated as a joint entry in this book, though listed under Marxs n,ame alone, as he is generally (and I think rightly) considered to have been the dominant partner.
Marx was soon expelled from France, and he then moved to Brussels. It was there, in. 1847, that he published his first signifi- cant work, The Poverty ofPhilosophy. The following year, he and Engels co-authored the Communist Manifesto, their most Widely read work. Later that year, Marx returned to Cologne, but was
expelled in a matter of months. He then moved to London, where he spent the rest of his life.
Although he earned some money as a journalist, :Marx spent the bulk of his time in London doing research and writing books on politics and economics. (During those years, Marx and his fam- ily were supported primarily by generous contributions from En- gels.) The first volume ofDas Kapital, Marxs most important work, appeared in 1867. When Marx died, in 1883, the other two vol-
umes had not yet been completed; they were edited and published by Engels from the notes and manuscripts that       left behind. Marxs writings form the theoretical basis of Communism, as well as many modern forms of socialism. At the time Marx died,
no country had yet put his ideas into practice. In the century since then, however, Communist governments were established in many places, including Russia and China; and in dozens of other coun- tries movements based on his teachings have arisen and have at- tempted to gain power. The activities of those Marxist parties-
activities which have included propaganda, assassinations, terror- ism, and rebellions in order to achieve power, plus wars, brutal repression, and bloody purges after reaching power-kept the world in turmoil for decades and have caused roughly 100 million deaths! No philosopher in history has had so great an impact on the world in the century after he wrote. You may believe-as I
do-that Marxism has been a disaster, both economically and polit- ically; but surely it has not been an insignificant movement. In- deed, the only reason Marx has not been ranked even higher in this book is that he must share the credit--or rather, the blame-for what has occurred with many other persons, including such notable figures as Lenin, Stalin, and :Mao Zedong.
In view of the foregoing, it is clear that Marx deserves a high place on this list. The question is, how high should he be ranked? Even if one acknowledges the enormous influence that Commu- nism has had, one may still question the importance of       him- self within the Communist movement. The actual conduct of the Soviet government was never rigidly controlled by the works of
Marx. He wrote about concepts such as the Hegelian dialectic and the surplus value of labor, and such abstractions seem to have had little effect on the day-to-day policies of the Hussian or Chinese governments.
It has often been pointed out that the Marxist theory of eco- nomics is badly in error. Certainly, many of Marxs specific predic- tions have turned out to be incorrect. For example, he predicted that in capitalistic countries the working people would become progressively poorer as time went on; clearly, this has not hap- pened. Marx also predicted that the middle class would be elimi- nated, with most of its members falling back into the proletariat, and only a few rising into the capitalist class. Obviously, this has not happened either. He also seemed to believe that increased mechanization would diminish the profits of the capitalists, a pre- diction that is not only wrong, but seems quite foolish. \Vhether
his economic theories are right or wrong, however, has little to do with Marxs influence. A philosophers importance lies not in the correctness of his views, but in whether his ideas move people to action. Judged on that basis, Marx was unquestionably ofenormous importance.
Marxist movements have generally stressed four main ideas: (1) A few rich persons live in great wealth, while most workers live in comparative poverty. (2) The way to rectify this injustice is to set up a socialist system; that is, a system where the means of production are owned by the government rather than by private individuals. (3) In most cases, the only practical way to establish this system is by a violent revolution. (4) To preserve this socialist system, the dictatorship of the Communist party must be main- tained for a considerable time.Each of the first three ideas had been clearly stated long be- fore Marx. The fi)urth statement is derived in part from Marxs idea of "the dictatorship of the proletariat." However, the duration of the Soviet dictatorship appears to have been more a result of the practices of Lenin and Stalin than of the writings of Marx. It has therefore been claimed by some that       s influence on Communism has been more nominal than real, and that the re- spect paid to his writings is mere window dressing, an attempt to
claim "scientific" justification for ideas and policies that would have been adopted anyway.
While there is some truth in such claims, they are surely much too extreme. Lenin, for example, did not merely claim to follow Marxs teachings; he had actually read them, fully accepted them, and believed that he was following them. The same is true of Mao Zedong and of many other Communist leaders. True, Marxs ideas may have been misunderstood or reinterpreted; how- ever, the same could be said for the ideas of Jesus, Buddha, or Muhammad. If all the main policies of the various Marxist govern- ments and movements had been directly derived from the writings of Karl Marx, he would be even higher on this list.
Some of Marxs ideas-for example, his interesting notion of "the economic interpretation of history"-are apt to remain influ- ential even if CommuniSlll itself dies out. Plainly, though, a major factor in deciding how high :Marx should be ranked will be ones estimate of the importance of Communism in the long-term history of the world. A century after Marxs death, there were well over a billion persons who were at least nominally his followers. This was a greater number of adherents than any other ideology has ever had-not just in absolute numbers, but also as a fraction of the total world population. That fact led many Communists to hope (and anti-Communists to fear) that the future might well see the eventual worldwide triumph of Marxism.
In the first edition of this book I wrote, "though one cannot be sure just how far Communism will go and just how long it will last, it should be apparent by now that the ideology is solidly             and will be a major influence in the world for at least a few centuries to come." It now appears that that estimate was unduly pessimistic. With the renunciation ofCommunism by Rus- sia, by the other republics of the former Soviet Union, and by most of the countries that had been client states of the Soviet Union, the role of Marxism in the world has declined precipitously over
the past few years; and one certainly gets the impression that that decline is irreversible.
If that is indeed the case-and I suspect that it is-then it would seem that the interval during which Marxism was a major force will turn out to be only about a century, rather than many centuries. The overall influence of Karl Marx will therefore be a good deal less than I had estimated in the first edition of this book. Even then, he will still be a significantly more important figure than either Napoleon or Hitler: The impact of those men was both briefer than Marxs and less extensive geographically.</string>
    <!--twenty8-->
    <string name="twenty8_ORVILLE_WRIGHT_and_WILBUR_WRIGHT">Since the achievements of these two brothers are so closely inter- hvined, they have been combined as a single entry, and their stories will be told together. Wilbur Wright was born in 1867, in Millville, Indiana. Orville Wright, his brother, was born in
1871, in Dayton, Ohio. Both boys received high school educa- tions, although neither actually received his diploma.
Both boys were mechanically gifted, and both were in- terested in the subject of manned flight. In 1892, they opened a shop where they sold, repaired, and manufactured bicycles. This provided funds for their overriding interest, which was aeronautical research. They eagerly read the writings of other workers in aeronautics - Otto Lilienthal, Octave Chanute, and Samuel P. Langley. In 1899, they started working on the pro- blem of flight themselves. By December 1903, after a little more than four years work, their efforts were crowned with success.
One may wonder why the Wright brothers were able to suc- ceed where so many others had failed. There were several reasons for their success. In the first place, two heads are much better than one. The Wright brothers always worked together and cooperated perfectly with each other. In the second place, they wisely decided that they would first learn how to fly before attempting to build a powered airplane. This sounds a bit paradoxical: how can you learn to fly unless you first have an airplane? The answer is that the Wright brothers learned how to fly by using gliders. They started working with kites and gliders in 1899. The next year, they brought their first full-scale glider (that is, large enough to carry a man) to Kitty Hawk, in North Carolina, to test it out. It was not too satisfactory. They built and tested a second full-scale glider in 1901, and a third in 1902. The third glider incorporated some of their most important innova- tions. (Some of their basic patents, applied for in 1903, relate to that glider rather than to their first powered plane.) In the third glider, they made more than a thousand successful flights. The Wright brothers were already the best and most experienced glider pilots in the world before they started to build a powered aircraft.

Their experience with glider flights provides a third clue to their success. Most persons who had previously attempted to con- struct airplanes had worried chiefly about how to get their con- traptions off the ground. The Wright brothers correctly realized that the biggest problem would be how to control the aircraft after it was in the air. They therefore spent most of their time and effort designing ways to maintain the stability and control of the aircraft during flight. They succeeded in devising means for three-axis control of their craft, and this enabled them to achieve
complete maneuverability.
The Wright brothers also made important contributions to
wing design. They soon realized that the previously published data on this subject were unreliable. They therefore built their own wind tunnel, and in it tested more than two hundred dif- ferently shaped wing surfaces. On the basis of these experiments, they were able to construct their own tables describing how the pressure of the air upon a wing depended on the wing shape. This information was then used to design wings for their aircraft.
 Despite all these achievements, the Wright brothers could not have succeeded if they had not appeared at the right moment in history. Attempts at powered flight in the first half of the nine- teenth century were inevitably doomed to failure. Steam engines were simply too heavy in proportion to the power that they pro- duced. By the time the Wright brothers came along, efficient in- ternal combustion engines had already been invented. However, those internal combustion engines in common use had far too high a ratio of weight to power to be usable in a flying machine. As no manufacturer seemed able to design an engine with a low enough weight-to-power ratio, the Wright brothers (with the help of a mechanic) designed their own. It is an indication of their genius that, although they spent relatively little time on the design of the engine, they ·were still able to construct an engine superior to those which most manufacturers could design. In ad- dition, the Wright brothers had to design their own propellers. The one that they used in 1903 had about a 66 percent efficiency.
The first flight was made on December 17, 1903, at Kill Devil Hill, near Kitty Hawk, North Carolina. The brothers each made two flights on that day. The first flight, made by Orville Wright, lasted 12 seconds and covered 120 feet. The final flight, made by Wilbur Wright, lasted 59 seconds and covered 852 feet. Their plane, which they called the Flyer I (it is today popularly called the Kitty Hawk), cost less than a thousand dollars to build. It had a wing span of about 40 feet and weighed about 750 pounds. It had a 12-horsepower engine, which weighed only 170 pounds. Incidentally, the original airplane is now in the National Air and Space Museum, in Washington, D.C.
Although there were five witnesses to those first flights, relatively few newspapers reported it the next day (and generally not very accurately). Their hometown paper in Dayton, Ohio, ignored it completely. It \vas, in fact, almost five years before it was generally realized in the world at large that manned flight had actually been achieved.
After their flights at Kitty Hawk, the Wright brothers returned to Dayton, where they built a second airplane, the Flyer II. They made 105 flights in that airplane in 1904, without,however, attracting much attention. Flyer Ill, an improved and very practical model, was built in 1905. Even though they had made many flights near Dayton, most people still did not believe that the airplane had been invented. In 1906, for example, the Paris edition of the Herald Tribune carried an article on the Wright brothers with the headline "Flyers or Liars?"
In 1908, however, the Wright brothers put an end to the publics doubts. Wilbur Wright took one of their planes to France, gave a series of public demonstrations of the aircraft in action, and organized a company there to market their inven- tion. Meanwhile, back in the United States, Orville Wright was giving similar public displays. Unfortunately, on September 17, 1908, the plane he was flying crashed. It was the only serious ac- cident that either of them ever had. A passenger was killed, and Orville broke a leg and two ribs, but recovered. His successful flights, however, had already persuaded the United States gov- ernment to sign a contract for the supply of airplanes to the U.S. War Department, and in 1909 the Federal budget included an allocation of $30,000 for Army aviation.
For a while there was considerable patent litigation be- tween the Wright brothers and rival claimants, but in 1914 the courts ruled in their favor. Meanwhile, Wilbur Wright con- tracted typhoid fever and died in 1912, at the age of forty-five. Orville Wright, who in 1915 sold his financial interests in the airplane company, lived on till 1948. Neither of the brothers ever married.
Despite a lot of earlier research in the field, and many prior attempts and claims, there is no question that the Wright brothers deserve the lions share of the credit for the invention of the airplane. In deciding where to rank them on this list, therefore, the main factor is ones assessment of the importance of the airplane itself. It seems to me that the airplane is a far less important invention than either the printing press or the steam engine, each of which has revolutionized the entire mode of human existence. Still, it is unquestionably an invention of great significance, with applications in both peace and war. In a few decades, the airplane has shrunk our once vast planet and turned it into a small world. Furthermore, the successful achievement of manned flight was an essential preliminary to the development of space travel.
For untold centuries men had dreamed of flying. But prac- tical persons had always believed that the "flying carpets" of the Arabian Nights were only dreams, and could never exist in the real world. The genius of the Wright brothers fulfilled the age- old dream of mankind, and turned a fairy tale into reality.</string>
    <!--twenty9-->
    <string name="twenty9_GENGHIS_KHAN">Genghis Khan, the great Mongol conqueror, was born about 1162. His father, a petty Mongol chieftain, named the boy Temujin, after a defeated rival chieftain. When Temujin was nine, his father was killed by members of a rival tribe, and for some years the surviving members of the family lived in constant danger and privation. This was an inauspicious beginning, but Temujins situation was to becoIne a lot worse before it got bet- ter. When he was a young man, he was captured in a raid by a rival tribe. To prevent his escaping, a wooden collar was placed around his neck. From this extremity of helplessness, as an il- literate prisoner in a primitive, barren country, Temujin rose to become the most powerful man in the world.
    His rise started when he managed to escape from his cap- tors. He then allied himself with Toghril, a friend of his fathers, and chieftain of one of the related tribes living in the area. There followed many years of internecine warfare among these various Mongol tribes, in the course of which Temujin gradually fought his way to the top.
The tribesmen of Mongolia had long been known as skilled horsemen and fierce warriors. Throughout history, they had made sporadic raids into northern China. However, before the rise of Temujin, the various tribes had always spent most of their energy in fighting each other. By a combination of military prowess, diplomacy, ruthlessness, and organizational ability, Temujin managed to weld all of these tribes together under his leadership, and in 1206 an assembly of the Mongol chieftains proclaimed him Genghis Khan, or "the universal emperor."
The formidable military machine that Genghis Khan had assembled was then turned outward upon neighboring nations. He first attacked the Hsi Hsia state in northwestern China and the Chin Empire in northern China. While these battles were go- ing on, a dispute arose between Genghis Khan and the Khwarezm Shah Muhammad, who ruled a considerable empire in Persia and central Asia. In 1219, Genghis led his armies against the Khwarezm Shah. Central Asia and Persia were over- run, and the Khwarezm Shahs empire was completely destroyed. While other Mongol armies were attacking Russia, Genghis Khan himself led a raid into Afghanistan and northern India. He returned to Mongolia in 1225, and died there in 1227.
Shortly before his death, Genghis Khan requested that his third son, Ogadai, be named to succeed him. It was a wise choice, for Ogadai became a brilliant general in his own right. Under his leadership, the Mongol armies continued to advance in China, completely overran Russia, and advanced into Europe. In 1241, a series of Polish, German, and Hungarian armies were completely routed by the Mongols, who advanced well past Budapest. However, in that year Ogadai died, and the Mongol armies withdrew from Europe, never to return.

There was a substantial interruption while the Mongol chieftains argued about the succession. However, under the next two Khans (Genghiss grandsons, Mangu Khan and Kublai Khan) the Mongol advance in Asia was resumed. By 1279, when Kublai Khan completed the conquest of China, the Mongols ruled the largest land empire in all of history. Their domains in- cluded China, Russia, and Central Asia, in addition to Persia and most of Southwest Asia. Their armies had raided successfully from Poland to northern India, and Kublai Khans sovereignty was recognized in Korea, Tibet, and parts of Southeast Asia.
An empire of this size, given the primitive means of transportation existing at the time, could not possibly be held together for long, and the Mongol empire soon split up. But Mongol rule lasted for a long time in several of the successor states. The Mongols were expelled from most of China in 1368. In Russia, however, their rule lasted much longer. The Golden Horde, the name ususally given to the Mongol kingdom set up in Russia by Genghiss grandson Batu, endured until the sixteenth
century, and the Khanate of the Crimea survived until 1783. Other sons or grandsons of Genghis established dynasties that ruled in central Asia and in Persia. Both of these areas were con- quered in the fourteenth century by Timur (Tamerlane), who was himself of Mongol blood, and who claimed descent from Genghis. Tamerlanes dynasty was finally brought to an end in the fifteenth century. However, even this was not the end of Mongol conquests and rule. Tamerlanes great-great-grandson, Baber, invaded India, there to found the Mogul (Mongol) dynas- ty. The Mogul rulers, who eventually conquered almost all of In- dia, remained in power until the mid-eighteenth century.
In the course of history, there has been a succession of men-madmen, if you will-who set out to conquer the world and who achieved a considerable measure of success. The most notable of these megalomaniacs were Alexander the Great, Genghis Khan, Napoleon Bonaparte, and Adolf Hitler. Why do all four of these men rank so highly on this list? Are not ideas ultimately more important than armies? I would certainly agree that in the long run the pen is mightier than the sword. However, the short run matters, too. Each of these four men con- trolled such a large territory and population, and exerted such an enormous influence on the lives of their contemporaries, that they cannot be curtly dismissed as common bandits.</string>
    <!--thirty-->
    <string name="thirty_ADAM_SMITH">Adam Smith, the leading figure in the development of economic theory, was born in 1723, in the town of Kirkcaldy, Scotland. As a young man, he studied at Oxford University, and from 1751 to 1764 he was a professor of            at Glasgow University. While there, he published his first book, Theory oj Moral Sen- timents, which established his reputation in intellectual circles. However, his lasting fame rests primarily on his great work, An Inquiry Into the Nature and Causes oj the Wealth oj Nations, which was published in 1776. The book was an immediate suc- cess, and for the rest of his life Smith enjoyed fame and respect. He died in Kirkcaldy, in 1790. Smith had no children and never married.
Adam Smith was not the first person to devote himself to economic theory, and many of his best-kno\vn ideas were not original. But he was the first to present a comprehensive and systematic theory of economics that was sufficiently correct to serve as a foundation for future progress in the field. For this reason, it may fairly be said that The Wealth oj Nations is the starting point of the modern study of political economy.
One of the books great achievements was that it cleared away many past misconceptions. Smith argued against the older mercantilist theory, \vhich stressed the importance of a state hav- ing large supplies of gold bullion. Similarly, his book rejected the view of the physiocrats that land was the principal source of value, and instead asserted the basic importance of labor. Smith heavily stressed the great increase in production that could be brought about through the division of labor, and he attacked the whole set of antiquated and arbitrary government restrictions that were hampering industrial expansion.
The central idea of The Wealth oj Nations is that the seem- ingly chaotic free market is actually a self-regulating mechanism, which automatically tends to produce the type and quantity of goods that are most desired and needed by the community. For example, suppose some desirable product is in short supply. Naturally, its price will increase, and the higher price will lead to higher profits for those \vho manufacture it. Because of the high profits, other manufacturers will be eager to produce the article also. The resultant increase in production will alleviate the original shortage. Furthermore, the increased supply, in con- junction with competition between various manufacturers, will tend to reduce the price of the commodity to its "natural price," i.e., its production cost. No one has deliberately set out to help society by eliminating the shortage; nevertheless, the problem has been solved. Each person, in Smiths words, "intends only his own gain," but he is, as it were, "led by an invisible hand to pro- mote an end which was no part of his intention...By pursuing his own interest he frequently promotes that of the society more ef- fectually than when he really intends to promote it" (The Wealth oj Nations, Book IV , Chapter II).
The "invisible hand," however, cannot do the job properly if there are obstructions to free competition. Smith therefore believed in free trade and argued strongly against high tariffs. In fact, he strongly opposed most government interference with business and the free market. Such interference, he claimed, almost always decreases economic efficiency, and ultimately results in the public paying higher prices. (Smith did not invent the term "laissez faire," but he did more than any other man to promote the concept.)
Some people have the impression that Adam Smith was a mere apologist for business interest, but such a view is incorrect. He repeatedly, and in the strongest terms, denounced monopolis- tic business practices and urged their elimination. Nor was Smith naive regarding actual business practices. Here is a typical obser- vation from The Wealth oj Nations: "People of the same trade seldom meet together but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against the public, or in some diversion to raise prices."
So well did Adam Smith organize and present his system of economic thought, that within a few decades the earlier schools of economic thought were abandoned. Virtually all of their good points had been incorporated into Smiths system, while he had systematically exposed their shortcomings. Smiths successors, in- cluding such important economists as Thomas Malthus and David Ricardo, elaborated and refined his system (without changing its basic outlines) into the structure that is today refer- red to as classical economics. Although modern economic theory has added new concepts and techniques, it is largely a natural outgrowth of classical economics.
In The Wealth oj Nations, Smith partly anticipated the views of Malthus on overpopulation. However, while Ricardo and Karl Marx both insisted that population pressure would pre- vent wages from rising above the subsistence level (the so-called "iron law of wages"), Smith stated that under conditions of in- creasing production wages would be able to increase. Quite ob-
viously, events have proved that Smith was correct on this point, while Ricardo and Marx were wrong.
Quite aside from any question of the correctness of Smiths views, or of his influence upon later theorists, is the matter of his influence upon legislation and government policies. The Wealth oj Nations was written with great skill and clarity, and it was widely read. Smiths arguments against government interference in business and commercial affairs, and in favor of low tariffs and free trade, had a decided influence upon governmental policies during the entire nineteenth century. Indeed, his in- fluence on such policies is still felt today.
Since economic theory has advanced greatly since Smiths day, and since some of his ideas have been superseded, it is easy to underrate Adam Smiths importance. The fact is, though, that he was the principal originator and founder of economic theory as a systematic study, and as such is a major figure in the history of human thought.</string>
    <!--thirty1-->
    <string name="thirty1_WILLIAM_SHAKESPEARE">The great British playwright and poet, William Shakespeare, is generally acknowledged to be the greatest writer who ever lived. There is a good deal of dispute about his identity (which will be discussed below), but the talent and achievements of the author are agreed to by all.
Shakespeare wrote at least thirty-six plays, including such masterpieces as Hamlet, Macbeth, King Lear, Julius Caesar, and Othello, a magnificent set of 154 sonnets, and a few longer poems. In view of his genius, accomplishments, and deserved fame, it may seem a bit odd that his name does not appear higher on this list. I have ranked Shakespeare this low not because I am unapprecia- tive of his artistic accomplishments, but only because of my belief that, in general, literary and artistic figures have had comparatively little influence on human history.
The activities of a religious leader, scientist, politician, ex- plorer, or philosopher frequently influence developments in many other fields of human endeavor. For example, scientific advances have had tremendous impact upon economic and political affairs, and have also affected religious beliefs, philosophical attitudes, and developments in art.
However, a famous painter, though he may have a great deal of influence upon the work of subsequent painters, is likely to have very little influence upon the development of music and literature, and virtually none upon science, exploration, or other fields of human endeavor. Similar statements can be made concerning po- ets, playwrights, and composers of music. In general, artistic fig- ures influence only art, and indeed, only the particular field of art in which they work. It is for this reason that no figure in the literary, musical, or visual arts has been ranked in the top twenty, and only a handful appear on this list at all.
Why, then, are there any artistic figures on this list? One answer is that our general culture-in the sociological sense-is in part created by art. Art helps to form the connective glue ofsociety. It is no accident that art is a feature of every human civilization that has ever existed.
Furthermore, the enjoyment of art plays a direct part in the life of each individual person. In other words, an individual may spend part of his time reading books, part of his time looking at paintings, etc. Even if the time we spent listening to music had no effect whatsoever upon our other activities that time would still represent some not insignificant fraction of our lives. However, art does affect our other activities, and in some sense our whole life. Art connects us to our souls; it expresses our deepest feelings and validates them for us.
In some cases, artistic works have a more or less explicit philo- sophical content, which can influence our attitudes on other topics. This, of course, occurs more frequently in the case of literary com- positions than in the case of music or paintings. For example, when in Romeo and Juliet (Act III, scene 1) Shakespeare has the prince say, "Mercy but murders, pardoning those that kill," an idea is presented that (whether or not one accepts it) has obvious philo- sophical content, and is more likely to influence political attitudes than is, say, viewing the "Mona Lisa."
It seems beyond dispute that Shakespeare is preeminent among all literary figures. Relatively few people today read the works of Chaucer, Virgil, or even Homer, except when those works are assigned reading in school. However, a performance of one of Shakespeares plays is certain to be well attended. Shakespeares gift for a well-turned phrase is without parallel, and he is fre- quently quoted-even by persons who have never seen or read his plays. Furthermore, it is plain that his popularity is not a mere passing fad. His works have given pleasure to readers and viewers for almost four centuries. As they have already stood the test of time, it seems reasonable to assume that the works of Shakespeare will continue to be popular for a good many centuries to come.
In assessing Shakespeares importance, one should take into account that had he not lived, his plays would never have been written at all. (Of course, a corresponding statement could be lnade regarding every artistic or literary figure, but that factor does not seem particularly important in evaluating the influence of minor artists. )
Although Shakespeare wrote in English, he is truly a world figure. Ifnot quite a universal language, English is closer to being one than any other language ever has been. Moreover, Shake- speares works have been very widely translated, and his works have been read and performed in a very large number ofcountries.
There are, ofcourse, some popular authors whose writings are disdained by literary critics. Not so with Shakespeare, whose works have received unstinting praise from literary scholars. Generations of playwrights have studied his works and have attempted to emu- late his literary virtues. This combination of enormous influence on other writers and continued worldwide popularity makes it plain that William Shakespeare is entitled to a high position in this book. However, there has long been a controversy as to the identity of the man who wrote under that name.
The orthodox view (which I accepted uncritically when writ- ing the first edition of this book) is that he was the same person as William Shakspere, who was born in Stratford-on-Avon in 1564 and died there in 1616. However, on carefully evaluating the arguments of the skeptics and the counter-arguments of the orthodox, I have concluded that the skeptics have much the better of the argument and have reasonably established their case.
The bulk of the evidence indicates that "William Shakespeare" was a pseudonym used by Edward de Vere, the 17th Earl ofOxford, and that William Shakspere (or Shaxpere, or Shakspeyr, or Shag- spere, or Shaxbere: the family name was spelled several ways in Stratford, but ahnost always without the first "e"; it was theref()re pronounced quite differently-with a short "a"-than Shakespeare) was merely a prosperous merchant whose business took him to London, but who had nothing to do with the writing of the plays.
I am not suggesting that de Vere was a ghostwriter for Shak- spere, who took public credit for the plays at the time. During his lifetime, Shakspere was not considered to be the author, nor did he ever claim to be! The notion that Shakspere was the great play- wright William Shakespeare did not arise until 1623-seven years after Shakspere died!-when the First Folio edition of Shake- speares plays appeared. The editors of that book included some prefatory material in which it was strongly hinted (though never said directly) that the man from Stratford-on-Avon was the author.
To understand why it is so unlikely that Shakspere was the playwright it is first necessary to present the orthodox version of his biography, which goes as follows:
Shaksperes father, John, had once been fairly prosperous, but he fell on hard times, and young Willimn was reared in difficult financial circumstances. Nevertheless, he attended the Stratford Grammar School, where he studied Latin and classical literature.
When William was eighteen he made a young woman named Anne Hathaway pregnant. He duly married her, and she gave birth a few months later. Two and one-half years later she gave birth to twins: so William had a wife and three children to support before he was twenty-one years old.
We have no knowledge of his activities or whereabouts for the next six years, but in the early 1590s he was present in London as a member of an acting troup. He was a successful actor, but soon branched out into writing plays and poetry. By 1598 he was already being hailed as the greatest of all English writers, living or dead. Shakspere stayed in London for about twenty years, during which time he wrote at least thirty-six plays, 154 sonnets, and a few longer poems. Within a few years he became prosperous, and in 1597 was able to purchase an expensive home ("New Place") in Stratford. His family remained behind in Stratford the whole time, but he continued to support them. Oddly, he never published any of the great plays he was writ- ing. But unscrupulous printers, realizing their commercial value, published pirated editions of nearly half of them. Although the pirated editions are often rather garbled, Shakspere made no at- tempt to interfere.
About 1612, when he was forty-eight years old, he suddenly retired from writing, returned to Stratford, and resumed living with his wife. He died there in April 1616, and was buried in the church courtyard. The stone over his supposed grave does not bear his name; however, some time later a monument was erected on the wall nearby. Three weeks before his death he executed a will, leaving most of his property to his elder daughter, Susanna. She and her descendants continued to live at New Place until the last of them died, in 1670.t should be pointed out that a good deal of the foregoing biography is pure conjecture on the part of orthodox biographers. For example, there is no actual record of Shakspere ever being a student at Stratford Grammar School. Nor did any student or teacher there ever claim to have been a classmate or instructor of the famous playwright. Similarly, it is unclear that he ever had an acting career.
Nevertheless, at first sight, the official story may sound plaus- ible. However, as soon as we examine it closely, grave difficulties arise.
The first problem-mentioned even by many orthodox biogra- phers-is that we have so little information about the life of Shak- spere, very much less than we would expect to have about so prominent a person. In an attempt to explain this surprising pau- city of data people sometimes say, "He lived almost four hundred years ago. Naturally most of the documents by and about him have been lost." But that view greatly underestimates the amount of information we have about the era Shakspere lived in.
He was not living in a backward country or a barbaric age, but in England during the reign of Queen Elizabeth, a well-docu- mented era where there were printing presses, where writing ma- terials were commonplace, and where very many persons knew how to read and write. Of course, many papers have been lost; but several million original documents from that era still survive.
Because of the great interest in William Shakespeare, an army of scholars has spent three generations scouring that data, search- ing for information about the worlds most renowned literary ge- nius. As a by-product of that search they have uncovered reams of information about every other major poet of the day-and about many minor poets as well. But all they have uncovered about Shak- spere are about three dozen minor references, not one of which describes him as a poet or playwright!
We know incomparably more about the lives of Francis Bacon, Queen Elizabeth, Ben Jonson, or Edmund Spencer than we do about Shaksperes life. Indeed, we know far more about even such a minor poet as John Lyly than we do of Shakspere.
The contrast with Isaac Newton-historys foremost scientific genius-is particularly striking. We have many thousands of origi- nal documents by and about Newton (who, like Shakspere, came from a small town in England). Admittedly, Newton was born sev- enty-eight years after Shakspere. But we also have much more detailed information about Galileo (born the same year as Shak- spere), about Michelangelo (born eighty-nine years earlier), or even about Boccaccio (born in 1313) than we do about Shakspere.
A related problem is the fact that during his years in London the great playwright was virtually invisible. Shakspere is supposed to have spent roughly twenty years in London (1592-1612). But we cannot find a single record, during that whole twenty-year stretch, of anyone seeing the great actor and playwright in the flesh. When people saw the famous actor Richard Burbage or met the play- wright Ben Jonson, they marked it down as a notable event. But if anyone in London, during the whole twenty years of his greatest prominence, saw Shakspere on stage, or discussed poetry with him, or corresponded with him, or met him at a party or on the street, they did not think the encounter worthy of mention!
The only plausible explanation for the above facts is that the name «William Shakespeare" was a pseudonym used by the author in a successful attempt to keep his identity secret, and that those persons who did meet the author therefore did not know they were meeting the great William Shakespeare. (Obviously, Shakspere, whose name was so similar, could not have successfully hidden behind such a pen-name.)
Perhaps an even graver difficulty with the official story is the attitude towards Shakspere in Stratford-on-Avon. Though Shak- spere is supposed to have been the greatest writer in England- and a well-known actor to boot-nobody in his home town seemed to be aware that he was a famous man, nor that there was anything unusual about him! This is even more amazing when one recalls that he was poor when he left Stratford and wealthy when he returned, a change which would naturally tend to make friends and neighbors curious. Yet the fact is that during his lifetime, not one of his friends, or neighbors in Stratford-not even his own family!-ever referred to Shakspere as an actor, a playwright, a poet, or a literary figure of any sort! Well, what about the manuscripts of the plays in Shaksperes own handwriting? Surely they prove that he was the author. Unfor- tunately, there are no manuscripts of the plays in his handwriting, or any early drafts, or any fragments, or any unpublished or unfin- ished works. In fact, aside from six signatures on legal documents, there is NOTHING in his handwriting! No notes, no notebooks, no memoranda, no diaries. Not a single personal letter by him survives, nor a single business letter. (Nor do even his earliest biographers report having seen a single line in his handwriting.) Judging from the record, it appears that Shakspere, far from being an author, was barely literate, or even illiterate!
A related point is that Shaksperes parents, wife, and children were all illiterate. Now a man does not choose his parents, and he might select a mate for reasons other than her reading ability, but it seems scarcely believable that a man to whom the written word meant so much would allow his own daughters to grow up unable to read and write. If Shakspere was indeed Shakespeare, then he is the only prominent author in history whose children are known to have been illiterate!
Then there is the question of Shaksperes will. The original document survives: it is three pages long, and lists his property in considerable detail, with many specific bequests. Nowhere does it mention any poems, any plays, any manuscripts, any works in progress, or any literary rights. Nor does it make mention of any personal books or papers. There is no hint that he would like to see his remaining plays published (although at least twenty of them had not yet appeared in print), or that he had ever written a play or poem in his life. It is the will ofan unschooled, possibly illiterate, merchant.
We might also note that, in an era when the English poets typically arranged gaudy funerals and composed lengthy poetic eulogies when one of their members died, the death of Shakspere in 1616 went completely unmentioned by every writer in England. Not even Ben Jonson-who later claimed to have been a great admirer and friend of William Shakespeare-expressed the slight-est regret when Shakspere died, or mentioned the event at all. Clearly, the other poets of the day saw no connection between the Stratford man and the great playwright.
To my mind, the foregoing arguments are already conclusive, and no further proof is needed that Shakspere was not the play- wright and that "William Shakespeare" was a pseudonym used to conceal the true authors identity. However, there are additional strong arguments against Shakspere being the author, although their persuasiveness is not crucial to the case against him.
For example, it has been pointed out that most dramatists and writers of fiction include in their writings many incidents from their own lives. (Often, such events form a major part of the story.) But the plays of Shakespeare are virtually devoid of any incidents or circumstances which can be traced back to Shaksperes own experiences.
Another argument is that the author, William Shakespeare, was obviously an extremely well educated man; witness his enor- mous vocabulary (much larger than that of any other playwright), his familiarity with both Latin and French, his accurate knowledge of legal terminology, and his voluminous knowledge of classical literature. But everyone agrees that Shakspere never attended a university, and (as explained above) it is doubtful whether he even attended grammar school.
Still another point is that Shakespeare (the author) seems to be of aristocratic sympathies and background, very familiar with the sports of the aristocracy (such as fox-hunting and falconry) and familiar with court life and court intrigues. Shakspere, on the other hand, came from a small town and had a petit bourgeois back- ground.
There are many other aspects of the life of Shakspere that do not fit in with the hypothesis that he was the famous author, Wil- liam Shakespeare, and I could easily write many pages describing additional difficulties with that theory. (The reader who wants more details can find them in the excellent book, The Mysterious William Shakespeare, by Charlton Ogburn.) Of course, orthodox biographers have constructed hypothetical explanations for each of those difficulties, and for each of the problems I have already described. Some of those explanations are rather unlikely, but each one individually is at least possible.
For example, it is possible-although people tend to save let- ters that they receive from famous men-that by the merest coinci- dence every personal or business letter that Shakspere ever wrote has vanished without a trace, together with all his notes, notebooks, and manuscripts. It is possible that the greatest of English poets composed for his own epitaph the childish piece of doggerel that we see on Shaksperes gravestone. It is possible that a man whose plays show that he admired intelligent, educated women let his own daughters grow up illiterate. And it is possible that, although Shakspere was the most celebrated writer in England, not a single one of his friends, family, or neighbors in Stratford ever referred to him as an actor, poet, or playwright. Ifs not very likely, but ifs
possible!
However, in this case, as in .most, the whole is greater than any of its parts. Were there just one or two difficulties with the official story, we might accept even rather far-fetched explanations for them. But after a while we cant help noticing that nothing seems to fit the official story naturally. Everything about that story seems to require an ad hoc, and often far-fetched, explanation. The problem is that William Shakspere of Stratford-on-Avon was a barely literate small-town merchant, and neither his education, nor his character, nor his actions, nor what his family and neighbors said about him, are consistent with his being the great author, William Shakespeare.
Well, if Shakspere was not the author of the plays, who was? Many other persons have been suggested, ofwhich the best known is the famous philosopher Francis Bacon. But in recent years, the accumulation of evidence has swung opinion strongly towards Ed- ward de Vere.
We know a lot about Edward de Vere: he led an adventurous life, and many events in his life are mirrored in the plays. He was born in 1550, the son and heir of the 16th Earl of Oxford, a wealthy and high-ranking aristocrat. As befit the heir to a title which went back to the Norman Conquest, young Edward received training in all the customary skills of a young lord: riding, hunting, military arts, and also such Inilder pursuits as music and dancing. Nor was his academic education ignored. He had private tutors for both French and Latin, as well as other subjects. Eventually he obtained a bachelors degree from Cambridge University and a masters de- gree from Oxford. Afterwards, he studied law for a year at Grays Inn, one of the famed Inns of Court in London.
His father died when Edward was only twelve, and his mother subsequently remarried. However, Edward did not remain with his mother for long. Instead, he became a royal ward, and a guard- ian was appointed for him. The guardian chosen was William Cecil, Lord Treasurer of England, and a member of Queen Elizabeths privy council for many years. As the Queens oldest and most trusted adviser, Cecil was one of the most powerful men in En- gland.
Young de Vere, as befitted his high rank, was treated as a family member in Cecils household. (A somewhat mysterious incident, in which he killed one of Cecils servants, was kept out of the courts due to Cecils influence.) In his late teens he was introduced to Court, where he met all the leading figures, including the Queen herself. She was much taken with the young man who, in addition to being brilliant, athletic, and charming, was also very good-look- ing, and he soon became a favorite of hers.
When he was twenty-one, de Vere married Anne Cecil, his guardians daughter. Since they had been reared together, and she was almost his "kid sister," such a marriage was quite unusual. (But Posthumus Leonatus, the hero of Cymbeline, was also a royal ward who married his guardians daughter, and there are many other resemblances between his story and de Veres.)
When he was twenty-four, de Vere embarked on a lengthy trip through Europe. He visited France and Germany, spent about ten months in Italy, and then returned to England via France. On the trip back across the English Channel his ship was attacked by pirates, who planned to hold their captives for ransom. But de Vere informed the pirates of his personal friendship with Queen Elizabeth, and the pirates decided it was prudent to release him promptly without demanding a ransom. (A very similar incident occurs to the hero of Hamlet.)
Meanwhile, his wife Anne had given birth to a daughter. Though the girl had been born only eight months after de Vere left England, he insisted that the child was not his, and, claiming that Anne was an adulteress, he refused to live with her. Most historians feel that his charge was ill-founded. Apparently de Vere eventually reached this conclusion also, as after a five-year separa- tion he dropped his charges and resumed living with Anne. (False charges of the adultery of a blameless young wife are a common theme in Shakespeares plays. For example: Alls Well That Ends Well, Cymbeline, The Winters Tale, and Othello. And in every case
the grievously wronged wife forgives her husband.)
During the five-year separation from his wife, de Vere had an affair with a court lady, which resulted in her pregnancy. Queen Elizabeth, angered at this, had de Vere arrested and sent to the Tower of London. He was released after a few months; but a friend of the young woman, resentful of de Veres actions, attacked him, and de Vere was badly injured. Street brawls between the two
families continued for a while, until the Queen threatened to jail them all unless the fighting stopped. (Reminds one of Romeo and
Juliet.)
After de Vere resumed living with his wife, they had five chil-
dren together. Then Anne, still only thirty-two years old, died suddenly. Four years later de Vere remarried, and his second wife outlived him.
Meanwhile, de Veres financial affairs-which had been in bad shape, due to his spendthrift habits-had improved radically. In 1586, when de Vere was thirty-six years old, Queen Elizabeth granted him a lifetime pension in the extraordinary amount of 1,000 pounds a year. That is equivalent to about $100,000 a year today, tax-free! A remarkable sum, especially considering that Elizabeth was notoriously tight-fisted with money! Curiously, the grant made no mention of any duties which de Vere must perform in return, nor of any past services for which he was being rewarded. The grant, however, was paid regularly for the rest of her life, and her successor (King James I) continued to pay it after her death in 1603.
De Vere had always been intensely interested in poetry and the theatre, was friends with many literary figures, and as a young man is known to have written poetry and plays in his own name. (Those early plays have been lost, but several ofthe poems survive. Some of them are quite good, though well below the standard of the mature William Shakespeare.) However he did not publish any of them, due to the prevailing notion that it was discreditable for an aristocrat to write poetry for publication. (Such an attitude seems very peculiar nowadays; but historians agree that such an attitude was common at the time, and that the taboo was rarely
violated.)
After the grant by Queen Elizabeth, though, de Vere never
wrote another line in his own name. But within a few years, poems and plays started appearing by the invisible author "William Shake- speare."
Why did Elizabeth grant this extraordinarily generous pension to de Vere? Although no reason was ever stated, the obvious expla- nation is that she-like so      other monarchs before her-was patronizing a talented artist in the hopes that his achievements would glorify her reign. If that was her motive, she certainly got her moneys worth. Indeed, no ruler before or since seems to have made a better choice!
After being awarded the pension by the Queen, the formerly very active Edward de Vere retired completely from court life. Presumably, he spent the last eighteen years of his life writing and revising the great plays and poetry that have made "William Shakespeare" famous. He died in 1604, during an epidemic of the plague, and was buried near his country home at Hackney, near the village of Stratford. (There were two towns in England named Stratford; and at the time that one was larger than Stratford-on- A von.)
Unlike Shakspere-or any of the other persons suggested as the author-Edward de Vere seems to fit perfectly the require- ments for the mysterious William Shakespeare. He had an excellent education, had studied law, and was well- versed in foreign languages. (He certainly knew Latin and French, and possibly other languages as well.)
He was an aristocrat, and had an insiders knowledge of court life and court intrigue.
He had the large amount of free time necessary to compose the plays.
He was repeatedly described by others as brilliant and tal- ented.
He had a lifelong interest in the theatre, and is known to have written poetry and plays in his own name when he was younger. Indeed, he was specifically named, during his lifetime, as one of those noblemen who had written poetry but (because of the taboo mentioned above) had not published it under his own name. More- over, he was praised as the most skillful and excellent of the gentle- men who had done so. (These descriptions are in documents surviving from that era.)
The plays of William Shakespeare contain a large number of incidents and characters which can be clearly identified as relating to events, personalities, and situations in the life of Edward de Vere. (A few of them have been noted above, but there are many others.)
The only problem at all with accepting de Vere as the author of the plays is the question: Why did he keep his identity a secret? There are several possible explanations.
1) There was a strong taboo at that time against noblemen writing poetry for publication, or plays for the commercial theatre. 2) De Vere was known to be an insider at court. Since many
of the plays dealt with court life, if he admitted authorship people would naturally (and probably correctly!) have assumed that vari- ous characters in the plays were intended as insulting parodies of various real people in court. Today, such writing is accepted· as commonplace and, though hardly friendly, not a cause for action. By the standards of those days, however, it would at least have been grounds for a lawsuit, and more likely for a duel. By hiding his identity, de Vere avoided such problems.
3) Many of the sonnets of Willialll Shakespeare are addressed to a female lover. His admission of authorship, therefi)re, would be embarrassing to his wife.
4) Far worse, many of the other sonnets are addressed to a male, and have often been interpreted as showing that the author was homosexual or bisexual. Whether or not that interpretation is correct (and the majority of critics believe it is not), admitting that he was the author of the sonnets would have caused gossip that would have been very embarrassing to his family.
Perhaps no one of these answers is entirely convincing by itself. Taken together, though, they might indeed be the full expla- nation for de Veres concealing his identity. However, it is certainly possible that he had additional reasons which we do not know of. (For example, it is possible that, as a condition of the pension granted him, Elizabeth had insisted that he follow the social norms-and avoid possible duels between her courtiers-by not publishing anything in his own name.)
Whether or not we know the full explanation for de Veres concealing his authorship, he matches the requirements for Shake- speare perfectly in all other respects-and remember: nobody else even comes close! To me, it seems virtually certain that he is the author.
One final question: How did Shakspere ever get to be consid- ered the author of the plays? That belief seems to have its origin in three references, each made a few years after Shakspere had died, and each somewhat ambiguous. Unless an unusual coinci- dence is postulated, it appears that someone (or ones) deliberately committed a hoax. Why was that done, and by whom?
We cannot be certain of the answer to that question; but the most likely explanation is that the hoax was perpetrated by de Veres family when they decided (about 1620) to have his collected works published and chose to continue to keep his identity secret. Their motives were probably quite similar to his: fear of scandal (and perhaps other motives, such as a promise to the monarch). To make the deception more complete, they decided to present an-
other person as the author. Shakspere was the obvious choice as the stand-in, because of the similarity of names. Also, since he had been dead for several years he could not expose the fraud; and since he was little known in London, and even less remembered, there were very few others in town who would realize that the story was a hoax.
The deception was probably fairly easy to carry out. Ben Jon- son, who provided a prefatory poem to the First Folio edition, was persuaded to include a couple of ambiguous lines that strongly hinted (without saying so directly, or telling any other flat-out lies) that the author came from Stratford-on-Avon. They also arranged for a monument to be erected there, near Shaksperes grave, with an inscription which includes strong (though vague) words of praise. Since the identity of William Shakespeare had always been kept a secret, a few hints that he was the man from Stratford sufficed to get the story started. Nobody at the time was very interested in checking the story carefully. (There was much less interest in literary biography then than there is now.) By the time the first biography of Shakespeare was written (by William Rowe: 1709) those who knew the truth had long been dead, and the myth of Shaksperes authorship long accepted. </string>
    <!--thirty2-->
    <string name="thirty2_JOHN_DALTON">John Dalton was the English scientist who, in the early nine- teenth century, introduced the atomic hypothesis into the main- stream of science. By so doing, he provided the key idea that made possible the enormous progress in chemistry since his day.
To be sure, he was not the first person to suggest that all material objects are composed of vast numbers of exceedingly small, indestructible particles called atoms. That notion had been suggested by the ancient Greek philosopher, Democritus (460-370 B.C.?), and probably even earlier. The hypothesis was adopted by Epicurus (another Greek philosopher), and was brilliantly presented by the Roman writer, Lucretius (died: 55 B.C.), in his famous poem De rerum natura (On the Nature oj Things). Democrituss theory (which had not been accepted by Aristotle) was neglected during the Middle Ages, and had little effect on modern science. Still, several leading scientists of the seventeenth century (including Isaac Newton) supported similar notions. But none of the earlier atomic theories were expressed quantitatively, nor were they used in scientific research. Most important, nobody saw the connection between the philosophical speculations about atoms and the hard facts of chemistry.
That was where Dalton came in. He presented a clear, quantitative theory, which could be used to interpret chemical experiments, and could be precisely tested in the laboratory.
Though his terminology was slightly different from the one we use now, Dalton clearly expressed the concepts of atoms, molecules, elements, and chemical compounds. He made it clear that although the total number of atoms in the world is very large, the number of different types of atoms is rather small. (His original book listed twenty elements, or species of atoms; today, slightly over a hundred elements are known.)
Though different types of atoms differ in weight, Dalton in- sisted that any two atoms of the same species are identical in all their properties, including mass. (Sophisticated modern experi- ments show that there are exceptions to this rule. For any given chemical element there exist two or more types of atoms-called isotopes-which differ slightly in mass, though their chemical properties are almost identical.) Dalton included in his book a table listing the relative weights of different kinds of atoms-the first such table ever prepared, and a key feature of any quantitative atomic theory.
Dalton also stated clearly that any two molecules of the same chemical compound are composed of the same combination of atoms. (For example, each molecule of nitrous oxide consists of two atoms of nitrogen and one atom of oxygen.) From this it follows that a given chemical compound-no matter how it may be prepared, or where found-always contains the same elements in exactly the same proportion by weight. This is the "law of definite proportions," which had been discovered ex- perimentally by Joseph Louis Proust a few years earlier.
So convincingly did Dalton present his theory that within twenty years it was adopted by the majority of scientists. Fur- thermore, chemists followed the program that his book sug- gested: determine exactly the relative atomic weights; analyze chemical compounds by weight; determine the exact combin- ation of atoms which constitutes each species of molecule. The success of that program has, of course, been overwhelming.
It is difficult to overstate the importance of the atomic hypo- thesis. It is the central notion in our understanding of chemistry.In addition, it is an indispensable prologue to much of modern physics. It is only because atomism had been so frequently discussed before Dalton that he does not appear even higher on this list.
Dalton was born in 1766, in the village of Eaglesfield, in northern England. His formal schooling ended" when he was only eleven years old, and he was almost entirely self-taught in science. He was a precocious young man, and when he was twelve years old he became a teacher himself. He was to be a teacher or private tutor for most of his remaining years. When he was fifteen, he moved to the town of Kendal, and when he was twenty-six he moved to Manchester, where he dwelled until his death in 1844. He never married.
Dalton became interested in meteorology in 1787, when he was twenty-one years old. Six years later, he published a book on the subject. The study of air and the atmosphere aroused his in- terest in the properties of gases in general. By performing a series of experiments, he discovered two important laws governing the behavior of gases. The first, which Dalton presented in 1801, states that the volume occupied by a gas is proportional to its temperature. (It is generally known as           law, after the French scientist who had discovered it several years before Dalton, but who had failed to publish his results.) The second, also presented in 1801, is known as Daltons law of partial pressures.
By 1804, Dalton had formulated his atomic theory and prepared a list of atomic weights. However, his principal book, A New System oj Chemical Philosophy, did not come out till 1808. That book made him famous, and in later years, many honors were accorded him.
Incidentally, Dalton suffered from a form of color blind- ness. Characteristically, the condition aroused his curiosity. He studied the subject and eventually published a scientific paper on color blindness-the first ever written on the topic! </string>
    <!--thirty3-->
    <string name="thirty3_ALEXANDER_THE_GREAT">Alexander the Great, the most celebrated conqueror of the an- cient world, was born in 356 B.C, in Pella, the capital city of Macedonia. His father, King Philip II of Macedon, was a man of truly outstanding ability and foresight. Philip enlarged and reorganized the Macedonian army, and converted it into a fighting force of the highest caliber. He first used this army to conquer surrounding regions to the north of Greece, and then turned south and conquered most of Greece itself. Next, Philip created a federation of the Greek city-states, with himself as leader. He was planning to make war on the vast Persian Empire to the east of Greece; indeed, the invasion had already commenc- ed, in 336 B.C, when Philip, still only forty-six years old, was assassinated.
    Alexander was only twenty years old when his father died, but he succeeded to the throne without difficulty. Philip had carefully prepared his son to succeed him, and the young Alex- ander already had considerable military experience. Nor had his father neglected his intellectual education. Alexanders tutor had been the brilliant philosopher Aristotle, perhaps the greatest scientist and philosopher of the ancient world.
In both Greece and the northern territories, the peoples con- quered by Philip saw the occasion of his death as a good op- portunity to throw off the Macedonian yoke. However, Alex- ander, in the two years following his accession to the throne, was able to subdue both regions. He then turned his attention to Per- sia.
For two hundred years, the Persians had governed a vast territory that stretched all the way from the Mediterranean to In- dia. Although Persia was no longer at the height of its powers, it was still a formidable adversary-the largest, mightiest, and wealthiest empire on Earth.
Alexander launched his invasion of the Persian Empire in 334 B.C. Since he had to leave part of his army at home to main- tain control of his European possessions, Alexander had only 35,000 troops with him when he set out on his audacious quest-a very small force compared with the Persian armies. In spite of the numerical disadvantage, Alexander won a series of crushing victories over the Persian forces. There were three main reasons for his success. In the first place, the army which Philip had left him was better trained and organized than the Persian forces. In the second place, Alexander was a general of outstand- ing genius, perhaps the greatest of all time. The third factor was Alexanders own personal courage. Although he would direct the early stages of each battle from behind the lines, Alexanders policy was to lead the decisive cavalry charge himself. This was a risky procedure, and he was frequently wounded. But his troops saw that Alexander was sharing their danger, and was not asking them to take any risks that he himself would not take. The effect on their morale was enormous.
    Alexander first led his troops through Asia Minor, defeating the smaller Persian armies stationed there. Then, moving into northern Syria, he routed an immense Persian army at Issus. Alexander then moved further south, and after a difficult seven- month siege, conquered the Phoenician island-city of Tyre, in present-day Lebanon. While Alexander was besieging Tyre, he received a message from the Persian king offering to cede Alex- ander half of his empire in return for a peace treaty. One of Alex- anders generals, Parmenio, thought the offer rather good. "I would take that offer, if I were Alexander," he said. "And so would I," Alexander replied, "if I were Parmenio."
After the fall of Tyre, Alexander continued south. Gaza fell after a two-month siege. Egypt surrendered to him without a fight. Alexander then paused for a while in Egypt to rest his troops. There, though still only twenty-four years old, he was crowned pharaoh and declared a god. He then led his armies back into Asia, and at the decisive battle of Arbela, in 331 B.C., he completely routed a much larger Persian army.
After that victory Alexander led his troops into Babylon, and into the Persian capitals of Susa and Persepolis. The Persian king, Darius III (not to be confused with his predecessor, Darius the Great), was assassinated by his officers in 330 B.C., to prevent him from surrendering to Alexander. Nevertheless, Alexander defeated and killed Dariuss successor, and in three years of fighting, subdued all of eastern Iran and pushed on into Central Asia.
With the whole Persian Empire now subject to him, Alex- ander might no\v have returned home and reorganized his new dominions. But his thirst for conquest was still unslaked, and he continued on, into Afghanistan. From there he led his army across the Hindu Kush mountains into India. He won a series of victories in western India, and intended to continue on to eastern India. His troops, however, exhausted by years of fighting, refus- ed to go any farther, and Alexander reluctantly returned to Per- sia.
After returning to Persia, Alexander spent the next year or so reorganizing his empire and army. And a major reorganization it was. Alexander had been brought up to believe that Greek culture represented the only true civilization, and that all of the non-Greek peoples \vere barbarians. Such, of course, was the prevailing view throughout the Greek world, and even Aristotle had shared it. But, despite the fact that he had thoroughly defeated the Persian armies, Alexander had come to realize that the Persians were not barbarians at all, and that individual Per- sians could be as intelligent, capable, and worthy of respect as in- dividual Greeks. He therefore conceived the notion of fusing the two parts of his empire together, thereby creating a joint Graeco- Persian culture and kingdom, with himself, of course, as ruler. So far as we can determine, he really intended the Persians to be equal partners with the Greeks and Macedonians. To implement this plan, he took large numbers of Persians into his army. He also held a great feast, "the marriage of East and West," at which several thousand Macedonian troops were formally mar- ried to Asian women. He himself, although he had previously married an Asian princess, married the daughter of Darius.
It is plain that Alexander intended to make additional con- quests with this reorganized army. We know that he planned to invade Arabia, and probably also the regions north of the Persian Empire. He may also have intended another invasion of India, or the conquest of Rome, Carthage, and the western Mediterra- nean. Whatever his plans may have been, as it turned out, there were to be no further conquests. In early June, in the year 323 B .C ., while in Babylon, Alexander suddenly fell ill of a fever, and
, he died ten days later. He was not yet thirty-three years old. Alexander had named no successor, and soon after his death a fight for power ensued. In the struggle that followed, Alex- anders mother, wives, and children were all killed. His empire
was eventually divided among his generals.
Because Alexander died young and undefeated, there has
been much speculation as to what ,might have occurred had he lived. If he had led his forces into an invasion of the western Mediterranean lands, he would most likely have been successful, and in that case, the entire history of western Europe might have been vastly different. But such speculations, however interesting, have little relevance to an assessment of Alexanders actual in- fluence.
Alexander was perhaps the most dramatic figure in history, and his career and personality have remained a source of fascina- tion. The true facts of his career are dramatic enough, and dozens of legends have grown up around his name. It was plainly his ambition to be the greatest warrior of all time, and he seems to deserve that title. As an individual fighter, he combined abili- ty and courage. As a general, he was supreme, and in eleven years of fighting, he never lost a single battle.
At the same time, however, he was an intellectual who had studied under Aristotle and treasured the poetry of Homer. In- deed, in his realization that non-Greeks were not necessarily bar-barians, he showed far more vision than most Greek thinkers of his day. In other ways, however, he was surprisingly short- sighted. Although he repeatedly risked his life in battle, he made no provisions for a successor, and his failure to do so was in large part responsible for the rapid breakup of his empire after his death.
Alexander reputedly could be very charming, and he was often extremely conciliatory and charitable to defeated enemies.On the other hand, he was also an egomaniac with a ferocious temper. On one occasion, in a drunken argument, he killed a close associate of his, Cleitus, a man who had once saved his life.
Like Napoleon and Hitler, Alexander had an overwhelming effect upon his own generation. His short-term influence, however, was less than theirs, simply because the limited means of travel and communication existing at the time restricted his in- fluence to a smaller portion of the globe.
In the long run, the most important effect of Alexanders conquests was to bring the Greek and Middle Eastern civiliza- tions into close contact \vith each other, and thereby to greatly enrich both cultures. During and immediately after Alexanders career, Greek culture spread rapidly into Iran, Mesopotamia, Syria, Judea, and Egypt; before Alexander, Greek culture had been entering these regions only slowly. Also, Alexander spread Greek influence into India and Central Asia, areas which it had never reached before. But the cultural influence was by no means a one-way affair. During the Hellenistic Age (the cen- turies immediately following Alexanders career), eastern ideas- particularly religious ideas-spread into the Greek world. It was this Hellenistic culture-predominantly Greek but with strong oriental influences-that eventually affected Rome.
In the course of his career, Alexander founded more than twenty new cities. The most famous of these was Alexandria, in Egypt, which soon became one of the leading cities of the world, and a notable center of learning and culture. A few others, such as Herat and Kandahar in Afghanistan, also developed into cities of importance.
Alexander, Napoleon, and Hitler seem fairly close in overall influence. One gets the impression, though, that the influence of the other two men will be less enduring than that of Alexander. On that basis, he has been ranked slightly above them, even though his short-term influence was somewhat less than theirs.</string>
    <!--thirty4-->
    <string name="thirty4_NAPOLEON_BONAPARTE">The celebrated French general and emperor, Napoleon I, was born in Ajaccio, Corsica, in 1769. His original name was Napoleone Buonaparte. France had acquired Corsica only some fifteen months before his birth, and in his early years, Napoleon was a Corsican nationalist who considered the French to be op- pressors. Nevertheless, Napoleon was sent to military academies in France, and when he graduated in 1785, at the age of sixteen, he became a second lieutenant in the French army.
    Four years later, the French Revolution erupted, and within a few years, the new French government was involved in wars with several foreign powers. Napoleons first opportunity to distinguish himself came in 1793, at the siege of Toulon (in which the French recaptured the city from the British), where he was in charge of the artillery. (By this time he had abandoned his Cor- sican nationalist ideas and considered himself a Frenchman.) His accomplishments at Toulon won him promotion to brigadier general, and in 1796, he was given the command of the French army in Italy. There, in 1796-97, Napoleon achieved a spec- tacular series of victories. A hero, he then returned to Paris.
In 1798, Napoleon headed a French invasion of Egypt. The campaign was a disaster. On the land, Napoleons armies were generally successful. But the British navy, under the leadership of Lord Nelson, destroyed the French fleet, and in 1799 Napoleon abandoned his army in Egypt and returned to France.
Back in France, Napoleon found that the public remembered the successes of his Italian campaign rather than the debacle of the Egyptian expedition. Capitalizing on this, a month after his return, Napoleon took part in a coup d etat, together with the Abbe Sieyes and others. The coup resulted in a new government, the Consulate, with Napoleon holding the of- fice of first consul. Although an elaborate constitution was adopted, and was ratified by a popular plebiscite, it was only a mask for the military dictatorship of Napoleon, who had soon gained the ascendancy over the other conspirators.
Napoleons rise to power was, thus, incredibly rapid. In August 1793, before the siege of Toulon, Napoleon had been a totally unknown twenty-four-year-old minor officer of not-quite French birth. Less than six years later, Napoleon, still only thir- ty, was the undisputed ruler of France-a position he was to hold for over fourteen years.
During his years in power, Napoleon instituted major revi- sions in the administration of France and in the French legal system. For example, he reformed the financial structure and the judiciary; he created the Bank of France and the University of France; and he centralized the French administration. Although each of these changes had a significant, and in some cases endur- ing, impact on France itself, they had little impact on the rest of the world.
One of Napoleons reforms, however, was destined to have an impact far beyond the borders of France. That was the crea- tion of the French civil code, the famous Code Napoleon. In many ways the code embodied the ideals of the French Revolu- tion. For example, under the code there were no privileges of birth, and all men were equal under the law. At the same time, the code was sufficiently close to the older French laws and
.customs to be acceptable to the French public and the legal pro- fession. On the whole, the code was moderate, well organized, and written with commendable brevity and outstanding lucidi- ty. As a result, the code has not only endured in France (the French civil code today is strikingly similar to the original Code Napoleon) but has been adopted, with local modifications, in many other countries.
It was always Napoleons policy to insist that he was the defender of the Revolution. Nevertheless, in 1804 he had himself proclaimed Emperor of France. In addition, Napeoleon installed three of his brothers on the thrones of other European states. These actions doubtless aroused the resentment of some French republicans-who considered such behavior a complete betrayal of the ideals of the French Revolution-but Napoleons only serious difficulties were to result from his foreign wars.
In 1802, at Amiens, Napoleon had signed a peace treaty with England, giving France a respite after more than a decade of almost continuous warfare. However, the following year the peace treaty broke do\vn, and a long series of wars with England and her allies followed. Though Napoleons armies repeatedly won victories on the land, England could not be conquered unless her navy was defeated. Unfortunately for Napoleon, at the crucial battle of Trafalgar, in 1805, the English navy won an overwhelming victory; thereafter, Englands control of the seas was not seriously disputed. Although Napoleons greatest victory (at Austerlitz, against the armies of Austria and Russia) came on- ly six weeks after Trafalgar, it did not really compensate for the naval disaster.
In 1808, Napoleon foolishly involved France in a long and pointless war on the Iberian peninsula, in which French armies were bogged down for years. Napoleons decisive blunder, however, was his Russian campaign. In 1807, Napoleon had met with the Czar, and in the Treaty of Tilsit, they had vowed eter- nal friendship. But the alliance gradually deteriorated, and in June 1812, Napoleon led his Grande Armee into Russia.
The results are well known. The Russian army generally avoided fighting pitched battles against Napoleon, and he was able to advance rapidly. By September, he had occupied Moscow. However, the Russians set fire to the city, and most of it was destroyed. After waiting five weeks in Moscow (in a vain hope that the Russians would sue for peace), Napoleon finally decided to retreat. But by then it was too late. The combination of the Russian army, the Russian winter, and the inadequate supplies of the French army soon turned the retreat into a rout. Less than 10 percent of the Grande Armee got out of Russia alive.
Other European countries, such as Austria and Prussia, realized that they now had an opportunity to throw off the French yoke. They joined forces against Napoleon, and at the battle of Leipzig, in October 1813, Napoleon suffered another crushing defeat. The following year he resigned and was banish- ed to Elba, a small island off the Italian coast.
In 1815, he escaped from Elba and returned to France, where he was welcomed and restored to power. But the other European powers promptly declared war, and a hundred days after his restoration, he met his final defeat at Waterloo. After Waterloo, Napoleon was imprisoned by the British on St. Helena, a small island in the south Atlantic. He died there, of cancer, in 1821.
Napoleons military career presents a surprising paradox. His genius at tactical maneuvering was dazzling, and if he were to be judged only by that, he might perhaps be considered the greatest general of all time. In the field of grand strategy, however, he was prone to making incredibly gross blunders, such as the invasions of Egypt and Russia. His strategic errors were so egregious that Napoleon should not be placed in the first rank of military leaders. Is this unfair second-guessing? I think not. Cer- tainly, one criterion of a generals greatness is his ability to avoid disastrous errors. It is very hard to second-guess the very greatest generals, such as Alexander the Great, Genghis Khan, and Tamerlane, whose armies were never defeated. Because Napole- on was defeated in the end, all of his foreign conquests proved ephemeral. After his final defeat, in 1815, France possessed less territory than she had in 1789, at the outbreak of the Revolution.
    Napoleon was, of course, an egomaniac, and he has often been compared to Hitler. But there is a crucial difference be- tween the two men. Whereas Hitler was motivated in large part by a hideous ideology, Napoleon was merely an ambitious op- portunist, and he had no particular interest in perpetrating hor- rible massacres. Nothing in Napoleons regime remotely com- pares with the Nazi concentration camps.
Napoleons very great fame makes it easy to overestimate his influence. His short-term influence was indeed enormous, pro- bably larger than Alexander the Greats had been, though much less than Hitlers. (It has been estimated that approximately 500,000 French soldiers died during the Napoleonic Wars; however, in comparison, it has been estimated that 8,000,000 Germans died during the Second World War.) By any standard, Napoleons activities disrupted far fewer of his contemporaries lives than did Hitlers.
In regard to long-term influence, Napoleon seems more im- portant than Hitler, though less so than Alexander. Napoleon made extensive administrative changes in France, but France comprises less than one-seventieth of the worlds population. In any event, such administrative changes should be viewed in pro- per prospective. They have had far less effect upon the lives of in- dividual Frenchmen than the numerous technological changes of the last two centuries.
It has been said that the Napoleonic era provided time for the changes instituted during the French Revolutionary era to become established, and for the gains made by the French bourgeoisie to be consolidated. By 1815, when the French monarchy was finally re-established, these changes were so well entrenched that a return to the social patterns of the ancien regime was unthinkable. The most important changes, however, had been instituted before Napoleon; by 1799, when Napoleon took office, it was probably already too late for any return to the status quo ante. However, Napoleon, despite his own monar- chical ambitions, did playa role in spreading the ideals of the French Revolution throughout Europe.
Napoleon also had a large, though indirect, effect on the history of Latin America. His invasion of Spain so weakened the Spanish government that for a period of several years it lost effec- tive control of its colonies in Latin America. It was during this period of de jacto autonomony that the Latin American in- dependence movements commenced.
Of all Napoleons actions, however, the one that has perhaps had the most enduring and significant consequences was one that was almost irrelevant to his main plans. In 1803, Napoleon sold a vast tract of land to the United States. He realized that the French possessions in North America might be difficult to protect from British conquest, and besides he was short of cash. The Louisiana Purchase, perhaps the largest peaceful transfer of land in all of history, transformed the United States into a nation of near-continental size. It is difficult to say what the United States would have been like without the Louisiana Purchase; certainly it would have been a vastly different country than it is today. In- deed, it is doubtful whether the United States would have become a great power \vithout the Louisiana Purchase.
Napoleon, of course, was not solely responsible for the Loui- siana Purchase. The American government clearly played a role as well. But the French offer \vas such a bargain that it seems likely that any American government would have accepted it, while the decision of the French government to sell the Louisiana territory came about through the arbitrary judgment of a single individual, Napoleon Bonaparte. </string>
    <!--thirty5-->
    <string name="thirty5_THOMAS_EDISON">The versatile inventor Thomas Alva Edison was born in 1847, in the town of Milan, Ohio. He had only three months of formal education, and his schoolmaster considered him to be retarded!
Edison created his first invention, an electric vote-recorder, when he was only twenty-one years old. It did not sell, and thereafter Edison concentrated on inventing objects that he ex- pected would be readily marketable. Not long after the vote- recorder, he invented an improved stock ticker system which he sold for forty thousand dollars, a tremendous sum in those days. A series of other inventions followed, and Edison was soon both wealthy and famous. Probably his most original invention was
     the phonograph, which he patented in 1877. More important to the world, however, was his development of a practical in- candescent light bulb in 1879.
Edison was not the first to invent an electrical lighting system. A few years earlier, electric arc lamps had been utilized for street lighting in Paris. But Edisons bulb, together with the system of distributing electric power that he developed, made electric lighting practical for ordinary home use. In 1882, his company started producing electricity for homes in New York City, and thereafter the home use of electricity spread rapidly throughout the world.
By setting up the first distribution company that carried electrical power into private homes, Edison laid the groundwork for the development of an enormous industry. It is, after all, not only the electric light which uses this power source today, but the whole array of home electrical appliances, from the TV set to the washing machine. Furthermore, the availability of electric power from the distribution network that Edison had established greatly stimulated the use of, electricity by industry.
Edison contributed enormously to the development of motion-picture cameras and projectors. He made important im- provements in the telephone (where his carbon transmitter mark- edly improved audibility), in the telegraph, and in the type- writer. Among his other inventions were a dictating machine, a mimeograph machine, and a storage battery. All told, Edison patented more than a thousand separate inventions-a truly in- credible total.
One reason for Edisons astonishing productivity is that ear- ly in his career he set up a research laboratory at Menlo Park, New Jersey, where he employed a group of capable assistants to help him. This was the prototype of the large research laboratories that so many industrial firms have since established. Edisons origination of the modern, well-equipped research laboratory, where many persons work together as a team, was one of his most important inventions-though, of course, one which he could not patent. Edison was not merely an inventor; he also engaged in
manufacturing and organized several industrial companies. The
most important of these eventually became the General Electric Company.
Although not by temperament a pure scientist, Edison did make one significant scientific discovery. In 1882, he discovered that in a near-vacuum, an electric current could be made to flow between two wires that did not touch each other. This phenomenon, called the Edison effect, is not only of considerable theoretical interest, but has important practical applications as well. It led, in time, to the development of the vacuum tube and to the foundation of the electronics industry.
For most of his life, Edison suffered from seriously impaired hearing. However, he more than compensated for that handicap by his astonishing capacity for hard work. Edison was married twice (his first wife died young) and had three children by each marriage. He died in West Orange, New Jersey, in 1931.
There is no dispute concerning Edisons talent. Everyone agrees that he was the greatest inventive genius who ever lived. His parade of useful inventions is awe-inspiring, even though it is probable that most of them would have been developed by others within thirty years. However, if we consider his inventions in- dividually, we see that no one of them was of really critical im- portance. The incandescent light bulb, for example, although widely used, is not an irreplaceable part of modern life. In fact, fluorescent light bulbs, which operate on a completely different
scientific principle, are also widely used, and our everyday life would not be much different if we had no incandescent bulbs at all. Indeed, before electric lights came into use, candles, oil lamps, and gaslights were generally regarded as reasonably satisfactory sources of light.
The phonograph is certainly an ingenious device, but no one would claim that it has transformed our daily life to the extent that radio, television, or the telephone have. Futhermore, in re- cent years, quite different methods of recording sound have been developed, such as the magnetic tape recorder, and today it would make relatively little difference if there were no phonographs or record players at all. Many of Edisons patents related to improvements of devices that other persons had already invented and that were already in quite usable form. Such improvements, although helpful, cannot be considered of major importance in the overall sweep of history.
But although no single one of Edisons inventions was of overwhelming importance, it is worth remembering that he did not invent just one device, but more than one thousand. It is for this reason that I have ranked Edison higher than such renowned inventors as Guglielmo Marconi and Alexander Graham Bell. </string>
    <!--thirty6-->
    <string name="thirty6_ANTONY_VAN_LEEUWENHOEK">Antony van Leeuwenhoek, the man who discovered microbes, was born in 1632, in the town of Delft, in the Netherlands. He came from a middle-class family, and for most of his adult life held a minor post with the town government.
Leeuwenhoeks great discovery came about because he had taken up microscopy as a hobby. In those days, of course, one could not purchase microscopes in a store, and Leeuwenhoek constructed his own instruments. He was never a professional lens grinder, nor did he ever receive formal instruction in the field; but the skill he developed was truly remarkable, far ex- ceeding that of any of the professionals of his day.
     Although the compound microscope had been invented a generation before he was born, Leeuwenhoek did not make use of it. Instead, by very careful and accurate grinding of small lenses of very short focal length, Leeuwenhoek was able to attain a resolving power greater than that of any of the early compound microscopes. One of his surviving lenses has a magnifying power of about 270 times, and there are indications that he had made even more powerful ones.
Leeuwenhoek was an extremely patient and careful observer, and he was possessed of keen eyesight and unbounded curiosity. With his minute lenses, he examined a wide variety of materials, from human hair to dogs semen; from rain water to small insects; as well as muscle fibers, skin tissues, and many other specimens. He took careful notes, and he made meticulous drawings of the things he observed.
From 1673 on, Leeuwenhoek was in correspondence with the Royal Society of England, the leading scientific society of his day. Despite his lack of advanced education (he had attended an elementary school, but knew no language except Dutch), he was elected a fellow of the society in 1680. He also became a cor- responding member of the Academy of Sciences in Paris.
Leeuwenhoek married twice and had six children, but no grandchildren. He enjoyed good health, and was able to con- tinue working in his later years. Many dignitaries came to visit him, including both the Czar of Russia (Peter the Great) and the Queen of England. He died in 1723, in Delft, at the age of nine- ty.
Leeuwenhoek made many significant discoveries. He was the first person to describe spermatozoa (1677), and one of the earliest to describe red blood corpuscles. He opposed the theory of spontaneous generation of lower forms of life, and presented much evidence against it. He was able to show, for example, that fleas propagate in the usual manner of winged insects.
His greatest discovery came in 1674, when he made the first observations of microbes. It was one of the great seminal discoveries in human history. Inside a small drop of water, Leeuwenhoek had discovered an entire new world, a totally un- suspected new world, teeming with life. And although he did not know it yet, this new world was of very great importance to human beings. Indeed, those "very little animalcules" that he had observed often held the power of life and death over humans. Once he had studied them, Leeuwenhoek was able to find microbes in many different places: in wells and ponds, in rain water, in the mouths and intestines of human beings. He described various types of bacteria, as well as protozoa, and calculated their sizes.
Applications of Leeuwenhoeks great discovery were not to come until the time of Pasteur, almost two centuries later. In fact, the entire subject of microbiology remained practically dor- mant until the nineteenth century, when improved microscopes were developed. One might therefore argue that had Leeuwenhoek never lived, and his discoveries not been made un- til the nineteenth century, it might have made little difference to the progress of science. However, there is no denying that Leeuwenhoek did discover microbes, and that it was through him that the scientific world actually became aware of their ex- istence.
Leeuwenhoek is sometimes regarded as a man who by sheer luck happened to stumble on an important scientific discovery. Nothing could be further from the truth. His discovery of microorganisms was a natural consequence of his careful con- struction of microscopes of unprecedented quality, and of his pa- tience and accuracy as an observer. In other words, his discovery resulted from a combination of skill and hard work-the very an- tithesis of mere luck.
The discovery of microbes is one of the few really important scientific discoveries that is largely attributable to the work of a single person. Leeuwenhoek worked alone. His discovery of pro- tozoa and bacteria was unanticipated and-unlike most other advances in biology-was in no sense a natural outgrowth of previous biological knowledge. It is that factor, together with the importance of the eventual applications of his discovery, which account for his high place on this list.
    </string>
    <!--thirty7-->
    <string name="thirty7_WILLIAM_T_C_MORTON">
The name of William Thomas Green Morton may not ring a bell in the minds of most readers. He was, however, a far more in- fluential person than many more famous men, for Morton was the man principally responsible for the introduction of the use of anesthesia in surgery.
Few inventions in all of history are so highly valued by in- dividual human beings as anesthetics, and few have made as pro- found a difference in the human condition. The grimness of surgery in the days when a patient had to be awake while a surgeon sawed through his bones is frightful to contemplate.The ability to put an end to this kind of pain is certainly one of the greatest gifts that any man ever gave to his fellows.
     Morton was born in 1819, in Charlton, Massachusetts. As a young man, he studied at the Baltimore College of Dental Surgery. In 1842, he began the practice of dentistry. For a while, in 1842 and 1843, he was the partner of Horace Wells, a slightly older dentist who was himself interested in anesthesia. It seems, however, that their partnership was not profitable, and it ended in late 1843.
A year later, Wells began experimenting with nitrous oxide ("laughing gas") as an anesthetic. He was able to use it effectively in his dental practice in Hartford, Connecticut. Unfortunately, however, a public demonstration that he attempted in Boston was unsuccessful.
In his own dental practice, Morton specialized in fitting people for artificial teeth. To do this properly, it was necessary to extract the roots of the old teeth first. Such extraction, in the days before anesthesia, was extremely painful, and the desirability of some means of anesthesia was apparent. Morton correctly judged that nitrous oxide would not be sufficiently effective for his pur-
poses, and he searched for a more powerful agent.
Charles T. Jackson, a learned doctor and scientist whom Morton knew, suggested that he try using ether. That ether had anesthetic properties had been discovered more than three hun- dred years earlier by Paracelsus, a famous Swiss physician and alchemist; one or two similar reports had also been printed dur- ing the first part of the nineteenth century. But neither Jackson, nor any of the persons who had written about ether, had ever used the chemical in a surgical operation.
Ether sounded like a promising possibility to Morton, and he experimented with it, first on animals (including his pet dog) and then on himself. Finally, on September 30, 1846, a perfect opportunity arose for testing ether on a patient. A man named Eben Frost walked into Mortons office with a terrible toothache and a willingness to try anything which might relieve the pain of the necessary extraction. Morton administered ether to him and then pulled his tooth. When Frost regained consciousness, he reported that he had felt no pain. A better result could hardly have been hoped for, and Morton could see success, fame, and fortune in front of him.
Although the operation had been witnessed, and was reported in Boston newspapers the next day, it did not attract widespread attention. Clearly, a more dramatic demonstration was needed. Morton therefore asked Dr. John C. Warren, senior surgeon at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, for an opportunity to give a practical demonstration-before a group of doctors-of his method of preventing pain. Dr. Warren agreed, and a demonstration was scheduled at the hospital. There, on October 16, 1846, before a considerable audience of doctors and medical students, Morton administered ether to a surgical patient, Gilbert Abbott; Dr. Warren then removed a tumor from Abbotts neck. The anesthetic proved completely effective, and the demonstration was an overwhelming success. That demonstration, which was promptly reported in many
newspapers, was directly responsible for the widespread use of anesthetics in surgical operations over the course of the next few years.
Several days after the operation on Abbott, an application for a patent was filed by Morton and Jackson. Although a patent was granted to them the following month, it did not prevent a series of priority fights from arising. Mortons claim that he was entitled to most of the credit for the introduction of anesthesia was contested by a few other persons, particularly by Jackson. Furthermore, Mortons expectation that his innovation would make him rich was not fulfilled. Most doctors and hospitals who made use of ether did not bother to pay any royalties. The costs of litigation and of his struggle for priority soon exceeded.the money that Morton received for his invention. Frustrated and impoverished, he died in 1868, in New York City. He was not quite forty-nine years old.
The usefulness of anesthesia in dentistry and in major surgery is obvious. In estimating Mortons overall importance, therefore, the main difficulty is in deciding to what extent credit for the introduction of anesthesia should be divided between Morton and the various other men involved. The principal other persons to be considered are: Horace Wells, Charles Jackson, and Crawford W. Long, a Georgia doctor. On considering the facts, it appears to me that Mortons contribution was far more impor- tant that any of the others, and I have ranked him accordingly.
It is true enough that Horace Wells had started using anesthesia in his dental practice almost h:vo years before Mor- tons successful use of ether. But the anesthetic that Wells used, nitrous oxide, did not and could not have revolutionized surgery.
Despite some desirable qualities, nitrous oxide is simply not a powerful enough anesthetic to be used alone in major surgery. (It is useful today when employed in a sophisticated combination with other drugs, and also in some dental work.) Ether, on the other hand, is an amazingly effective and versatile chemical, and its use revolutionized surgery. In most individual cases today, a more desirable drug, or combination of drugs, than ether can be found; but for roughly a century after its introduction, ether was the anesthetic most usually employed. Despite its disadvantages (it is inflammable, and nausea is a common after-effect of its use), it is still perhaps the most versatile single anesthetic ever discovered. It is easy to transport and to administer; and, most important of all, combines safety and potency.
Crawford W. Long (born 1815, died 1878) was a Georgian doctor who had used ether in surgical operations as early as 1842, which was four years before Mortons demonstration. However, Long did not publish his results until 1849, which was long after Mortons demonstration had made the usefulness of ether in surgery well known to the medical world. As a result, Longs work benefited only a handful of patients, whereas Mortons work benefited the world at large.
Charles Jackson suggested the use of ether to Morton, and he also gave Morton helpful advice on how to administer ether to patients. On the other hand, Jackson himself never made any significant use of ether in a surgical operation; nor, prior to 1-10r- tons successful demonstration, did Jackson make any attempt to inform the medical world of what he did know about ether. It was Morton, not Jackson, who risked his reputation by making a public demonstration. If Gilbert Abbott had died on the operating table, it seems exceedingly unlikely that Charles T. Jackson would have claimed any responsibility for the demonstration.
Where does William Morton belong on this list? An apt comparison could be made between Morton and Joseph Lister. Both were medical men; both are famous for introducing a new technique or procedure that revolutionized surgery and childbearing; both of the innovations seem, in hindsight, to have been fairly obvious; neither man was actually the first to employ the technique or procedure which was publicized and popular- ized through his efforts; and each must share the credit for his in-
novation with others. I have ranked Morton higher than Lister principally because I believe that in the long run the introduction ofanesthesia was a more important development than the introduc- tion of antiseptic surgery. After all, to some extent, modern antibi- otics can substitute for the lack of antiseptic measures during surgery. Without anesthesia, delicate or prolonged operations were not feasible, and even simple operations were often avoided until it was too late for them to be of help.
The public demonstration of a practical means of anesthesia
that Morton gave on that October morning in 1846 is one of the
great dividing points in human history. Perhaps nothing sums up
Mortons achievement better than the inscription on his monu- ment:</string>
    <!--thirty8-->
    <string name="thirty8_GUGLIELMO_MARCONI">Guglielmo Marconi, the inventor of the radio, was born in Bologna, Italy, in 1874. His family was quite well-to-do, and he was educated by private tutors. In 1894, when he was twenty years old, Marconi read of the experiments that Heinrich Hertz had performed a few years earlier. Those experiments had clear- ly demonstrated the existence of invisible electromagnetic waves, which move through the air with the speed of light.
Marconi was immediately fired by the idea that these waves could be used to send signals across great distances without wires. This would provide many possibilities of communication that were not possible with the telegraph. For example, by this method messages might be sent to ships at sea.
By 1895, after only a years work, Marconi succeeded in pro-ducing a working device. In 1896, he demonstrated his device in England, and received his first patent on the invention. Marconi soon formed a company, and the first "Marconigrams" were sent in 1898. The following year, he was able to send wireless messages across the English Channel. Although his most impor- tant patent was granted in 1900, Marconi continued to make and patent many improvements on his invention. In 1901, he suc- ceeded in sending a radio message across the Atlantic Ocean, from England to Newfoundland.
The importance of the new invention was dramatically illustrated in 1909, when the S.S. Republic was damaged in a collision and sank at sea. Radio messages brought help, and all but six persons were rescued. That same year, Marconi won a Nobel Prize for his invention. The following year, he succeeded in transmitting radio messages from Ireland to Argentina, a distance of over six thousand miles.
All these messages, by the way, were sent in the dot-and- dash system of Morse code. It was known that the voice could also be transmitted by radio, but this was not done until 1906.Radio broadcasting on a commercial scale only began in the early 1920s, but then its popularity and importance grew very quickly.
An invention to which the patent rights were so extremely valuable was certain to stimulate legal disputes. Ho\vever, this litigation died out after 1914, when the courts recognized Mar- conis clear priority. In his later years, Marconi did significant research in shortwave and microwave communication. He died in Rome, in 1937.
Since Marconi is famous only as an inventor, it is clear that his influence is proportional to the importance of radio and its direct offshoots. (Marconi did not invent television. However, the invention of radio was a very important precursor of tele- vision, and it therefore seems just to give Marconi part of the credit for the development of television as well.) Obviously, wireless communication is enormously important in the modern world. It is used for the transmission of news, for entertainment, for military purposes, for scientific research, and in police work, as well as for other purposes. Although for some purposes the telegraph (which had been invented more than half a century earlier) would serve almost as well, for a large number of uses the
radio is irreplaceable. It can reach automobiles, ships at sea, airplanes in flight, and even spacecraft. It is plainly a more im- portant invention than the telephone, since a message sent by telephone might be sent by radio instead, whereas radio messages can be sent to places that cannot be reached by telephone.
Marconi has been ranked higher on this list than Alexander Graham Bell, simply because wireless communication is a more important invention than the telephone. I have ranked Edison slightly above Marconi because of the vast number of his inven- tions, even though no one of them is nearly as important as the radio. Since radio and television are only a small part of the prac- tical applications of the theoretical work of Michael Faraday and James Clerk Maxwell, it seems fair that Marconi should be rank- ed considerably below those two men. It seems equally clear that only a handful of the most important political figures have had as much influence on the world as Marconi has had, and therefore, he is entitled to a fairly high place on this list.</string>
    <!--thirty9-->
    <string name="thirty9_ADOLF_HITLER">I must confess that it is with a feeling of disgust that I include Adolf Hitler in this book. His influence was almost entirely per- nicious, and I have no desire to honor a man whose chief im- portance lies in his having caused the deaths of some thirty-five million people. However, there is no getting away from the fact that Hitler had an enormous influence upon the lives of a very great number of persons.
Adolf Hitler was born in 1889, in Braunau, Austria. As a young man, he was an unsuccessful artist, and sometime during his youth he became an ardent German nationalist. During World \Var I, he served in the German army, was wounded, and received two medals for bravery.
Germanys defeat left him shocked and angered. In 1919, when he was thirty, he joind a tiny, right-wing party in Munich, which soon changed its name to the National Socialist German Workers Party (the Nazi party, for short). Within two years he had become its undisputed leader (in German: Fuehrer).
Under Hitlers leadership, the Nazi party rapidly increased in strength, and in November 1923, it attempted a coup detat known as "the Munich Beer Hall Putsch." \Vhen the putsch failed, Hitler was arrested, tried for treason, and convicted. However, he was released from jail after serving less than one year of his sentence.
In 1928, the Nazi party was still small. However, the advent of the Great Depression caused a general public disaffection with the established German political parties. The Nazis rapidly gain- ed strength, and in January 1933, at the age of fourty-four, Hitler became chancellor of Germany.
Upon becoming chancellor, Hitler rapidly established a dic- tatorship by using the government apparatus to crush all oppo- sition. It should not be thought that this process consisted of a gradual erosion of civil liberties and the rights of criminal defen- dants. It was accomplished very quickly, and the Nazis frequent- ly did not bother with trials at all. Many political opponents were beaten up, or simply murdered outright. Still, in the pre-war years, Hitler gained the genuine support. of most Ger- mans, because he was able to reduce unemployment and gener- ate economic recovery.
Hitler then set Germany on a path of conquest that was to produce WorId War II. He achieved his first territorial gains without actually going to war. England and France, beset with their own economic problems, so desperately desired peace that they did not intervene when Hitler violated the Treaty of Ver- sailles by building up the German army, nor when his troops oc- cupied and fortified the Rhineland (March 1936), nor when he forcibly annexed Austria (March 1938). They even acquiesced (September 1938) to his annexation of the Sudetenland, the well- fortified border region of Czechoslovakia. An inter- national agreement known as the Munich Pact, which the British and French hoped would buy "peace in our time," left Czechoslovakia helpless, and Hitler took over the rest of that country a few months later. At each stage, Hitler cleverly com- bined arguments justifying his actions with the threat that he would go to war if his desires were thwarted, and at each stage, the Western democracies timidly backed down.
England and France, however, were determined to defend Poland, Hitlers next target. Hitler first protected himself by signing, in August 1939, a "non-aggression" pact with Stalin (ac- tually an offensive alliance, in which the two dictators agreed on how to divide Poland between them). Nine days later, Germany attacked Poland, and sixteen days after that, the Soviet Union did also. Though England and France declared war on Ger-
many, Poland was quickly defeated.
Hitlers greatest year was 1940. In April, his armies gobbled
up Denmark and Norway. In May, they overran Holland, Belgium, and Luxembourg. In June, France capitulated. But later that year, the British withstood a long series of attacks by the German air force-the celebrated "Battle of Britain"-and Hitler was never able to launch an invasion of England.
Hitlers armies conquered Greece and Yugoslavia in April 1941. In June 1941, Hitler tore up his non-aggression pact with the Russians and attacked them, too. His armies conquered enor- mous stretches of Soviet territory, but were unable to eliminate the Russian armies before winter. Though already fighting both England and Russia, Hitler nevertheless declared war on the United States in December 1941, a few days after the Japanese had attacked the United States naval base at Pearl Harbor.
By the middle of 1942, Germany ruled a larger portion of Europe than had ever been controlled by any nation in history; in addition, she ruled much of North Africa. The turning point of the war came in the last half of 1942, when Germany lost the crucial battles of El Alamein in Egypt and Stalingrad in Russia.After those setbacks, German military fortunes declined steadily. But although Germanys eventual defeat should now have seem- ed inevitable, Hitler refused to give up. Despite fearful casual- ties, Germany continued fighting for more than two years after Stalingrad. The bitter end came in the spring of 1945. Hitler committed suicide in Berlin on April 30; seven days later, Ger- many surrendered.
During his years in power, Hitler engaged in a policy of genocide \vithout parallel in history. He was a fanatical racist, with a particularly virulent animosity toward the Jews. He made it his specific, publicly-stated goal to kill every Jew in the world. During his regime, the Nazis constructed large extermination camps, equipped with massive gas chambers for this purpose. In every territory that came under his control, innocent men, women, and chlIdren were rounded up and shipped off in cattle cars to be killed in those chambers. In the space of just a few years, almost 6,000,000 Jews died in this way.
The Jews were not Hitlers only victims. During his regime, staggering numbers of Russians and gypsies were also massacred, as well as many others who were deemed to be either racially in- ferior or enemies of the state. It should never be imagined that these murders were spontaneous acts, performed in the heat and passion of battle: Hitlers death camps were organized as careful- ly as a great business enterprise. Records were kept, quotas set, and the bodies of the dead systematically searched for such valuables as gold tooth fillings and wedding rings. The bodies of many of the victims were also utilized for the manufacture of soap. So intent upon this program of murder was Hitler, that even late in the war, when Germany was short of fuel for domestic and military use, the cattle cars were kept rolling to the death camps on their grisly-but militarily useless-mission.
For several reasons, it seems obvious that Hitlers fame will last. In the first place, he is widely considered to be the most evil man in all of history. If men like Nero and Caligula, whose misdeeds \vere small in comparison with Hitlers, have remained well-known for twenty centuries as symbols of cruelty, it seems
safe to predict that Hitler, whose reputation as the most evil per- son in history is uncontested, will remain famous for many, many centuries. In addition, of course, Hitler will be remem- bered as the principal instigator of World War II, the largest war the world has yet seen. The advent of nuclear weapons makes it very unlikely that there will be many such large-scale wars in the future. Therefore, even two or three thousand years from now, World War II will probably be considered a major event in history.
Furthermore, Hitler will remain famous because his entire story is so bizarre and so interesting. That a foreigner (Hitler was born in Austria, not Germany) without political experience, money, or political connections could, in a period of less than fourteen years, become the head of a major world power, is truly amazing. His ability as an orator was extraordinary. Judged by his ability to move people to significant action, it is likely that Hitler was the most effective orator in all of history. Finally, the fiendish uses to which he put his power, once he had attained it, will not soon be forgotten.
It is probable that no figure in history has had more in- fluence upon his own generation than Adolf Hitler. In ad- dition to the tens of millions of people who died in the war that he instigated, or in the Nazi concentration canlps, there were millions more who were made homeless or whose lives were en- tirely disrupted as a result of the fighting.
Any estimate of Hitlers influence must take into consider- ation two other factors. First, much of what actually occurred under his leadership would probably not have occurred at all had it not been for Hitler. (In this respect, he stands in sharp contrast to such persons as, say, Charles Darwin or Simon Bolivar.) It is true, of course, that the situation in Germany and in Europe pro- vided Hitler with an opportunity. His militaristic and anti- Semitic remarks, for example, certainly struck a responsive chord in many of his listeners. There is no sign, however, that most Germans in the 1920s or 1930s either wanted or intended their government to follow a policy nearly as extreme as Hitlers proved, and there is little indication that other potential German leaders would have done the same thing. Nor, in fact, were the actual events of the Hitler era even approximately predicted by any outside observer.
Second, the entire Nazi movement was dominated by a single leader to an extraordinary degree. Marx, Lenin, Stalin, and others all played major roles in the rise of Communism. But National Socialism had no significant leader before Hitler, and none after him. He led the Nazis to power, and maintained his leadership throughout their period in power. When he died, the Nazi party and the government it headed died with him.
But though Hitlers influence on his own generation was so enormous, the effects of his actions upon future ages seem to be rather slight. Hitler totally failed to accomplish any of his major goals, and what little effect he appears to have had on later generations seems to be in the opposite direction from what he intended. For example, Hitler was interested in expanding Ger- man influence and territory. But his territorial conquests, although very large, were ephemeral, and today Germany has less territory than it did when Hitler took office. It was Hitlers consum-ing passion to destroy the Jews; but fifteen years after Hitler took office, an independent Jewish state came into existence for the first time in 2,000 years. Hitler hated both Communism and Russia. However, at his death, and partly as a result of the war he started, the Russians were able to extend their control over a large part of eastern Europe, and Communist influence in the world was greatly expanded. Hitler despised democracy and hoped to destroy it, not just in other nations, but in Germany, too. Nevertheless, Germany is a functioning democracy today, and her citizens appear to have far less tolerance for authoritarian rule than any generation of Ger- mans before Hitlers time ever had.
What does this strange combination of enormous influence in his own day and relatively little influence on future gener- ations add up to? Hitlers effect upon the world of his day was so enormous that it is obvious that he must be ranked fairly high on this list. But he surely must be placed well behind such figures as Shih Huang Ti, Augustus Caesar, and Genghis Khan, whose ac- tions influenced the world for centuries after they lived. The closest parallels are with Napoleon and Alexander the Great. In the short run, Hitler disturbed the world even more than those two men did; he has been ranked slightly below them because of their greater long-term influence.</string>
    <!--forty-->
    <string name="forty_PLATO">The ancient Greek philosopher Plato represents the starting point of Western political philosophy, and of much of our ethical and metaphysical thought as well. His speculations on these subjects have been read and studied for over 2,300 years. Plato stands, therefore, as one of the great fathers of Western thought.
Plato was born into a distinguished Athenian family, in about 427 B.C. As a young man, he made the acquaintance of the noted philosopher Socrates, who became his friend and mentor. In 399 B .C ., Socrates, then seventy years old, was tried on rather vague charges of impiety and of corrupting the youth of Athens. Socrates was condemned, sentenced to death, and executed. The execution of Socrates-whom Plato calls "the wisest, the justest, and the best of all the men whom I have ever known"-left Plato with an enduring distaste for democratic government.
Not long after the death of Socrates, Plato left Athens and spent the next ten or twelve years in foreign travel. About 387 B .C ., he returned to Athens and founded a school there, the Academy, which continued in operation for over nine hundred years. Plato spent most of his remaining forty years in Athens, teaching and writing philosophy. His most famous pupil was Aristotle, who came to the Academy when he was seventeen years old and Plato sixty. Plato died in 347 B.C., at the age of eighty.
Plato wrote thirty-six books, mostly on political and ethical questions, but also on metaphysics and theology. Obviously, it is not possible to summarize these works in a few short sentences. However, at the risk of oversimplifying his thought, I will try to summarize the main political ideas expressed in Platos most famous book, The Republic, which represents his concept of an ideal society.
The best form of government, Plato suggests, is an aristocracy. By this he means not an hereditary aristocracy, or a monarchy, but an aristocracy of merit-that is, rule by the best and wisest persons in the state. These persons should be chosen not by a vote of the citizens, but by a process of co-optation. The persons who are already members of the ruling, or guardian class should admit additional persons to their ranks purely on the basis of merit.
Plato believed that all persons, both male and female, should be given the chance to demonstrate their fitness to be members of the guardian class. (Plato was the first major philosopher, and for a long time virtually the only one, to suggest the basic equality of the sexes.) To insure equality of opportun- ity, Plato advocated the rearing and education of all children by the state. Children should first receive a thorough physical train- ing; but music, mathematics, and other academic disciplines should not be neglected. At several stages, extensive exa.min- ations should be given. The less successful persons should be assigned to engage in the economic activity of the community, while the more successful persons should continue to receive fur- ther training. This additional education should include not only
the normal academic subjects, but also the study of "philoso-phy," by which Plato means the study of his metaphysical doc- trine of ideal forms.
At age thirty-five, those persons who have convincingly demonstrated their mastery of theoretical principles are to receive an additional fifteen years of training, which should con- sist of practical working experience. Only those persons who show that they can apply their book learning to the real world should be admitted into the guardian class. Moreover, only those persons who clearly demonstrate that they are primarily in- terested in the public welfare are to become guardians.
Membership in the guardian class would not appeal to all persons. The guardians are not to be wealthy. They should be permitted only a minimal amount of personal property, and no land or private homes. They are to receive a fixed (and not very large) salary, and may not own either gold or silver. Members of the guardian class should not be permitted to have separate families, but are to eat together, and are to have mates in com- mon. The compensation of these philosopher-kings should not be material wealth, but rather the satisfaction of public service. Such, in brief, was Platos view of the ideal republic.
The Republic has been widely read for many centuries. It should be noted, however, that the political system advocated therein has not been used as the model for any actual civil government. During most of the interval between Platos day and our own, most European states have been governed by hereditary monarchies. In recent centuries, several states have adopted democratic forms of government; there have also been instances of military rule, or of demagogic tyrannies, such as those of Hitler and Mussolini. None of those forms of government is similar to Platos ideal republic. Platos theories have never been adopted by any political party, nor have they formed the basis of a political movement in the way that the theories of Karl Marx have. Should we therefore conclude that Platos works, though spoken of with respect, have been completely ignored in practice? I think not.
H is true that no civil gove.rnment in Europe has been pat-terned directly on Platos model; nevertheless, there is a striking similarity between the position of the Catholic Church in medieval Europe and that of Platos guardian class. The medieval Church consisted of a self-perpetuating elite, whose members had all received training in an offical philosophy. In principle, all males, regardless of family background, were eligi- ble to enter the priesthood (although females were excluded). In principle, too, the clergy had no families, and it was intended that they should be motivated primarily by concern for their flock, rather than by a desire for self-aggrandizement.
Platos ideas have also influenced the structure of the United States government. Many members of the American Constitu- tional Convention were familiar with Platos political ideas. It was intended, of course, that the United States Constitution would provide a means of discovering and giving effect to the popular will. But it was also intended as a means for selecting the wisest and best persons to govern the nation.
The difficulty in assessing Platos importance is that his in- fluence through the ages, while broad and pervasive, has been subtle and indirect. In addition to his political theories, his discussions of ethics ,and metaphysics have influenced many subsequent philosophers. If Plato has been ranked considerably lower than Aristotle on the present list, it is principally because Aristotle was an important scientist as well as a philosopher. On the other hand, Plato has been ranked higher than such thinkers as Thomas Jefferson and Voltaire, because their political writings have so far affected the world for only two or three centuries, while the influence of Plato has endured for over twenty-three centuries.</string>
    
</resources>