<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <!--One Muhammad-->
    <string name="OneMUHAMMAD">My choice of Muhammad to lead the list of the worlds most in- fluential persons may surprise some readers and may be question- ed by others, but he was the only man in history who was supremely successful on both the religious and secular levels.
Of humble origins, Muhammad founded and promulgated one of the worlds great religions, and became an immensely ef- fective political leader. Today, thirteen centuries after his death, his influence is still powerful and pervasive.
The majority of the persons in this book had the advantage of being born and raised in centers of civilization, highly cultured or politically pivotal nations. Muhammad, however, was born in the year 570, in the city of Mecca, in southern
    Arabia, at that time a backward area of the world, far from the centers of trade, art, and learning. Orphaned at age six, he was reared in modest surroundings. Islamic tradition tells us that he was illiterate. His economic position improved when, at age twenty-five, he married a wealthy widow. Nevertheless, as he approached forty, there was little outward indication that he was a remarkable person.
Most Arabs at that time were pagans, and believed in many gods. There were, however, in Mecca, a small number of Jews and Christians; it was from them, most probably, that Muhammad first learned ofa single, omnipotent God who ruled the entire universe. When he was forty years old, Muhammad became convinced that this one true God (Allah) was speaking to him (through the Arch- angel Gabriel) and had chosen him to spread the true faith.
For three years, Muhammad preached only to close friends and associates. Then, about 613, he began preaching in public. As he slowly gained converts, the Meccan authorities came to consider him a dangerous nuisance. In 622, fearing for his safety, Muhammad fled to Medina (a city some 200 miles north of Mec- ca), where he had been offered a position of considerable political power.
This flight, called the Hegira, was the turning point of the Prophets life. In Mecca, he had had few followers. In Medina, he had many more, and he soon acquired an influence that made him virtually an absolute ruler. During the next few years, while Muhammads following grew rapidly, a series of battles were fought between Medina and Mecca. This war ended in 630 with Muham- mads triumphant return to Mecca as conqueror. The remaining two and one-half years of his life witnessed the rapid conversion of the Arab tribes to the new religion. When Muhammad died, in
632, he was the effective ruler of all of southern Arabia.
The Bedouin tribesmen of Arabia had a reputation as fierce warriors. But their number was small; and plagued by disunity and internecine warfare, they had been no match for the larger armies of the kingdoms in the settled agricultural areas to the north. However, unified by Muhammad for the first time in
    history, and inspired by their fervent belief in the one true God, these small Arab armies now embarked upon one of the most astonishing series of conquests in human history. To the northeast of Arabia lay the large Neo-Persian Empire of the Sassanids; to the northwest lay the Byzantine, or Eastern Roman Empire, centered in Constantinople. Numerically, the Arabs were no match for their opponents. On the field of battle, though, it was far different, and the inspired Arabs rapidly con- quered all of Mesopotamia, Syria, and Palestine. By 642, Egypt had been wrested from the Byzantine Empire, while the Persian armies had been crushed at the key battles of Qadisiya in 637, and
Nehavend in 642.
But even these enormous conquests-which were made
under the leadership of Muhammads close friends and im- mediate successors, Abu Bakr and Umar ibn al-Khattab-did not mark the end of the Arab advance. By 711, the Arab armies had swept completely across North Africa to the Atlantic Ocean. There they turned north and, crossing the Strait of Gibraltar, overwhelmed the Visigothic kingdom in Spain.
For a while, it must have seemed that the Moslems would overwhelm all of Christian Europe. However, in 732, at the famous Battle of Tours, a Moslem army, which had advanced in- to the center of France, was at last defeated by the Franks. Nevertheless, in a scant century of fighting, these Bedouin tribesmen, inspired by the word of the Prophet, had carved out an empire stretching from the borders of India to the Atlantic Ocean-the largest empire that the world had yet seen. And everywhere that the armies conquered, large-scale conversion to the new faith eventually followed.
Now, not all of these conquests proved permanent. The Per- sians, though they have remained faithful to the religion of the Prophet, have since regained their independence from the Arabs. And in Spain, more than seven centuries of warfare finally re- sulted in the Christians reconquering the entire peninsula. How- ever, Mesopotamia and Egypt, the two cradles of ancient civili- zation, have remained Arab, as has the entire coast of North
    Africa. The new religion, of course, continued to spread, in the intervening centuries, far beyond the borders of the original Moslem conquests. Currently, it has tens of millions of adherents in Africa and Central Asia, and even more in Pakistan and nor- thern India, and in Indonesia. In Indonesia, the new faith has been a unifying factor. In the Indian subcontinent, however, the
conflict between Moslems and Hindus is still a major obstacle to unity.
How, then, is one to assess the overall impact of Muham- mad on human history? Like all religions, Islam exerts an enor- mous influence upon the lives of its followers. It is for this reason that the founders of the worlds great religions all figure promi- nently in this book. Since there are roughly twice as many Chris- tians as Moslems in the world, it may initially seem strange that
    Muhammad has been ranked higher than Jesus. There are two principal reasons for that decision. First, Muhammad played a far more important role in the development of Islam than Jesus did in the development of Christianity. Although JesllS was re- sponsible for the main ethical and moral precepts of Christianity (insofar as these differed from Judaism), it was St. Paul who was the main developer of Christian theology, its principal proselytizer,
and the author of a large portion of the New Testament. Muhammad, however, was responsible for both the theology of Islam and its main ethical and moral principles. In addition, he played the key role in proselytizing the new faith, and in establish-
ing the religious practices of Islam. Moreover, he is the author of the Moslem holy scriptures, the Koran, a collection of Muham- mads statements that he believed had been divinely inspired. Most of these utterances were copied more or less faithfully during Muhammads lifetime and were collected together in authoritative form not long after his death. The Koran, therefore, closely repre- sents Muhammads ideas and teachings and, to a considerable extent, his exact words. No such detailed compilation of the teach- ings of Christ has survived. Since the Koran is at least as impor- tant to Moslems as the Bible is to Christians, the influence of Muhammad through the medium of the Koran has been enormous. It is probable that the relative influence of Muhammad on Islam has been larger than the combined influence of Jesus Christ and St. Paul on Christianity. On the purely religious level, then, it seems likely that Muhammad has been as influential in human history as Jesus.
Furthermore, Muhammad (unlike Jesus) was a secular as well as a religious leader. In fact, as the driving force behind the Arab conquests, he may well rank as the most influential political leader of all time.
Of many important historical events, one might say that they were inevitable and would have occurred even without the particular political leader who guided them. For example, the South American colonies would probably have won their inde- pendence from Spain even if Simon BolIvar had never lived. But
    this cannot be said of the Arab conquests. Nothing similar had occurred before Muhammad, and there is no reason to believe that the conquests would have been achieved without him. The only comparable conquests in human history are those of the Mongols in the thirteenth century, which were primarily due to the influence of Genghis Khan. These conquests, however, though more extensive than those of the Arabs, did not prove permanent, and today the only areas occupied by the Mongols are those that they held prior to the time of Genghis Khan.
It is far different with the conquests of the Arabs. From Iraq to Morocco, there extends a whole chain of Arab nations united not merely by their faith in Islam, but also by their Arabic language, history, and culture. The centrality of the Koran in the Moslem religion and the fact that it is written in Arabic have probably prevented the Arab language from breaking up into mutually unintelligible dialects, \vhich might othenvise have oc- curred in the intervening thirteen centuries. Differences and divisions between these Arab states exist, of course, and they are considerable, but the partial disunity should not blind us to the important elements of unity that have continued to exist. For in-
stance, neither Iran nor Indonesia, both oil-producing states and both Islamic in religion, joined in the oil embargo of the \vinter of 1973-74. It is no coincidence that all of the Arab states, and only the Arab states, participated in the embargo.
We see, then, that the Arab conquests of the seventh cen- tury have continued to play an important role in human history, down to the present day. It is this unparalleled combination of secular and religious influence which I feel entitles Muhammad to be considered the most influential single figure in human history.
    </string>
    <!--Two ISAAC_NEWTON-->
    <string name="two_ISAAC_NEWTON">Isaac Newton, the greatest and most influential scientist who ever lived, was born in Woolsthorpe, England, on Christmas Day, 1642, the same year that Galileo died. Like Muhammad, he was born after the death of his father. As a child, he showed considerable mechanical aptitude, and was very clever with his hands. Although a bright child, he was inattentive in school and did not attract much attention. When he was a teenager, his mother took him out of school, hoping that he would become a successful farmer. Fortunately, she was persuaded that his prin- cipal talents lay elsewhere, and at eighteen, he entered Cam- bridge University. There, he rapidly absorbed what was then kno\vn of science and mathematics, and soon moved on to his own independent research. Between his twenty-first and twenty-seventh years, he laid the foundations for the scientific theories that subsequently revolutionized the world.
The middle of the seventeenth century \vas a period of great scientific ferment. The invention of the telescope near the begin-
    ning of the century had revolutionized the entire study of astronomy. The English philosopher Francis Bacon and the French philosopher Rene Descartes had both urged scientists throughout Europe to cease relying on the authority of Aristotle and to experiment and observe for themselves. What Bacon and Descartes had preached, the great GaBleo had practiced. His astronomical observations, using the newly invented telescope, had revolutionized the study of astronomy, and his mechanical experiments had established what is now known as Newtons first law of motion.
Other great scientists, such as William Harvey, who discovered the circulation of the blood, and Johannes Kepler, who discovered the laws describing the motions of the planets around the sun, were bringing new basic information to the scientific community. Still, pure science was largely a plaything of intellectuals, and as yet there was no proof that when applied to technology, science could revolutionize the whole mode of human life, as Francis Bacon had predicted.
Although Copernicus and Galileo had swept aside some of the misconceptions of ancient science and contributed to a great- er understanding of the universe, no set of principles had been formulated that could turn this collection of seemingly unrelated
. facts into a unified theory with which to make scientific predic- tions. It was Isaac Newton who supplied that unified theory and set modern science on the course which it has followed ever since.
Ne\vton was always reluctant to publish his results, and although he had formulated the basic ideas behind most of his work by 1669, many of his theories were not made public until much later. The first of his discoveries to be published was his ground-breaking work on the nature of light. In a series of careful experiments, Newton had discovered that ordinary white light is a mixture of all the colors of the rainbow. He had also made a careful analysis of the consequences of the laws of the reflection and refraction of light. Using these laws, he had in 1668 designed and actually built the first reflecting telescope, the type of telescope that is used in most major astronomical obser-
    vatories today. These discoveries, together with the results of many other optical experiments which he had performed, were presented by Newton before the British Royal Society when he was twenty-nine years old.
Newtons achievements in optics alone would probably enti- tle him to a place on this list; however, they are considerably less important than his accomplishments in pure mathematics and mechanics. His major mathematical contribution was his inven- tion of integral calculus, which he probably devised when he was twenty-three or twenty-four years old. That invention, the most important achievement of modern mathematics, is not merely the seed out of which much of modern mathematical theory has grown, it is also the essential tool without which most of the subsequent progess in modern science would have been impos- sible. Had Newton done nothing else, the invention of integral calculus by itself would have entitled him to a fairly high place on this list.
Newtons most important discoveries, however, were in the field of mechanics, the science of how material objects move. Galileo had discovered the first law of motion, which describes the motion of objects if they are not subjected to any exterior forces. In practice, of course, all objects are subjected to exterior forces, and the most important question in mechanics is how ob- jects move under such circumstances. This problem was solved by Newton in his famous second law of motion, which may right- ly be considered the most fundamental law of classical physics. The second law (described mathematically by the equation F = rna) states that the acceleration of an object (Le., the rate at which its velocity changes) is equal to the net force on the object divided by the objects mass. To those first two laws, Newton ad- ded his famous third law of motion (which states that for each action-i.e., physical force-there is an equal and opposite reac- tion), and the most famous of his scientific laws, the law of
universal gravitation. This set of four laws, taken conjointly, form a unified system by means of which virtually all macro- scopic mechanical systems, from the swinging of a pendulum to
    the motion of the planets in their orbits around the sun, may be investigated, and their behavior predicted. Newton did not merely state these laws of mechanics; he himself, using the math- ematical tools of the calculus, showed how these fundamental laws could be applied to the solution of actual problems.
Newtons laws can be and have been applied to an extremely broad range of scientific and engineering problems. During his lifetime, the most dramatic application of his laws was made in the field of astronomy. In this area, too, Newton led the way. In 1687, he published his great work, the Mathematical Principles oj Natural Philosophy (usually referred to simply as the Principia), in \vhich he presented his law of gravitation and laws of motion. Newton showed how these laws could be used to pre- dict precisely the motions of the planets around the sun. The principal problem of dynamical astronomy- that is, the problem of predicting exactly the positions and motions of the stars and planets-was thereby completely solved by Newton in one mag- nificent sweep. For this reason, Newton is often considered the greatest of all astronomers.
What, then, is our assessment of Newtons scientific im- portance? If one looks at the index of an encyclopedia of science, one will find more references (perhaps two or three times as many) to Newton and to his laws and discoveries than to any other individual scientist. Furthermore, one should consider what other great scientists have said about Newton. Leibniz, no friend of Sir Isaacs, and a man with whom he engaged in a bitter dispute, wrote: "Taking mathematics from the beginning of the world to the time when Newton lived, what he has done is much the better part." The great French scientist Laplace wrote: "The Principia is preeminent above any other production of human genius." Lagrange frequently stated that Newton was the great- est genius      ever lived, while Ernst Mach, writing in 1901, said: "All that has been accomplished in mathematics since his day has been a deductive, formal, and mathematical develop- ment of mechanics on the basis of Newtons laws." This, per- haps, is the crux of Newtons great accomplishment: he found
    science a hodgepodge of isolated facts and laws, capable of de- scribing some phenomena but of predicting only a few; he left us a unified system of la\vs, which were capable of application to an enormous range of physical phenomena, and which could be used to make exact predictions.
In a brief summary like this, it is not possible to detail all of Newtons discoveries; consequently, many of the lesser ones have
    been omitted, although they were important achievements in their own right. Newton made significant contributions to ther- modynamics (the study of heat) and to acoustics (the study of sound); he enunciated the extremely important physical prin- ciples of conservation of momentum and conservation of angular momentum; he discovered the binomial theorem in mathema- tics; and he gave the first cogent explanation of the origin of the stars.
Now, one might grant that Newton was by far the greatest and most influential scientist who ever lived but still ask why he should be ranked higher than such major political figures as Alex- ander the Great or George Washington, and ahead of such major religious figures as Jesus Christ and Gautama Buddha. My own view is that even though political changes are of significance, it is fair to say that most people in the world were living the same way 500 years after Alexanders death as their forebears had lived five centuries before his time. Similarly, in most of their daily ac- tivities, the majority of human beings were living the same way in 1500 A.D. as human beings had been living in 1500 B.C .. In the last five centuries, however, with the rise of modern science, the everyday life of most human beings has been completely revolu- tionized. We dress differently, eat different foods, work at dif- ferent jobs, and spend our leisure time a great deal differently than people did in 1500 A.D. Scientific discoveries have not only revolutionized technology and economics; they have also com- pletely changed politics, religious thinking, art, and philosophy.
Few aspects of human activity have remained unchanged by this scientific revolution, and it is for this reason that so many scien- tists and inventors are to be found on this list. Newton was not only the most brilliant of all scientists; he was also the most influ- ential figure in the development of scientific theory, and there- fore well merits a position at or near the top of any list of the worlds most influential persons.
Newton died in 1727, and was buried in Westminster Ab- bey, the first scientist to be accorded that honor.</string>
    <!--Three JESUS CHRIST-->
    <string name="three_JESUS_CHRIST">The impact of Jesus on human history is so obvious and so enor- mous that few people would question his placement near the top of this list. Indeed, the more likely question is why Jesus, who is the inspiration for the most influential religion in history, has not been placed first.
There is no question that Christianity, over the course of time, has had far more adherents than any other religion. However, it is not the relative influence of different religions that is being estimated in this book, but rather the relative influence of individual men. Christianity, unlike Islam, was not founded by a single person but by two people-Jesus and St. Paul-and the principal credit for its development must therefore be appor- tioned behveen those two figures.
Jesus formulated the basic ethical ideas of Christianity, as well as its basic spiritual outlook and its main ideas concerning human conduct. Christian theology, however, was shaped prin- cipally by the work of St. Paul. Jesus presented a spiritual message; Paul added to that the worship of Christ. Furthermore,
    St. Paul was the author of a considerable portion of the New Testament, and was the main proselytizing force for Christianity during the first century.
Jesus was still fairly young when he died (unlike Buddha or Muhammad), and he left behind a limited number of disciples. At the time of Jesus death, his followers simply formed a small Jewish sect. It was due in considerable n1easure to Pauls writings, and to his tireless proselytizing efforts, that this small sect was transformed into a dynamic and much greater move- ment, which reached non-Jews as well as Jews, and \vhich even- tually grew into one of the great religions of the world.
For these reasons, some people even contend that it is Paul, rather than Jesus, who should really be considered the founder of Christianity. Carried to its logical conclusion, that argument would lead one to place Paul higher on this list than Jesus! However, although it is not clear what Christianity would be like without the influence of St. Paul, it is quite apparent that with- out Jesus, Christianity would not exist at all.
However, it does not seem reasonable to consider Jesus responsible for all the things which Christian churches or in- dividual Christians later did in his name, particularly since he would obviously disapprove of many of those things. Some of them-for example the religious wars between various Christian sects, and the barbaric massacres and persecutions of the Jews- are in such obvious contradiction to the attitudes and teachings of Jesus that it seems entirely unreasonable to say that Jesus in-
spired them.
Similarly, even though modern science first arose in the
Christian nations of western Europe, it seems inappropriate to think of Jesus as responsible for the rise of science. Certainly, none of the early Christians interpreted the teachings of Jesus as a call for scientific investigation of the physical world. Indeed, the conversion of the Roman world to Christianity was accompanied and followed by a drastic decline in both the general level of technology and the general degree of interest in science.
That science did eventually arise in Europe is indeed an in- :dication that there was something in the European cultural
    heritage that was favorable to the scientific way of thinking. That something, however, was not the sayings of Jesus, but rather Greek rationalism, as typified by the works of Aristotle and Euclid. It is noteworthy that modern science developed, not during the heyday of church power and of Christian piety, but rather on the heels of the Renaissance, a period during which Europe experienced a renewal of interest in its pre-Christian heritage.
The story of Jesus life, as it is related in the New Testament, is familiar to most readers and will not be repeated here. However, a few points are worth noting. In the first place, most of the information that \ve have about Jesus life is uncertain. \Ve are not even sure what his original name was. Most probably it was the common Je\vish nan1e, Yehoshua (Joshua in English). The year of his birth, too, is uncertain, although 6 B.C. is a likely date. Even the year of his death, which must have been well known to his follo\vers, is not definitely known today. Jesus himself left no writings behind, and virtually all our information concerning his life comes from the accounts in the New Testa- ment.
Unfortunately, the Gospels contradict each other on various points. For example, Matthew and Luke give completely dif- ferent versions of Jesus last words; both of these versions, inci- dentally, are direct quotations from the Old Testament.
It was no accident that Jesus \vas able to quote from the Old Testament; though the progenitor of Christianity, he was himself a devout Jew. It has been frequently pointed out that Jesus was in many ways very similar to the Hebrew prophets of the Old Testament, and was deeply influenced by them. Like the pro- phets, Jesus had an extraordinarily impressive personality, which made a deep and lasting impression on the people who met him. He was charismatic in the deepest and fullest sense of the word.
However, in sharp contrast to Muhammad, who exercised political as well as religious authority, Jesus had virtually no in- fluence on political developments during his own lifetime, or
Juring the succeeding century. (Both men, of course, have had 1n enormous indirect influence on long-term political develop-
    ments.) Jesus made his influence felt entirely as an ethical and
spiritual leader.
If it was primarily as an ethical leader that Jesus left his mark, it is surely pertinent to ask to what extent his ethical ideas have influenced the world. One of Jesus central precepts, cer- tainly, was the Golden Rule. Today, the Golden Rule is accepted by most people, Christians and non-Christians alike, as a reasonable guide to moral conduct. We may not always act in ac- cordance with it, but we usually try to do so. If Jesus had actual- ly originated that almost universally accepted principle, he would surely have been the first man on this list.
In fact, though, the Golden Rule was an accepted precept of Judaism long before Jesus was born. Rabbi Hillel, the leading Jewish rabbi of the first century B .C ., explicitly enunciated the Golden Rule and pronounced it the foremost principle of Judaism. Nor was the notion known only to the Western world. The Chinese philosopher Confucius had proposed it in about 500 B .C ., and the saying also appears in the Mahabharata, an ancient Hindu poem. In fact, the philosophy behind the Golden Rule is accepted by almost every major religious group.
Does this mean that Jesus had no original ethical ideas? Not at alll A highly distinctive viewpoint is presented in Matthew 5:43-44:
Ye have heard that it hath been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbor, and hate thine enemy_ But I say unto you, Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which despitefully use you, and persecute you.
And a few lines earlier: "...resist not evil: but whosoever shall smite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other also."
Now, these ideas-which were not a part of the Judaism of Jesus day, nor of most other religions-are surely among the most remarkable and original ethical ideas ever presented. If they were widely followed, I would have had no hesitation in placing Jesus first in this book.
But the truth is that they are not widely followed. In fact,
they are not even generally accepted. Most Christians consider the injunction to "Love your enemy" as-at most-an ideal which might be realized in some perfect world, but one which is not a reasonable guide to conduct in the actual world \ve live in. We do not normally practice it, do not expect others to practice it, and do not teach our children to practice it. Jesus most dis- tinctive teaching, therefore, remains an intriguing but basically untried suggestion.
    </string>
    <!--Four BUDDHA-->
    <string name="four_BUDDHA">Gautama Buddha, whose original name was Prince Siddhartha, was the founder of Buddhism, one of the worlds great religions. Siddhartha was the son of a king ruling in Kapilavastu, a city in northeast India, near the borders of Nepal. Siddhartha himself (of the clan of Gautama and the tribe of Sakya) was purportedly born in 563 B .C ., in Lumbini, within the present borders of Nepal. He was married at sixteen to a cousin of the same age. Brought up in the luxurious royal palace, Prince Siddhartha did not want for material comforts. Nevertheless, he \vas profoundly dissatisfied. He observed that most human beings were poor and continually suffered from want. Even those who were wealthy were frequently frustrated and unhappy, and all men were sub-
ject to disease and ultimately succumbed to death. Surely, Sid-
    dhartha thought, there must be more to life than transitory plea- sures, which were all too soon obliterated by suffering and death. When he was twenty-nine, just after the birth of his first son, Gautama decided that he must abandon the life he was liv- ing and devote himself wholeheartedly to the search for truth. He departed from the palace, leaving behind his wife, his infant
son, and all his worldly possessions, and became a penniless \vanderer. For a while he studied with some of the famed holy men of the day, but after mastering their teachings, he found their solutions to the problems of the human situation unsatisfac- tory. It was widely believed that extreme asceticism was the pathway to true wisdom. Gautama therefore attempted to become an ascetic, for several years engaging in extreme fasts and self-mortification. Eventually, however, he realized that tormenting his body only clouded his brain, without leading him any closer to true wisdom. He therefore resumed eating normal- ly, and abandoned asceticism.
In solitude, he grappled with the problems of human ex- istence. Finally, one evening, as he sat beneath a giant fig tree, all the pieces of the puzzle seemed to fall into place. Siddhartha spent the whole night in deep reflection, and when the morning came, he was convinced that he had found the solution and that he \vas now a Buddha, an "enlightened one."
At this time, he was thirty-five years old. For the remaining forty-five years of his life, he traveled throughout northern In- dia, preaching his new philosophy to all who were willing to listen. By the time he died, in 483 B .C ., he had made thousands of
converts. Though his words had not been written down, his disciples had memorized many of his teachings, and they were passed to succeeding generations by word of mouth.
The principal teachings of the Buddha can be summarized in what Buddhists call the "Four Noble Truths": first, that human life is intrinsically unhappy; second, that the cause of this unhappiness is human selfishness and desire; third, that in- dividual selfishness and desire can be brought to an end-the resulting state, when all desires and cravings have been
    eliminated, is termed nirvana (literally "blo\ving out" or "extinc- tion"); fourth, that the method of escape from selfishness and desire is what is called the "Eightfold Path": right views, right thought, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right meditation. It might be added that Buddhism is open to all, regardless of race, and that (unlike Hin- duism) it recognizes no distinctions of caste.
For some time after Gautamas death the new religion spread slowly. In the third century B.C., the great Indian emperor Asoka became converted to Buddhism. His support brought about the rapid expansion of Buddhist influence and teachings in India and the spread of Buddhism to neighboring countries. Buddhism spread south into Ceylon, and eastward in- to Burnla. From there it spread into all of southeast Asia, and down into          and into \vhat is now Indonesia. Buddhism also spread north, directly into Tibet, and to the northwest, into Afghanistan and Central Asia. It spread into China, where it won a large follov,:ing, and from there into Korea and Japan.
Within India itself, the ne\v faith started to decline after about 500, and almost vanished after about 1200. In China and Japan, on the other hand, Buddhism remained a major religion. In Tibet and in southeast Asia, it has been the principal religion for many centuries.
Buddhas teachings were not written down until several centuries after his death, and, understandably, his movement has split into various sects. The two principal divisions of Bud- dhism are the Theravada branch, dominant in southern Asia, and considered by most Western scholars as the one closer to the Buddhas original teachings, and the Mahayana branch, dom-
,inant in Tibet, China, and northern Asia generally.
Buddha, as the founder of one of the worlds major religions, clearly deserved a place near the head of this list. Since there are only about 200 million Buddhists in the world, com- pared with over 500 million Moslems and about one billion Christians, it would seem evident that Buddha has influenced
fewer people than either Muhammad or Jesus. However, the dif-
    ference in numbers can be misleading. One reason that Bud- dhism died out in India is that Hinduism absorbed many of its ideas and principles. In China, too, large numbers of persons who do not call themselves Buddhists have been strongly in- fluenced by Buddhist philosophy.
Buddhism, far more than Christianity or Islam, has a very strong pacifist element. The orientation toward nonviolence has
played a significant role in the political history of Buddhist coun- tries.
    It has often been said that if Christ were to return to earth, he would be shocked at many of the things which have been done in his name, and horrified at the bloody fights between different sects of persons who call themselves his followers. Buddha, too, would doubtless be amazed at many of the doctrines that have been presented as Buddhist. But while there are many sects of Buddhism, and large differences between those sects, there is nothing in Buddhist history that remotely compares with the bloody religious wars that took place in Christian Europe. In this respect, at least, Buddhas teachings seem to have had far greater influence on his followers than Christs teachings had on his.
Buddha and Confucius have had an approximately equal in- fluence upon the world. Both lived at about the same time, and the number of their adherents has not been,too different. I have chosen to place Buddha before Confucius for two reasons: first, the advent of Communism in China seems to have greatly diminished Confucian influence; and second, the failure of Confu- cianism to spread widely outside of China indicates how closely the ideas of Confucius were grounded in pre-existing Chinese atti- tudes. Buddhist teachings, on the other hand, are in no sense a restatement of previous Indian phi-
losophy, and Buddhism has spread
far beyond the boundaries of India
due to the originality of Gautama
Buddhas concept, and the wide ap-
peal of his philosophy.
    </string>
    <!--five CONFUCIUS-->
    <string name="five_CONFUCIUS">The great Chinese philosopher Confucius was the first man to develop a system of beliefs synthesizing the basic ideas of the Chinese people. His philosophy, based on personal morality and on the concept of a government that served its people and ruled by moral example, permeated Chinese life and culture for well over two thousand years, and has greatly influenced a substantial portion of the worlds population.
Confucius was born about 551 B.C., in the small state of Lu, which is in the present province of Shantung, in northeastern China. His father died when he was quite young, and Confucius and his mother lived in poverty. As a young man, the future philosopher served as a minor government official, but after several years he resigned his post. He spent the next sixteen years teaching, attracting a considerable number of disciples to his philosophy. When he was about fifty years old, he was awarded a high position in the government of Lu; however, after about four years, enemies at court brought about his dismissal, and, in- deed, his exile from the state. He spent the next thirteen years as
    an itinerant teacher, and then returned to his home state for the last five years of his life. He died in 479 B.C.
Confucius is often credited as the founder of a religion, but this description is inaccurate. He very rarely referred to the Dei- ty, refused to discuss the afterlife, and avoided all forms of metaphysical speculation. He was basically a secular philosopher, interested in personal and political morality and conduct.
The two most important virtues, according to Confucius, are jen and li, and the superior man guides his conduct by them. len has sometimes been translated as "love," but it might better be defined as "benevolent concern for ones fellow men." Li describes a combination of manners, ritual, custom, etiquette,
and propriety.
Ancestor worship, the basic Chinese religion even before
Confucius, was reinforced by the strong emphasis that he placed on family loyalty and respect for ones parents. Confucius also taught that respect and obedience were owed by wives to their husbands and by subjects to their rulers. But the Chinese sage did not approve of tyranny. He believed that the state exists for the benefit of the people, not vice versa, and he repeatedly stressed that a ruler should govern primarily by moral example rather than by force. Another of his tenets was a slight variant of the Golden Rule: "What you do not want done to yourself, do not do to others."
Confuciuss basic outlook was highly conservative. He believed that the Golden Age was in the past, and he urged both rulers and people to return to the good old moral standards. In fact, however, the Confucian ideal of government by moral ex- ample had not been the prevailing practice in earlier times, and Confucius was therefore a more innovative reformer than he claimed to be.
Confucius lived during the Chou dynasty, a period of great intellectual ferment in China. Contemporary rulers did not ac- cept his program, but after his death his ideas spread widely throughout his country. However, with the advent of the Chin
    dynasty, in 221 B.C., Confucianism fell upon evil days. The first emperor of the Chin dynasty, Shih Huang Ti, was determined to eradicate Confuciuss influence, and to make a clean break with the past. He ordered the suppression of Confucian teachings and the burning of all Confucian books. This attempt at suppression was unsuccessful, and when the Chin dynasty came to a close a few years later, Confucian scholars were again free to teach their
doctrine. During the succeeding dynasty, the Han (206 B.C.- 220 A .D .), Confucianism became established as the official Chi- nese state philosophy.
Starting with the Han dynasty, Chinese emperors gradually developed the practice of selecting government officials by means of civil service examinations. In the course of time these examina- tions came to be based to a large extent on a knowledge of the Confucian classics. Since entry into the government bureaucracy was the main route to financial success and social prestige in the Chinese empire, the civil service examinations were extremely competitive. Consequently, for generations a large number of the most intelligent and ambitious young men in China devoted many years to intensive study of the Confucian classics, and, for many centuries the entire civil administration of China was com- posed of persons whose basic outlook had been permeated by the Confucian philosophy. This system endured in China (with some interruptions) for roughly two thousand years, from about 100 B.C. to about 1900 A.D.
Hut Confucianism was not merely the official philosophy of
    the Chinese administration. Confucian ideals were accepted by the majority of the Chinese people, and for over two thousand years deeply influenced their life and thought.
There are several reasons for Confuciuss enormous appeal to the Chinese. First, his personal sincerity and integrity were beyond question. Second, he was a moderate and practical per- son, and did not delnand of men what they could not achieve. If he asked them to be honorable, he did not expect them to be
saintly. In this regard as in others, he reflected the practical temperament of the Chinese people. And this perhaps, was the key to the immense success that his ideas achieved in China. Con- fucius was not asking the Chinese to change their basic beliefs. Rather, he was restating, in a clear and impressive form, their basic traditional ideals. Perhaps no philosopher in history has been so closely in touch with the fundamental views of his coun- trymen as Confucius.
Confucianism, which stresses the obligations of individuals rather than their rights, may seem rather stodgy and unappeal- ing by current Western standard. As a philosophy of govern- ment, though, it proved remarkably effective in practice. Judged on the basis of its ability to maintain internal peace and prosper- ity, China, for a period of two thousand years, was on the average the best-governed region on earth.
The ideals of Confucius, closely grounded as they are in Chinese culture, have not been widely influential outside East Asia. They have, however, had a major impact in Korea and Japan, both of which have been greatly influenced by Chinese culture.
At the present time, Confucianism is in low estate in China. The Chinese Communists, in an effort to break completely with the past, have vigorously attacked Confucius and his doctrines, and it is possible that the period of his influence upon history has drawn to a close. In the past, however, the ideas of Confucius have proven to be very deeply rooted within China, and we should not be surprised if there is a resurgence of Confucianism in the course of the next century.
    </string>
    <!--six SY PAUL-->
    <string name="six_ST.PAUL">The apostle Paul, who was a younger contemporary of Jesus, became the foremost proselytizer of the new religion of Chris- tianity. His influence on Christian theology proved to be the most permanent and far-reaching of all Christian writers and thinkers.
Paul, also known as Saul, was born in Tarsus, a city in Cili- cia (in present-day Turkey), a few years into the Christian era. Although a Roman citizen, he was of Jewish birth, and in his youth he learned Hebrew and received a thorough Jewish educa- tion. He also learned the trade of tentmaking. As a young man, he went to Jerusalem to study under Rabbi Gamaliel, an eminent Jewish teacher. Though Paul was in Jerusalem at the same time as Jesus, it is doubtful whether the two men ever met.
    After the death of Jesus, the early Christians were regarded as heretics and suffered persecution. For a while, Paul himself participated in this persecution. However, during a journey to Damascus he had a vision in which Jesus spoke to him, and he was converted to the new faith. It was the turning point of his life. The one-time opponent of Christianity became the most vigorous and influential proponent of the new religion.
Paul spent the rest of his life thinking and writing about Christianity, and winning converts to the new religion. During his missionary activities, he traveled extensively in Asia Minor, Greece, Syria, and Palestine. Paul was not as successful in preaching to the Jews as some of the other early Christians. In- deed, his manner often aroused great antagonism, and on several occasions his life was endangered. In preaching to non-Jews, however, Paul was outstandingly successful, so much so that he is often referred to as the "Apostle to the Gentiles." No other man played so large a role in the propagation of Christianity.
After three long missionary trips within the eastern part of the Roman Empire, Paul returned to Jerusalem. He was arrested there, and was eventually sent to Rome to stand trial. It is unclear how that trial ended, or if he ever left Rome. Eventually, however (most likely about 64 A.D.), he was executed near Rome.
Pauls immense influence on the development of Christiani- ty rests upon three things: (1) his great success as a missionary; (2) his writings, which constitute an important part of the New Testament; and (3) his role in the development of Christian theology.
Of the twenty-seven books of the New Testament, no fewer than fourteen are attributed to Paul. Even though modern scholars believe that four or five of those books were actually written by other people, it is clear that Paul is the most impor- tant single author of the New Testament.
Pauls influence on Christian theology has been in- calculable. His ideas include the following: Jesus was not merely
an inspired human prophet, but was actually divine. Christ died for our sins, and his suffering can redeem us. Man cannot achieve
salvation by attempting to conform to biblical injunctions, but only by accepting Christ; conversely, if one accepts Christ, his sins will be forgiven. Paul also enunciated the doctrine of original sin (see Romans 5:12-19).
Since obedience to the law alone cannot provide salvation, Paul insisted that there was no need for converts to Christianity to accept Jewish dietary restrictions, or to conform to the rituals of the Mosaic Code, or even to be circumcised. Several of the other early Christian leaders disagreed strongly with Paul on this point, and if their views had prevailed, it seems doubtful that Christianity would have spread so rapidly throughout the Roman Empire.
Paul never married, and though there seems to be no way of proving it, he apparently never had sexual relations with a woman. His views on sex and on women, because of their in- corporation into Holy Scripture, have had a marked influence upon later attitudes. His most famous dictum on the subject (I Corinthians 7:8-9) is: "I say therefore to the unmarried and the widows, it is good for them if they can abide even as I. But if they cannot contain, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn."
Paul also had rather strong ideas on the proper status of women: "Let the woman learn in silence with all subjection. But I suffer not a woman to teach, nor usurp authority over the man, but to be in silence. For Adam was first formed then Eve" (I Timothy 2:11-13). Similar ideas are expressed perhaps even more forcefully in I Corinthians 11:7-9. Doubtless, in such passages Paul was expressing a view already held by many of his contem- poraries; it is noteworthy, though, that Jesus does not appear to have made similar statements.
Paul, more than any other man, was responsible for the transformation of Christianity from a Jewish sect into a wo:t:1d religion. His central ideas of the divinity of Christ and of justification by faith alone have remained basic to Christian
    hought throughout all the intervening centuries. All subsequent Christian theologians, including Augustine, Aquinas, Luther, and Calvin, have been profoundly influenced by his writings. In- deed, the influence of Pauls ideas has been so great that some scholars have claimed that he, rather than Jesus, should be regarded as the principal founder of the Christian religion. Such a view seems too extreme. However, even if Pauls influence has not been on a par with Jesus, it has been vastly greater than that of any other Christian thinker.
    </string>
    <!--seven TSAI LUN-->
    <string name="seven_TS_AI_LUN">
Tsai Lun, the inventor of paper, is a man whose name is prob- ably unfamiliar to most readers. Considering the importance of his invention, the extent to which he has been ignored in the West is indeed surprising. There are major encyclopedias which do not have even brief articles on Tsai Lun, and his name is
seldom mentioned in standard history textbooks. In view of the obvious importance of paper, this paucity of references to Tsai Lun may arouse suspicion that he is a purely apocryphal figure. Careful research, however, makes it absolutely clear that Tsai Lun was a real man, an official at the Chinese imperial court, who, in or about the year 105, presented Emperor Ho Ti with samples of paper. The Chinese account of Tsai Luns invention
    which appears in the official history of the Han dynasty) is en- tirely straightforward and believable, without the least hint of magic or legend about it. The Chinese have always credited Tsai Lun with the invention of paper, and his name is well known in China.
Not a great deal is known about Tsai Luns life. Chinese records do mention that he was a eunuch. It is also recorded that the emperor was greatly pleased by Tsai Luns invention, and that as a result Tsai Lun was promoted, received an aristocratic title, and became wealthy. Later on, however, he became in- volved iIi palace intrigue, and this eventually led to his downfall. The Chinese records relate that upon his being disgraced, Tsai Lun took a bath, dressed in his finest robes, and drank poison.
The use of paper became widespread in China during the second century, and within a few centuries the Chinese were ex- porting paper to other parts of Asia. For a long time, they kept the technique of papermaking a secret. In 751, however, some Chinese papermakers were captured by the Arabs, and not long afterwards paper was being manufactured in both Samarkand
and Baghdad. The art of papermaking gradually spread throughout the Arab world, and in the twelfth century the Euro- peans learned the art from the Arabs. The use of paper gradually spread, and after Gutenberg invented modern printing, paper replaced parchment as the principal writing material in the W est.
Today, paper is so common that we take it for granted, and it is hard to envisage what the world was like without it. In China, before Tsai Lun, most books were made of bamboo. Obviously, such books were extremely heavy and clumsy. Some books were written on silk, but that was too expensive for general use. In the West, before paper was introduced, most books were written on parchment or vellum, which were made of specially
processed sheepskin or calfskin. This material had replaced the papyrus favored by the Greeks, Romans, and Egyptians. Both parchment and papyrus, however, not only were scarce, but were also expensive to prepare.
    That books and other written materials can today be pro- duced so cheaply and in such large quantities is due in con- siderable part to the existence of paper. It is true that paper would not be as important as it is today were it not for the print- ing press; however, it is equally true that the printing press
would not be nearly so important were it not for the existence of a cheap and plentiful material on which to print.
Which man, then, should be ranked higher: Tsai Lun or Gutenberg? Although I consider the two of almost equal im- portance, I have ranked Tsai Lun slightly higher for the follow- ing reasons: (1) Paper has many other applications besides its use as a writing material. In fact, it is an amazingly versatile
material, and a large percentage of the paper currently produced is used for purposes other than printing. (2) Tsai Lun preceded Gutenberg, and it is altogether possible that Gutenberg would not have invented printing had paper not already existed. (3) If only one of the two had ever been invented, I suspect that more bdoks would be produced by the combination of block printing (which was known long before Gutenberg) and paper than by
the combination of movable type and parchment.
Is it appropriate to include both Gutenberg and Tsai Lun among the ten most influential people who ever lived? In order to realize the full importance of the inventions of paper and print- ing, it is necessary to consider the relative cultural development of China and the West. Prior to the second century A.D., Chinese
civilization was consistently less advanced than Western civil- ization. During the next millenium, Chinas accomplishments ex- ceeded those of the West, and for a period of seven or eight cen- turies, Chinese civilization was by most standards the most ad-
vanced on earth. After the fifteenth century, however, western Europe outstripped China. Various cultural explanations for these changes have been advanced, but most such theories seem to ignore what I believe is the simplest explanation.
It is true, of course, that agriculture and writing developed earlier in the Middle East than they did in China. That alone, however, would not explain why Chinese civilization so per-
    istently lagged behind that of the West. The crucial factor, I believe, was that prior to Tsai Lun there was no convenient writing material available in China. In the Western world, papyrus was available, and although that material had its drawbacks, papyrus rolls were infinitely superior to books made of wood or bamboo. Lack of a suitable writing material was an overpowering obstacle to Chinese cultural progress. A Chinese scholar needed a wagon to carry around what we would consider a quite modest number of books. One can imagine the difficulty of trying to run a government administration on such a basis!
Tsai Luns invention of paper, however, changed the situ- ation entirely. With a suitable writing material available, Chinese civilization advanced rapidly, and within a few cen-
turies, was able to catch up with the West. (Of course, political disunity in the West played a       but that was far from being the whole story. In the fourth century, China was less united than the West, but nevertheless was developing rapidly in cultural matters.) During the succeeding centuries, while pro- gress in the West was comparatively       the Chinese brought forth such major inventions as the compass, gunpowder, and block printing. Since paper was cheaper than parchment, and available in larger quantities, the tables were now turned.
After Western nations began using paper, they were able to hold their own vis-a-vis China, and even succeeded in narrowing the cultural gap. The writings of Marco Polo, however, confirm the fact that even in the thirteenth century, China was far more prosperous than Europe.
Why, then, did China eventually fall behind the West? Various complex cultural explanations have been offered, but perhaps a simple technological one will serve. In fifteenth- century Europe, a genius named Johann Gutenberg developed a technique for the mass production of books. Thereafter, Euro- pean culture advanced rapidly. As China had no Gutenberg, the Chinese stayed with block printing, and their culture progressed relatively slowly.
If one accepts the foregoing analysis, one is forced to the
    conclusion that Tsai Lun and Johann Gutenberg are two of the central figures in human history. Indeed, Tsai Lun stands out well above most other inventors for another reason. Most inven- tions are a product of their times, and would have come about even if the person who actually invented them had never lived. But such is clearly not the case with regard to paper. Europeans did not start to manufacture it until a thousand years after Tsai
Lun, and then only because they had learned the process from the Arabs. For that matter, even after they had seen paper of Chinese manufacture, other Asian peoples were never able to discover how to manufacture it by themselves. Clearly, the invention of a method of manufacturing true paper was suffi-
ciently difficult that it was not bound to occur in any moderately ad- vanced culture, but rather required the ex- plicit contribution of
some very gifted indi- vidual. Tsai Lun was such an individual, and the method of paper- making that he em- ployed is (aside from mechanization, intro-
duced about 1800 A.D.) basically the same technique that has been used ever since.
These are the rea- sons I think it appropri- ate to place both Gut- enberg and Tsai Lun among the first ten per- sons in this book, with Tsai Lun ahead of Gutenberg.
    </string>
    <!--eight JOHANN_GUTENBERG-->
    <string name="eight_JOHANN_GUTENBERG">Johann Gutenberg is often called the inventor of printing. What
he actually did was to develop the first method of utilizing
movable type and the printing press in such a way that a large
variety of written material could be printed with speed and accuracy.
No invention springs full-blown from the mind of a single man, and certainly printing did not. Seals and signet rings, which work on the same principle as block printing, had been used since ancient times. Block printing had been known in China many centuries before Gutenberg, and, in fact, a printed
book dating from about 868 has been discovered there. The process was also known in the West before Gutenberg. Block printing makes possible the production of many copies of a given
    book. However, the process has one major drawback: since a completely new set of woodcuts or plates must be Inade for each new book, it is impractical for producing a large variety of books.
It is sometimes said that Gutenbergs main contribution was the invention of movable type. However, movable type was invented in China, some time in the middle of the eleventh century, by a man named Pi Sheng. His original type was made of earthenware, which is not very durable; however, other Chinese and Koreans made a series of improvements, and well before Gutenberg, Koreans were using metal type. In fact, the Korean government was supporting a foundry for the production of printing type in the early fifteenth century. Despite all this, it would be a mistake to think of Pi Sheng as a particularly influen- tial person. In the first place, Europe did not learn of movable
type from China, but developed it independently. In the second place, printing by means of movable type never came into general use in China itself until comparatively recent times, when modern printing procedures were learned from the West.
There are four essential components of modern printing methods. The first is movable type, along with some procedure for setting it and fixing it in position. The second is the printing press itself. The third is a suitable type of ink, and the last is a suitable material, such as paper, on which to print. Paper had been invented in China many years earlier (by Tsai Lun), and its use had spread to the West before Gutenbergs day. That was the only element of the printing process that Gutenberg found ready- made. Although some work had been done before him on each of the other three elements, Gutenberg made a variety of important
improvements. For example, he developed a metal alloy suitable for type; a mold for casting blocks of type precisely and accurate- ly; an oil-based printing ink; and a press suitable for printing.
But Gutenbergs overall contribution was far greater than any of his individual inventions or improvements. He is impor- tant principally because he combined all the elements of printing into an effective system of production. For printing, unlike all prior inventions, is essentially a process of mass production. A
    single rifle is in itself a more effective weapon than a single bow and arrow. A single printed book, however, is no different in its effect from a single hand-written book. The advantage of print- ing therefore is mass production. What Gutenberg developed was not a single gadget or device, or even a series of im- provements, but a complete manufacturing process.
Our biographical information concerning Gutenberg is scanty. We know that he was born about 1400, in the city of Mainz, Germany. His contributions to the art of printing \Nere made in the middle of the century, and his best known work, the
    so-called Gutenberg Bible, was printed at Mainz, around 1454. (Curiously, Gutenbergs name does not actually appear on any of his books, not even on the Gutenberg Bible, although it was
clearly printed with his equipment.) He does not appear to have been a particularly good businessman; certainly he never man- aged to make much money on his invention. He was involved in several lawsuits, one of which seems to have resulted in his forfeiting his equipment to his partner, Johann Fust. Gutenberg
died in 1468, in Mainz.
Some idea of Gutenbergs impact on world history can be gained by comparing the subsequent development of China and Europe. At the time Gutenberg was born, the two regions were about equally advanced technologically. But after Gutenbergs invention of modern printing, Europe progressed very rapidly, while in China-where the use of block printing was continued until much later-progress was comparatively slow. It is prob-
ably an overstatement to say that the development of printing was the only factor causing this divergence; certainly, however, it was an important factor.
It is also worth noting that only three persons on this list lived during the five centuries preceding Gutenberg, whereas sixty-seven lived during the five centuries following his death. This suggests that GutenbergS invention was a major factor- possibly even the crucial factor-in triggering the revolutionary developments of modern times.
It seems fairly certain that even had Alexander Graham Bell never lived, the telephone would still have been invented, and at about the same point in history. The same can be said of many other inventions. Without Gutenberg, though, the invention of modern printing might have been delayed for generations, and in
view of the overwhelming impact of printing on subsequent history, Gutenberg assuredly deserves a high place on our list.
    </string>
    <!--nine CHRISTOPHER COLUMBUS-->
    <string name="nine_CHRISTOPHER_COLUMBUS">Columbus, by attempting to find a westward route from Europe to the Orient, inadvertently discovered the Americas, and therebyhad a greater influence on world history than he could possibly have anticipated. His discovery, which inaugurated the age of exploration and colonization in the New World, was one of the critical turning points in history. It opened to the        of Europe two new continents for the settlement of their expanding populations, and provided a source of mineral wealth and raw materials that altered the economy of Europe. His discovery led to the destruction of the civilizations of the American Indians. In the long run, it also led to the formation of a new set of nationsin the western hemisphere, vastly different from the Indian nations
which had once inhabited the region, and greatly affecting the nations of the Old World.
The main outlines of Columbuss story are well known. He was born in Genoa, Italy, in 1451. When he grew up, he became a ships captain and a skilled navigator. He eventually became convinced that it was possible to find a practical route to East Asia by sailing due west across the Atlantic Ocean, and he pur-
    sued this idea with great tenacity. Eventually, he persuaded Queen Isabella I of Castile to finance his voyage of exploration.
His ships left Spain.on August 3, 1492. Their first stop was at the Canary Islands, off the coast of Africa. They left the Canaries on September 6 and sailed due west. It was a long voyage, and his sailors became frightened and wished to turn back. Colum- bus, however, insisted upon continuing, and on October 12, 1492, land was sighted.
Columbus arrived back in Spain the follo\ving March, and the triumphant explorer was received with the highest honors. He made three subsequent voyages across the Atlantic in the vain hope of making direct contact with China or Japan. Columbus
clung to the idea that he had found a route to East Asia long after most other people realized that he had not.
Isabella had promised Columbus that he would become
    governor of any lands which he discovered. However, he was so unsuccessful as an administrator that he was eventually relieved of his duties, and sent back to Spain in chains. There, he was promptly set free, but he was never again given an ad- ministrative postition. However, the common rumor that he died in poverty is without foundation. At the time of his death, in 1506, he was fairly wealthy.
It is pbvious that Columbuss first trip had a revolutionary impact upon European history, and an even greater effect on the Americas. The one date that every schoolchild knows is 1492. Still, there are several possible objections to ranking Columbus so high upon this list.
One objection is that Columbus was not the first European to discover the New World. Leif Ericson, the Viking sailor, had reached America several centuries before him, and it is plausible that several other Europeans crossed the Atlantic in the interval between the Viking and Columbus. Historically, however, Leif Ericson is a relatively unimportant figure. Knowledge of his discoveries never became widespread, nor did they trigger any large changes in either Europe or America. News of Columbuss discoveries, on the other hand, spread very rapidly throughout Europe. Within a few years of his return, and as a direct conse- quence of his discoveries, many additional expeditions to the New World were made and the conquest and colonization of the new territories began.
Like other figures in this book, Columbus is vulnerable to the argument that what he did would have been accomplished even if he had never lived. Fifteenth-century Europe was already in a ferment: commerce was expanding, and exploration was in- evitable. The Portuguese, in fact, had actively been searching for a new route to the Indies for a considerable time before Colum- bus.
It indeed seems probable that America would sooner or later have been discovered by the Europeans; it is even possible that the delay would not have been very great. But subsequent developments would have been quite different if America had
    originally been discovered in 1510, say, by a French or English expedition, instead of in 1492 by Columbus. In any event, Col- umbus was the man who actually did discover America.
A third possible objection is that even before Columbuss voyages, many fifteenth-century Europeans already knew that the world was round. That theory had been suggested by Greek philosophers many centuries earlier, and the firm endorsement of the hypothesis by Aristotle was enough to cause its acceptance by educated Europeans in the 1400s. However, Columbus is not
famous for showing that the earth was round. (As a matter of fact, he didnt really succeed in doing that.) He is famous for
    discovering the New World, and neither fifteenth-century Euro- peans nor Aristotle had had any knowledge of the existence of the American continents.
Columbuss character was not entirely admirable. He was exceptionally avaricious; in fact, one important reason that Col- umbus encountered difficulties in persuading Isabella to finance him was that he drove an extremely greedy bargain. Also, though it may not be fair to judge him by todays ethical standards, he treated the Indians with shocking cruelty. This is not, ho\vever, a list of the noblest characters in history, but rather of the most in- fluential ones, and by that criterion Columbus deserves a place near the top of the list.
    </string>
    <!--ten ALBERT EINSTEIN-->
    <string name="ten_ALBERT_EINSTEIN">Albert Einstein, the greatest scientist of the hventieth century and one of the supreme intellects of all time, is best known for his theory of relativity. There are actually two theories involved: the special theory of relativity, formulated in 1905, and the general theory of relativity, formulated in 1915, which might better be called Einsteins law of gravitation. Both theories are highly complicated, and no attempt will be made to explain them here; however, a few comments on special relativity are in order.
    A familiar maxim has it that "everything is relative." Ein- steins theory, however, is not a repetition of this philosophical platitude, but rather a precise mathematical statement of the way in which scientific measurements are relative. It is obvious that subjective perceptions of time and space depend on the observer. Before Einstein, however, most people had always believed that behind th-ese subjective impressions were real distances and an absolute time, which accurate instruments could measure objectively. Einsteins theory revolutionized scien- tific thought by denying the existence of any absolute time. The following example may illustrate just how radically his theory revised our ideas of time and space.
Imagine a spaceship, spaceship X, moving away from Earth at a speed of 100,000 kilometers per second. The speed is measured by observers on both the spaceship and on Earth, and their measurements agree. Meanwhile, another spaceship, spaceship Y, is moving in exactly the same direction as spaceship X, but at a much greater speed. If observers on Earth measure the speed of spaceship Y, they find that it is moving away from the Earth at a speed of 180,000 kilometers per second. Observers on spaceship Ywill reach the same conclusion.
Now, as both spaceships are moving in the same direction, it would seem that the difference in their speeds is 80,000 kilometers per second, and that the faster ship must be moving away from the slower ship at this rate.
However, Einsteins theory predicts that when observations are taken from the two spaceships, observers on both ships will agree that the distance between them is increasing at the rate of 100,000 kilometers per second, not 80,000 kilometers per second.
Now, on the face of it such a result is ridiculous, and the reader may suspect that some trick of wording is involved, or that some significant details of the problem have not been men- tioned. Not at all. The result has nothing to do with the details of construction of the spaceships or with the forces used to propel them. Nor is it due to any errors of observation, nor to any
    defects in the measuring instruments. No trick is involved. Ac- cording to Einstein, the foregoing result (which can readily be computed from his formula for the composition of velocities) is a consequence only of the basic nature of time and space.
Now, all of this may seem awfully theoretical, and indeed for years many persons dismissed the theory of relativity as a sort of "ivory tower" hypothesis, which had no practical significance. No one, of course, has made that mistake since 1945, when atomic bombs were dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki. One of the conclusions of Einsteins theory of relativity is that matter and energy are in a certain sense equivalent, and the relation be- tween them is given by. the formula E = Mc2 in which E represents energy, M equals mass, and c represents the speed of
light. Now since c, which is equal to 186,000 miles per second, is a very large number, c2 (that is, c times c) is a simply enormous number. It follows that even the partial conversion of a small
amount of matter will release tremendous quantities of energy. One cannot, of course, build an atomic bomb or a nuclear power plant simply from the formula E = Mc2  It must be borne in mind, too, that many other persons played important roles in the development of atomic energy; however, the importance of
Einsteins contribution is indisputable. Furthermore, it was Ein- steins letter to President Roosevelt, in 1939, pointing out the possibility of developing atomic weapons and stressing the im- portance of the United States developing such weapons before the Germans did, which helped launch the Manhattan Project, and which led to the development of the first atomic bomb.
Special relativity aroused heated controversy, but on one point everyone was agreed; it was the most mind-boggling scien- tific theory that would ever be invented. But everyone was wrong, for Einsteins general theory of relativity takes as a start- ing point the premise that gravitational effects are not due to physical forces in the normal sense of the word, but rather result from a curvature of space itself-a truly astonishing idea!
How can one measure a curvature of space itself? What does it even mean to say that space is curved? Einstein had not only
    advanced such a theory, but he had put his theory in a clear mathematical form, from which explicit predictions could be made and his hypothesis tested. Subsequent observations-the most celebrated of which are those made during total eclipses of the sun-have repeatedly confirmed the correctness of Einsteins equations.
The general theory of relativity stands apart in several ways from all other scientific laws. In the first place, Einstein derived his theory not on the basis of careful experiments, but rather on grounds of symmetry and mathematical elegance-on ra- tionalistic grounds, as the Greek philosophers and the medieval scholastics had attempted to do. (In so doing, he ran counter to the basically empirical outlook of modern science.) But whereas the Greeks, in their search for beauty and symmetry, had never managed to find a mechanical theory that could survive the crucial test of experiment, Einsteins theory has so far successful- ly withstood every test. One result of Einstins approach is that the general theory of is generally acknowledged to be the most beautiful, elegant, powerful, and intellectually satisfy- ing of all scientific theories.
General relativity stands apart in another way also. Most other scientific laws are only approximately valid. They hold in many circumstances, but not in all. So far as we know, however, there are no exceptions at all to the general theory of relativity. There is no known circumstance, either theoretical or ex- perimental, in which the predictions of general relativity are only approximately valid. Future experiments may mar the theorys perfect record; but so far the general theory of relativity remains the closest approach to ultimate truth that any scientist has yet devised.
Though Einstein is best known for his theories of relativity, his other scientific achievements would have won him renown as a scientist in any case. In fact, Einstein was awarded the Nobel Prize in physics primarily for his paper explaining the photo- electric effect, an important phenomenon that had previously puzzled physicists. In that paper, he postulated the existence of
    photons, or particles of light. Since it had been long established through interference experiments that light consisted of electro- magnetic waves, and since it was considered "obvious" that waves and particles were antithetical concepts, Einsteins hypothesis represented a radical and paradoxical break with classical theory. Not only did his photoelectric law turn out to have important practical applications, but his hypothesis of the photon had a major influence on the development of quantum theory, and is today an integral part of that theory.
In evaluating Einsteins importance, a comparison with Isaac Newton is revealing. Newtons theories were basically easy to understand, and his genius lay in being the first to develop them. Einsteins theories of relativity, on the other hand, are ex- tremely difficult to understand, even when they are carefully ex- plained. How much more difficult, therefore, to devise them originally! While some of Newtons ideas were in strong con- tradiction to the prevailing scientific ideas of his time, his theory never appeared to lack self-consistency. The theory of relativity,
on the other hand, abounds with paradoxes. It was part of Ein- steins genius that at the beginning, when his ideas were still the untested hypothesis of an unknown teenager, he did not let these apparent contradictions cause him to discard his theories. Rather, he carefully thought them through until he could show that these contradictions were apparent only, and that in each case there was a subtle but correct way of resolving the paradox.
Today, we think of Einsteins theory as being basically more "correct" than Newtons. Why, then, is Einstein lower on this list? Primarily because it was Newtons theories that laid the groundwork for modern science and technology. Most of modern technology would be the same today had only Newtons work been done, and not Einsteins.
There is another factor which affects Einsteins place on this list. In most cases, many men have contributed to the develop- ment of an important idea, as was obviously the case in the history of socialism, or in the development of the theory of elec- tricity and magnetism. Though Einstein does not deserve 100
    percent of the credit for the invention of the theory of relativity, he certainly deserves most of it. It seems fair to say that, to a larger degree than is the case for any other ideas of comparable importance, the theories of relativity are primarily the creation of a single, outstanding genius.
Einstein was born in 1879, in the city of Ulm, Germany. He attended high school in Switzerland, and became a Swiss citizen in the year 1900. He received his Ph.D. in 1905 from the Univer- sity of Zurich, but was unable to find an academic position at that time. However, that same year, he published his papers on
special relativity, on the photoelectric effect, and on the theory of Brownian motion. Within a few years, these papers, par- ticularly the one on relativity, established his reputation as one of the most brilliant and original scientists in the world. His theories were highly controversial; no modern scientist except Darwin has ever engendered as much controversy as Einstein. In spite of this, in 1913 he was appointed a professor at the University of Berlin, at the same time becoming director of the Kaiser Wilheim Institute of Physics and a member of the Prussian Academy of Science. These posts left him free to devote his full time to research, if he so chose.
The German government had little reason to regret offering Einstein this unusually generous package, for just two years later he succeeded in formulating the general theory of relativity, and in 1921 he was awarded the Nobel Prize. For the last half of his life, Einstein was world-famous, in all probability the most famous scientist that ever lived.
Since Einstein was Jewish, his situation in Germany became precarious when Hitler rose to power. In 1933, he moved to Princeton, New Jersey, to work at the Institute for Advanced Study, and in 1940 he became a United States citizen. Einsteins first marriage ended in divorce; his second was apparently happy. He had two children, both boys. He died in 1955, in Princeton.
Einstein was always interested in the human world about him, and frequently expressed his views on political matters. He was a consistent opponent of political tyranny, an ardent pacifist, and a firm supporter of Zionism. In matters of dress and social conventions, he was a marked individualist. He had a fine sense of humor, a becoming modesty, and some talent as a violinist. The inscription on Newtons tomb might be applied even more appropriately to Einstein: "Let mortals rejoice that so great an ornament to the human race has existed!"</string>
    <!--eleven LOUIS PASTEUR-->
    <string name="eleven_LOUIS_PASTEUR">
The French chemist and biologist Louis Pasteur is generally acknowledged to be the most important single figure in the history of medicine. Pasteur made many contributions to science, but he is most famous for his advocacy of the germ theory of disease and for his development of the technique of preventive inoculation.
Pasteur was born in 1822, in the town of Dole, in eastern France. As a college student in Paris, he studied science. His genius was not evident during his student days; in fact, one of his professors recorded him as "mediocre" in chemistry. However, after receiving his doctorate in 1847, Pasteur soon showed that his professors judgment had been in error. His research on the
    mirror-image isomers of tartaric acid made Pasteur a renowned chemist when he was only twenty-six years old.
He then turned his attention to the study of fermentation, and showed that that process is due to the action of certain types of microorganisms. He also demonstrated that the presence of certain other species of microorganisms could produce undesirable products in the fermenting beverages. This soon led him to the idea that some species of microorganisms could pro- duce undesirable products and effects in human beings and other animals.
Pasteur was not the first person to suggest the germ theory of disease. Similar hypotheses had been advanced earlier by Girolamo Fracastoro, Friedrich Henle, and others. But it was Pasteurs vigorous championship of the germ theory, substan- tiated by his numerous experiments and demonstrations, that were the principle factor in convincing the scientific community that the theory was correct.
If diseases were caused by germs, it seemed logical that by preventing harmful germs from entering the human body, diseases might be avoided. Pasteur therefore stressed the im- portance of antiseptic methods for physicians, and he was a ma- jor influence on Joseph Lister who introduced antiseptic methods into surgical practice.
Harmful bacteria can enter the human body through food and beverages. Pasteur developed a technique (called pasteuriza- tion) for destroying microorganisms in            That tech- nique, where practiced, has all but eradicated contaminated milk as a source of infection.
When he was in his mid-fifties, Pasteur turned his attention to the study of anthrax, a serious infectious disease which attacks cattle and many other animals, including human beings. Pasteur was able to show that a particular species of bacterium was responsible for the disease. Of far greater importance, however, was his development of a technique for producing a weakened strain of the anthrax bacillus. Injected into cattle, this weakened strain produced a mild form of the disease, which was not fatal
    but which enabled the cattle to develop an immunity to the nor- mal fornl of the disease. Pasteurs public demonstration of the ef- fectiveness of his technique in immunizing cattle against anthrax aroused great excitement. It was soon realized that his general method might be applied to the prevention of many other com- municable diseases.
Pasteur himself, in his most renowned single achievement, developed a technique for inoculating people against the dreaded disease of rabies. Other scientists, applying Pasteurs basic ideas, have since developed vaccines against many other serious diseases, such as epidemic typhus and poliomyelitis.
    Pasteur, who was an unusually hard worker, has a variety of lesser but still useful achievements to his credit. It was his ex- periments, more than any others, which convincingly demonstrated that microorganisms do not arise through spon- taneous generation. Pasteur also discovered the phenomenon of anaerobiosis; i.e., that certain microorganisms can live in the absence of any air or free oxygen. Pasteurs work on diseases of silkworms has been of great commercial value. Among his other
achievements was the development of a vaccine for the preven- tion of chicken cholera, a disease that attacks fowl. Pasteur died in 1895, near Paris.
A comparison is often made between Pasteur and Edward Jenner, the English physician who developed a vaccine against smallpox. Though Jenners work was done more than eighty years before Pasteurs, I consider Jenner much less important because his method of immunization worked for only one disease, whereas Pasteurs methods could be-and have been-
applied to the prevention of a large number of diseases.
Since the mid-nineteenth century, life expectancies in much of the world have roughly doubled. This enormous increase in human life spans has probably had a greater effect on the lives of individual human beings than has any other development in the entire history of the human race. In effect, modern science and medicine have presented each of us now living with virtually a second lifetime. If this increase in longevity could be solely at- tributed to the work of Pasteur, I would have had no hesitation at all in placing him first in this book. Nevertheless, Pasteurs contributions are so fundamental that there is no question that he deserves the largest share of the credit for the decline in death rates that has occurred in the last century, and that he is there-
fore assigned a high place on this list.</string>
    <!--twelve GALILEO_GALILEI-->
    <string name="twelve_GALILEO_GALILEI">Galileo Galilei, the great Italian scientist who was probably more responsible for the development of the scientific method than any other individual, was born in 1564, in the city of Pisa. As a young man, he studied at the University of Pisa, but drop- ped out for financial reasons. Nevertheless, he was able, in 1589, to obtain a teaching position at that university. A few years later, he joined the faculty of the University of Padua and remained there until 1610. It was during this period that the bulk of his scientific discoveries were made.
Galileos first important contributions were made in mechanics. Aristotle had taught that heavy objects fall at a more rapid rate than light objects, and generations of scholars had ac- cepted this assertion on the Greek philosophers authority. Galileo, however, decided to test it, and through a series of ex- periments, he soon found that Aristotle had been incorrect. The fact is that heavy and light objects fall at the same velocity except
    o the extent that they are retarded by the friction of the air. (In- cidently, the tradition that Galileo performed these experiments by dropping objects from the Leaning Tower of Pisa seems to be without foundation.)
Having learned this, Galileo took the next step. He carefully measured the distance that objects fall in a given period of time and found that the distance traversed by a falling object is pro- portional to the square of the number of seconds it has been fall- ing. This discovery (which implies a uniform rate of acceler- ation) is significant in itself. Even more important, Galileo was able to summarize the results of a series of experiments by a mathematical formula. The extensive use of mathematical form- ulas and mathematical methods is an important characteristic of modern science.
Another of Galileos major contributions was his discovery of the law of inertia. Previously, people had believed that a mov- ing object would naturally tend to slow down and stop unless some force were exerted to keep it moving. But Galileos ex- periments indicated that the common belief was erroneous. If retarding forces, such as friction, could be eliminated, a moving object would naturally tend to continue moving indefinitely. This important principle, which Newton restated clearly and in- corporated into his own system as the first law of motion, is one of the vital principles of physics.
Galileos most celebrated discoveries were in the field of astronomy. Astronomical theory in the early 1600s was in a state of great ferment, with an important dispute going on between the followers of the heliocentric theory of Copernicus and the adherents of the earlier geocentric theory. As early as 1604, Galileo had announced his belief that Copernicus was correct, but at that time he had no method of proving it. In 1609,
however, Galileo heard of the invention of the telescope in Holland. Although he had only the barest description of the device, Galileos genius was such that he was,soon able to con- struct a vastly superior telescope himself. With this new tool, he turned his observational talents to the heavens, and in a single year made a whole series of major discoveries.
He looked at the moon and sa\" that it was not a smooth sphere, but had numerous craters and high Glountains on it. Celestial objects, he concluded, were not smooth and perfect after all, but had the same sort of irregularities that one observed on earth. He looked at the Milky Way and saw that it was not a milky, nebulous body after all, but was composed of an enor- mous number of individual stars, which were so far away that the naked eye tended to blur them together. He looked at the
    planets and saw that four moons revolved around Jupiter. Here was clear evidence that an astronomical body could revolve about a planet other than Earth. He looked at the sun and observed sunspots. (Actually, other persons had observed sunspots before him, but Galileo publicized his observations more effectively and brought sunspots to the attention of the scientific world.) He ob- served that the planet Venus had phases quite similar to the phases of the moon. This became a significant piece of evidence corrobo- rating the Copernican theory that the earth and all the other planets revolve around the sun.
The invention of the telescope and the series of discoveries that resulted from it made Galileo famous. However, by sup- porting the theory of Copernicus he aroused opposition in impor- tant Church circles, and in 1616 he \-vas ordered to refrain from teaching the Copernican hypothesis. Galileo chafed under this restriction for several years. When the Pope died, in 1623, he was succeeded by a man who had been an admirer of Galileo. The following year the new Pope, Urban VIII, hinted (though somewhat ambiguously) that the prohibition would no longer be in force.
Galileo spent the next six years composing his most famous work, the Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems. This book was a masterly exposition of the evidence in favor of the Copernican theory, and the book was published in 1632 with the imprimatur of the Church censors. Nevertheless, Church authorities responded in anger when the book appeared, and Galileo was soon brought to trial before the Inquisition in Rome on charges of having violated the 1616 prohibition.
It seems clear that many churchmen were unhappy with the decision to prosecute the eminent scientist. Even under the Church law of the time, the case against Galileo was ques- tionable, and he was given a comparatively light sentence. He was not, in fact, confined to jail at all, but merely to house arrest in his own comfortable villa in Arcetri. Theoretically, he was to have no visitors, but that provision of the sentence was not en-
    forced. His only other punishment was the requirement that he publicly recant his view that the earth moved around the sun. This the sixty-nine-year-old scientist did in open court. (There is a famous and probably apocryphal story that after he finished making his retraction, Galileo looked down to the earth and whispered softly, "It still moves.") In Arcetri he continued to
write on mechanics. He died there, in 1642.
Galileos enormous contribution to the advancement of
science has long been recognized. His importance rests in part on his scientific discoveries such as the law of inertia, his invention of the telescope, his astronomical observations, and his genius in proving the Copernican hypothesis. Of greater importance,
    however, is his role in the development of the methodology of science. Most previous natural philosophers, taking their cues from Aristotle, had made qualitative observations and categoriz- ed phenomena; but Galileo measured phenomena and made quantitative observations. This emphasis on careful quantitative measurements has since become a basic feature of scientific
research.
Galileo is probably more responsible than any other man for
the empirical attitude of scientific research. It was he who first insisted upon the necessity of performing experiments. He re- jected the notion that scientific questions could be decided by reliance upon authority, whether it be the pronouncements of the Church or the assertions of Aristotle. He also rejected reliance on complex deductive schemes that were not based on a firm foundation of experiment. Medieval scholastics had discussed at great length what should happen and why things happen, but Galileo insisted upon performing experiments to determine what
actually did happen. His scientific outlook was distinctly non- mystical; in this respect, he was even more modern than some of his successors, such as Newton.
Galileo, it might be noted, was a deeply religious man. De- spite his trial and conviction, he did not reject either religion or the church, but only the attempt of Church authorities to stifle investigation of scientific matters. Later generations have quite rightly admired Galileo as a symbol of revolt against dogmatism, and against authoritarian attempts to stifle freedom of thought. Of greater importance, however, is the role he played in found- ing modern scientific method.</string>
    <!--thirteen ARISTOTLE-->
    <string name="thirteen_ARISTOTLE">Aristotle was the greatest philosopher and scientist of the ancient
world. He originated the study of formal logic, enriched almost
every branch of philosophy, and made numerous contributions to science.
Many of Aristotles ideas are outmoded today. But far more important than any of his individual theories is the rational ap- proach underlying his work. Implicit in Aristotles writings is the attitude that every aspect of human life and society may be an appropriate object of thought and analysis; the notion that the universe is not controlled by blind chance, by magic, or by the whims of capricious deities, but that its behavior is subject to ra-
tionallaws; the belief that it is worthwhile for human beings to conduct a systematic inquiry into every aspect of the natural world; and the conviction that we should utilize both empirical observations and logical reasoning in forming our conclusions. This set of attitudes-which is contrary to traditionalism,
superstition, and mysticism-has profoundly influenced Western civilization.
Aristotle was born in 384 B.C., in the town of Stagira, in Macedonia. His father was a prominent physician. At seventeen,
    Aristotle went to Athens to study in the Academy of Plato. He re- mained there for twenty years, until shortly after Plato died. From his father, Aristotle may have gained an interest in biology and in "practical science"; under Plato he cultivated an interest in philosophical speculation.
In 342 B.C., Aristotle returned to Macedonia to become the private tutor of the kings son, a thirteen-year-old boy who was to become known to history as Alexander the Great. Aristotle tutored the young Alexander for several years. In 335 B.C., after Alexander had ascended the throne, Aristotle returned to Athens, where he opened his own school, the Lyceum. He spent the next twelve years in Athens, a period roughly coinciding with Alex- anders career of military conquest. Alexander did not ask his former tutor for advice, but he did provide him generously with funds for research. This was probably the first example in history of a scientist receiving large-scale government funding for his. research, and it was to be the last for centuries to come.
Nevertheless, association with Alexander had its dangers. Aristotle was opposed on principle to the dictatorial style of Alex- ander, and when the conqueror executed Aristotles nephew on suspicion of treason, he seems to have considered executing Aristotle as well. But if Aristotle was too democratic for Alex- anders tastes, he was too closely associated with Alexander to be trusted by the Athenians. When Alexander died, in 323 B.C., the anti-Macedonian faction gained control in Athens, and Aristotle was indicted for "impiety." Aristotle, recalling the fate of Socrates seventy-six years earlier, fled the city, saying that he would not give Athens a second chance to sin against philosophy.
He died in exile a few months later, in 322 B.C., at the age of
sixty-two.
The sheer quantity of Aristotles output is astonishing.
Forty-seven of his works have survived, and ancient lists credit him with no fewer than 170 books. However, it is not merely the number of his works, but the enormous range of his erudition, which is amazing. His scientific works constitute a virtual en- cyclopedia of the scientific knowledge of his day. Aristotle wrote
    n astronomy, zoology, embryology, geography, geology, physics, anatomy, physiology, and almost every other field of learning known to the ancient Greeks. His scientific works repre-
sent, in part, a compilation of knowledge already aquired by
others; in part, the findings of assistants whom he hired to ac-
quire data for him; and in part, the results of his Own numerous observations.
To be a leading expert in every field of science is an incredi-
    ble feat, and one not likely to be duplicated by any man in the future. But Aristotle achieved even more than that. He was also an original philosopher, and made major contributions to every area of speculative philosophy. He wrote on ethics and on metaphysics, on psychology and on economics, on theology and on politics, on rhetoric and on aesthetics. He wrote on education, poetry, barbarian customs, and the constitution of the Athe- nians. One of his research projects was a collection of the con- stitutions of a large number of different states, which he sub- jected to a comparative study.
Perhaps most important of all was his work on the theory of logic, and Aristotle is generally considered the founder of this im- portant branch of philosophy. It was indeed the logical nature of his mind that enabled Aristotle to make contributions to so many fields. He had a gift for organizing thought, and the definitions that he proposed and the categories that he established have pro- vided the basis for later thought in many different fields. Never mystical and never an extremist, Aristotle is consistently the voice of practical common sense. He made mistakes, of course, but what is surprising is how few times in this vast encyclopedia of thought Aristotle made foolish errors.
Aristotles influence upon all later Western thought has been immense. During ancient and medieval times, his works were translated into Latin, Syriac, Arabic, Italian, French, Hebrew, German, and English. The later Greek writers studied and ad- mired his works, and so did Byzantine philosophers. His work was a major influence on Islamic philosophy, and for centuries his writings dominated European thought. Averroes, perhaps the most famous of all Arab philosophers, attempted to create a syn- thesis of Islamic theology and Aristotelian rationalism. Maimonides, the most influential of medieval Jewish thinkers,
achieved a similar synthesis for Judaism. But the most celebrated such work was the great Summa Theologica of the Christian scholar, St. Thomas Aquinas. Far too many medieval scholars were deeply influenced by Aristotle to list them all.
Admiration for Aristotle became so great that in late medieval times it approached idolatry, and his writings became a kind of intellectual straight jacket inhibiting further inquiry, rather than a lamp to light the way. Aristotle, who liked to ob- serve and think for himself, would doubtless have disapproved of the blind adulation that later generations gave to his writings.
Some of Aristotles ideas seem extremely reactionary by to- days standards. For example, he supported slavery as being in accord with natural law, and he believed in the natural inferior- ity of women. (Both of these ideas, of course, reflected the prevailing views of his time.) However, many of Aristotles views
are strikingly modern, e. g., "Poverty is the parent of revolution and crime," and "All who have meditated on the art of governing mankind are convinced that the fate of empires depends on the
education of youth." (There was, of course, no public education at the time that Aristotle lived.)
In recent centuries, Aristotles influence and reputation have declined considerably. Nevertheless, I feel that his influence was so pervasive, and lasted for so long, that I rather regret that I cannot place him higher on this list. His present ranking is
primarily a consequence of the enormous importance of each of the twelve persons preceding him.
    </string>
    <!--fortenn EUCLID-->
    <string name="forteen_EUCLID">
Few persons on this list have earned such enduring fame as the great Greek geometer, Euclid. Although in their lifetimes such figures as Napoleon, Alexander the Great, and Martin Luther were much better known than Euclid, in the long run his fame will probably well outlast theirs.
Despite his reknown, almost none of the details of Euclids life are known. We do know that he was active as a teacher in Alexandria, Egypt, in about 300 B.C. However, his dates of birth and death are uncertain, and we do not even know on which conti- nent he was born, much less in which city. Although he wrote
    several other books, some of which survive, his place in history rests primarily upon his great textbook of geometry, the Elements. The importance of the Elements does not lie in anyone of the individual theorems it demonstrates. Almost all of the theorems in the book had been known before Euclid, and a good many of the
proofs as well. Euclids great contribution was his arrangement of the material, and his formulation of the overall plan of the book. This involved, in the first place, the selection of a suitable set of axioms and postulates. (This was a very difficult task, requiring extraordinary judgment and great insight.) He then carefully ar- ranged the theorems so that each followed logically from its prede- cessors. Where necessary, he supplied missing steps and developed missing proofs. It is worth noting that the Elements, while primar-
ily a development of plane and solid geometry, also contains large sections on algebra and number theory.
The Elements has been used as a textbook for more than two thousand years, and is unquestionably the most successful textbook ever written. So superbly did Euclid do his work, that with the appearance of his book all prior geometry textbooks were super- seded and promptly forgotten. Originally written in Greek, the Elements has since been translated into many other languages. The
first printed edition appeared as early as 1482, only about thirty years after Gutenbergs invention of printing. Since then, over a thousand different editions have been published.
As an agent for training mens minds in the nature of logical reasoning, the Elements has been far more influential than any of Aristotles treatises on logic. It is the outstanding example of a complete deductive structure, and as such has fascinated thinkers ever since its creation.
It is fair to say that Euclids book was a major factor in the rise of modern science. Science is more than just a collection of accurate observations and shrewd generalizations. The great achievements of modern science come from a combination of em- piricism and experimentation on the one hand, and careful analysis and deductive reasoning on the other.
We are not certain just why science arose in Europe rather than in China or Japan, but it is safe to say that it was not merely
    by chance. Certainly, the roles played by such brilliant figures as Newton, Galileo, Copernicus, and Kepler were of tremendous importance. However, it seems likely that there were underlying reasons why men such as these flourished in Europe, rather than the Orient. Perhaps the most obvious historical factor predisposing western Europe to science was Greek rationalism, along with the mathematical knowledge that the Greeks had bequeathed.
To the Europeans, the idea that there were a few basic physi- cal principles from which everything else could be deduced seemed quite natural, for they had the example of Euclid before them. (In general, Europeans did not consider the geometry of Euclid to be merely an abstract system: they believed that Euclids postulates-and therefore his theorems-were actually true ofthe real world.)
All of the men just mentioned were steeped in the Euclidean tradition. Indeed, each of them had carefully studied the Elements, and it formed the basis of their mathematical knowledge. The in- fluence of Euclid on Isaac Newton is particularly obvious, since Newton wrote his great book, the Principia, in a geometric" form, similar to that of the Elements. Since then, many other Western scientists have emulated Euclid, by showing how their conclusions could all be logically derived from a small number ofinitial assump- tions; so have many mathematicans, such as Bertrand Russell and Alfred North Whitehead; and philosophers, such as Spinoza.
The contrast with China is particularly striking. For centuries, its technology was more advanced than that of Europe. But there was never any Chinese mathematician corresponding to Euclid, and consequently the Chinese never possessed the theoretical structure of mathematics that the West did. (The Chinese had a good knowledge of practical geometry, but their geometric knowl- edge was never reformulated into a deductive scheme.) Euclid was not translated into Chinese until about 1600 A.D., and it took a few centuries for his conception of a deductive scheme of geometry to become widely known among educated Chinese. Until that hap- pened, the Chinese did no serious work in science.
Similar statements might be made about Japan, where Eu- clids work was unknown until the eighteenth century, and even
    then not appreciated for a good many years. Though there are many excellent scientists in Japan today, there were none there before Euclid became known. One cannot help wondering whether the Europeans would have been able to create modern science had Euclid not prtpared the way!
Today, mathematicians have come to understand that Euclids geometry is not the only self-consistent geometrical system which can be devised; and during the past 150 years many non-Euclidean geometries have been constructed. Indeed, since Einsteins gen- eral theory of relativity has been accepted, scientists have realized that Euclidean geometry does not always hold true in the real universe. In the vicinity of black holes and neutron stars, for exam- ple, where the gravitational fields are extremely intense, Euclids geometry does not give an accurate picture of the world. However,
these cases are rather special; in most cases Euclids geometry provides a very close approximation of reality.
These recent advances in human knowledge, in any case, do not detract from Euclids intellectual achievement. Nor do they detract from his historical importance in the development of math- ematics and in the establishment of the logical framework neces- sary for the growth of modern science.
    </string>
    <!--fifteen MOSES-->
    <string name="fifteen_MOSES">
Probably no person in history has been so widely admired as the great Hebrew prophet Moses. Furthermore, his fame, as well as the number of people who respect him, has steadily grown throughout the ages. It is most likely that Moses flourished in the thirteenth century B. c., since Ramses II, generally thought to be the pharaoh of the Exodus story, died in 1237 B.C. During Moses lifetime, as the Book of Exodus makes clear, there were a fair number of Hebrews who disagreed with his policies. Within five centuries, ho\vever, Moses was revered by all the Jewish people. By 500 A .D ., his fame and reputation had spread, along with Christianity, throughout much of Europe. A century later, Muhammad recognized Moses as a true prophet, and with the spread of Islam, Moses became an admired figure throughout the Moslem world (even in Egypt). Today, some thirty-two centuries after he lived, Moses is honored by Jews, Christians, and
    Moslems alike, and is even respected by many agnostics. Thanks to modern communications, he is probably even better known today than he was in the past.
Despite his renown, reliable information concerning Moses life is scarce. There has even been speculation (not accepted by most scholars) that Moses was an Egyptian, since his name is of Egyptian, rather than Hebrew, origin. (It means "child" or "son," and occurs as part of the name of several famous pharaohs.) The Old Testament stories concerning Moses can hardly be accepted at face value, since they involve a large number of miracles. The stories of the burning bush, or of Moses turning his staff into a serpent, for example, are basically miraculous in nature; and it does tax ones credulity, perhaps, to believe that Moses, who \vas already eighty years old at the time
of the Exodus, still managed to lead the Hebrews in a forty-year trip through the desert. Surely, we would like to know exactly what the real Moses accomplished before his story was buried in an avalanche of legends.
Many persons have tried to give natural interpretations to the Biblical stories of the ten plagues and the crossing of the Red Sea. However, most of the favorite Old Testament stories con- cerning Moses are legendary, with analogues in other mythologies. The story of Moses and the bulrushes, for instance, is strikingly similar to a Babylonian story concerning Sargon of Akkad, a great king who reigned about 2360-2305 B.C.
In general, there are three major achievements attributed to Moses. First, he is credited with being the political figure who led the Hebrews in the Exodus from Egypt. On this point, at least, it is clear that he deserves credit. Second, he is the reputed author of the first five books of the Bible (Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy), which are often refer- red to as the "Five Books of Moses," and which constitute the
Jewish Torah. These books include the Mosaic Code, the set of laws which in principle governed the conduct of the Jews in biblical times, and which include the Ten Commandments. In view of the enormous influence which the Torah as a whole and
    the Ten Commandments in particular have had, their author would surely deserve to be considered a man of great and endur- ing influence. However, most biblical scholars agree that Moses was not the sole author of these books. The books were apparent- ly written by several authors, and the great bulk of the material was not put into writing until considerably after Moses death. It is possible that Moses played some role in codifying existing. Hebrew customs, or even in originating Hebrew laws, but there is really no way of judging how great his role was.
Third, many people consider Moses to be the founder of Jewish monotheism. In one sense, there is no basis at all for such a claim. Our only source of information concerning Moses is the Old Testament; and the Old Testament explicitly and unam- biguously credits Abraham with being the founder of mono- theism. Nevertheless, it is quite clear that Jewish monotheism would have died out had it not been for Moses, and he unques- tionably played the crucial role in its preservation and transmis- sion. In this, of course, lies his greatest importance, since Chris- tianity and Islam, the two largest religions in the world, are both derived from Jewish monotheism. The idea of one true God, which Moses believed in so passionately, has eventually spread
through a large part of the world.
    </string>
    <!--sixteen CHARLES DARWIN-->
    <string name="sixteen_CHARLES_DARWIN">Charles Darwin, the originator of the theory of organic evolution by means of natural selection, was born in Shrewsbury, Eng- land, on February 12, 1809 (on exactly the same day that Abra- ham Lincoln was born). At sixteen, he entered the University of Edinburgh to study medicine; however, he found both medicine and anatomy dull subjects, and after a while transferred to Cam- bridge to study for the ministry. At Cambridge, he found such activities as riding and shooting far more agreeable than his
studies. Nevertheless, he managed to impress one of his professors sufficiently to be recommended for the position of naturalist on the exploratory voyage of the H.M.S. Beagle. His father at first objected to Charless accepting the appointment, feeling that
    such a trip would simply be a further excuse for the young man to delay settling down to serious work. Fortunately, the elder Dar- win was persuaded to give his consent to the trip, for this was to prove one of the most rewarding ocean voyages in the history of Western science.
Darwin set sail on the Beagle in 1831, at the age of twenty- two. In the course of the next five years, the Beagle sailed around the world, skirting the coasts of South America at a leisurely pace, exploring the lonely Galapagos Islands, and visiting other islands of the Pacific, the Indian Ocean, and the South Atlantic. During the long course of the voyage, Darwin saw many natural wonders, visited primitive tribes, discovered large numbers of fossils, and observed an enormous number of plant and animal species. Furthermore, he took voluminous notes on everything that he observed. These notes provided the basis for almost all his later work; from them, he derived many of his principal ideas, as well as the immense wealth of evidence by which he made his theories prevail.
Darwin returned home in 1836, and over the next twenty years he published a series of books which established his reputa- tion as one of the leading biologists in England. As early as 1837, Darwin became convinced that animal and plant species were not fixed, but had evolved over the course of geologic history. At that time, however, he had no idea what might be the cause of such evolution. In 1838, however, he read An Essay on the Prin- ciple oj Population by Thomas Malthus, and that provided him with the vital clue to his notion of natural selection through com- petition for survival. But even after Darwin had formulated the principle of natural selection, he did not rush to present his ideas in print. He realized that his theory was bound to arouse a good deal of opposition, and he therefore spent a long time carefully assembling the evidence and marshalling the arguments in favor of his hypothesis.
He wrote an outline of his theory as early as 1842, and by 1844 was working on a full-length book. However, in June 1858, when Darwin was still adding to and revising his great work, he received a manuscript from Alfred Russel Wallace (a British naturalist who was at that time in the East Indies) outlining Wallaces own theory of evolution. In every essential point, Wallaces theory was the same as Darwins! Wallace had devel- oped his theory completely independently and had sent his manuscript to Darwin in order to obtain the opinion and com-
ments of an established scientist before publishing it. It was an embarrassing situation, which could easily have developed into an unpleasant battle over priority. Instead, Wallaces paper and an outline of Darwins book were presented as a joint paper before a scientific body the following month.
Oddly enough, that presentation did not arouse a great deal of attention. However, Darwins book, The Origin oj Species, published the following year, created a furor. In fact, it is prob- able that no scientific book ever published has been so widely and vigorously discussed, by scientist and layman alike, as On The Origin oj Species by Means oj Natural Selection, or the Preserva- tion oj Favoured Races in the Struggle for Life. The arguments were still going strong in 1871, when Darwin published The Des-
cent oj Man, and Selection in Relation to Sex. That book, which propounded the idea that man was descended from ape-like creatures, added still more fuel to the raging controversy.
Darwin himself took no part in the public debates on his theories. For one thing, he had been in bad health ever since the voyage of the Beagle (probably the result of a recurrent ailment, Chagas disease, which he had contracted from insect bites in South America). Furthermore, the partisans of evolution pos-
sessed, in Thomas H. Huxley, a skilled debater and a vigorous defender of Darwins theories. The large majority of scientists had accepted the basic correctness of Darwins theories by the time he died, in 1882.
Darwin was not the originator of the idea of the evolution of species; quite a few persons had postulated that theory before him, including the French naturalist, Jean Lamarck, and Charless own grandfather, Erasmus Darwin. But these hypo- theses had never gained the acceptance of the scientific world,
    because their proponents were unable to give convincing ex- planations of the means by which evolution occurred. Darwins great contribution was that he was able to present not only a mechanism-natural selection-by which evolution could occur, but also a large quantity of convincing evidence to support his hypothesis.
It is worth noting that Darwins theory was formulated without any reliance on genetic theory-or indeed, any know- ledge of it. In Darwins day, no one knew anything about the way in which particular characteristics were passed on from one generation to the next. Although Gregor Mendel was working out the laws of heredity during the same years that Darwin was writing and publishing his epoch-making books, Mendels work-which supplements Darwins so perfectly-was almost totally ignored until the year 1900, by which time Darwins theories were already well established. Thus, our modern under- standing of evolution, which combines the laws of genetic in- heritance with natural selection, is more complete than the theory proposed by Darwin.
Darwins influence on human thought has been immense. In the purely scientific sense, of course, he revolutionized the en- tire subject of biology. Natural selection is a very broad princi- ple indeed, and attempts have been made to apply it to many other fields, such as anthropology, sociology, political science, and economics.
Even more important, perhaps, than their scientific or sociological import, has been the impact of Darwins theories upon religious thought. In Darwins day, and for many years thereafter, many devout Christians believed that the acceptance of Darwins theories would undermine belief in religion. Their fears were perhaps justified, although it is obvious that many other factors have played a role in the general decline of religious sentiment. (Darwin himself became an agnostic.)
Even on a secular level, Darwins theory has caused a great change in the way that human beings think about their world. The human race as a whole no longer seems to occupy the central
    position in the natural scheme of things that it once did. We now have to regard ourselves as one species among many, and we recognize the possibility that we may one day be superseded. As a result of Darwins work, the viewpoint of Heraclitus, that "there is nothing permanent except change" has gained much wider ac- ceptance. The success of the theory of evolution as a general ex- planation of the origin of man has greatly strengthened belief in
the ability of science to provide answers to all physical questions (although not, alas, to all human problems). The Darwinian terms "the struggle for existence" and "the survival of the fittest" have passed into our vocabulary.
It is obvious that Darwins theories would have been ex- pounded even had he never lived. In fact, in view of Wallaces work, this is perhaps more obviously true of Darwin than of any other person on this list. Still, it \-vas Darwins writings which revolutionized biology and anthropology, and which have so altered our view of mans place in the world.</string>
    <!--seventeen SHIH HUANG TI-->
    <string name="seventeen_SHIH_HUANG_TI">The great Chinese emperor Shih Huang Ti, who ruled from 238-210 B.C, united China by force of arms and instituted a set of sweeping reforms. Those reforms have been a major factor in the cultural unity that China has maintained ever since.
Shih Huang Ti (also known as Chin Shih Huang Ti) was born in 259 B.C. and died in 210 B.C. To understand his im- portance, it is necessary to have some knowledge of the historical background of his times. He was born in the final years of the Chou dynasty, which had been founded about 1100 B.C. Cen- turies before his time, however, the Chou monarchs had ceased
    to be effective rulers, and China had become divided into a large number of feudal states.
The various feudal lords were constantly at war with one another, and gradually, several of the smaller rulers were eliminated. One of the most powerful of the warring states was Chin, in the western portion of the country. The Chin rulers had adopted the ideas of the Legalist school of Chinese philosophers as the basis of state policy. Confucius had suggested
that men should be governed primarily by the moral example of a good ruler; but according to the Legalist philosophy, most men were not good enough to be ruled in that way and could only be controlled by a strict set of laws firmly and impartially enforced. Laws were made by the ruler and could be changed at his pleasure to further state policy.
Possibly because of their adoption of Legalist ideas, possibly because of their geographical position, or possibly because of the capability of the Chin rulers, that state had already become the most powerful of the Chinese states at the time that Cheng (the future Shih Huang Ti) was born. Nominally, Cheng ascended the throne in 246 B.C;, at the age of thirteen, but, in fact, a regent governed until Cheng came of age in 238 B.C. The new monarch chose able generals and vigorously prosecuted the wars
against the remaining feudal states. The last of these were con- quered in 221 B.C., and he could now have declared himself Wang (king) of all China. To emphasize, however, the complete break he was making with the past, he chose a new title, and called himself Shih Huang Ti, which means "the first emperor."
Shih Huang Ti immediately began to institute a large number of important reforms. Determined to avoid the disunity which had destroyed the Chou monarchy, he decided to abolish the entire feudal system of government. The territory he ruled was re-apportioned into thirty-six provinces, each with a civilian governor appointed by the emperor. Shih Huang Ti decreed that the office of provincial governor.    no longer to be hereditary.
Indeed, the practice soon developed..of shifting governors from one province to another after a few years, to avoid the possibility
    of an amibitous governor attaining a strong power base of his own. Each province also had its own military leader, appointed by the emperor and removable at his pleasure, and a third, centrally-appointed official to maintain the balance between the civil and military governors. An extensive system of good roads was constructed, connecting the capital city with the provinces, and insuring that the central army could be quickly dispatched to any province besieged by a local revolt. Shih Huang Ti also decreed that the surviving members of the old aristocracy would have to move to Hsien Yang, his own capital, where he could keep an eye on them.
But Shih Huang Ti was not content with merely political and military unity in China; he sought commercial unity as well. He instituted a unified set of weights and measures throughout the country; standardized the coinage, various implements, and the axle lengths of wagons; and supervised the construction of roads and canals. He also established a system of unified laws throughout China and standardized the written language.
The emperors most famous (or perhaps infamous) act was the decree of 213 B.C, in which he ordered the burning of all the books in China. Exceptions were made for writings on such technical topics as agriculture and medicine, the historical records of the state of Chin, and the philosophical works of the Legalist writers. But the writings of all the other schools of philosophy-including the doctrines of Confucius-were to be destroyed. By this Draconian decree, probably the first example of large-scale censorship in all of history, Shih Huang Ti hoped to
destroy the influence of rival philosophies, and particularly that of the Confucian school. However, he did order that copies of the prohibited books were to be kept in the imperial library, in the capital city.
Shih Huang Tis foreign policy was equally vigorous. He made extensive conquests in the southern part of the country, and the regions that he annexed were eventually absorbed into China. In the North and West also, his armies were successful, but he could not permanently conquer the peoples living there.
    However, to prevent them from making raids into China, Shih Huang Ti connected the various local walls already existing on Chinas northern frontiers into one gigantic wall, The Great Wall of China, which has endured to the present day. These con- struction projects, together with the series of foreign wars, necessitated high taxes, which made the emperor unpopular.
Since rebellion against his iron rule was impossible, attempts were made to assassinate him. None of these attempts succeeded, however, and Shih Huang Ti died a natural death in the year 210 B.C.
The emperor was succeeded by his second son, who took the title Erh Shih Huang Ti. But Erh Shih Huang Ti lacked his fathers ability, and revolts soon broke out. Within four years he was killed; the palace and the imperial library were burned; and the Chin dynasty was totally destroyed.
But the work that Shih Huang Ti had accomplished was not to be undone. The Chinese were glad that his tyrannical rule was ended, but few of them wanted to return to the anarchy of the preceding era. The next dynasty (the Han dynasty) continued the basic administrative system set up by Chin Shih Huang Ti. In- deed, for twenty-one centuries the Chinese Empire continued to
be organized along the lines he had established. Although the harsh system of laws of the Chin were soon moderated by the Han emperors, and although the whole Legalist philosophy fell into disfavor and Confucianism became the official state philosophy, the cultural and political unification which Shih Huang Ti had created was not reversed.
The critical importance of Shih Huang Ti for China and for the world as a whole should now be apparent. Westerners have always been awed at the enormous size of China; however, throughout most of history China has not really been much more populous than Europe. The difference is that Europe has always been divided into many small states, while China has been united into a single large state. This difference
seems to have resulted from political and social factors rather than geography: internal barriers, such as mountain ranges,
    are just as prominent in China as they are in Europe. Of course, the unity of China cannot be ascribed to the work of Shih Huang Ti alone. Various other persons-for example, Sui Wen Ti-have also played important roles, but there seems no doubt of Shih Huang Tis central importance.
No discussion of Shih Huang Ti would be complete without mention of his brilliant and celebrated chief minister, Li Ssu. In fact, so important was the influence of Li Ssu on the emperors policies, that it is difficult to know how to divide the credit bet\veen them for the great changes instituted. Rather than attempt that, I have assigned all the credit for their joint achievement to Shih Huang Ti. (After all, although Li Ssu of- fered advice, it was the emperor who had the final say.)
Shih Huang Ti, partly because of his burning of the books, has been vilified by most later Confucian writers. They de- nounce him as a tyrant, superstitious, malevolent, illegitimate- ly born, and of mediocre ability. The Chinese Communists on the other hand, generally praise him as a progressive thinker. Western writers have occasionally compared Shih Huang Ti to Napoleon; however, it seems far more appropriate to compare him to Augustus Caesar, the founder of the Roman Empire. The empires that they established were of more or less the same size and population. However, the Roman Empire en- dured for a far shorter period, and the territory ruled by Augustus did not in the long run retain its unity, whereas the territory governed by Shih Huang Ti did, making him the more influential of the two.</string>
    <!--eighteen AUGUSTUS CAESAR-->
    <string name="eighteen_AUGUSTUS_CAESAR">Augustus Caesar, the founder of the Roman Empire, is one of the great pivotal figures in history. He ended the civil wars that had disrupted the Roman Republic during the first century B .C ., and he reorganized the Roman government so that internal peace and prosperity were maintained for two centuries.
Gaius Octavius (better known as Octavian; he did not receive the title "Augustus" until he was thirty-five years old) was born in 63 B.C. He was the grandnephew of Julius Caesar, who was the leading political figure of Rome during Octavians youth. Julius Caesar, who had no legitimate sons of his own, liked the youth, and helped prepare him for a political career. However,
    when Caesar was assassinated in 44 B.C., Octavian was still only an eighteen-year-old student.
The death of Caesar set off a long and bitter struggle for power between various ROlnan military and political figures. At first, his rivals, who were all men of long experience in the rough arena of Roman politics, did not consider the youthful Octavian a serious threat. Indeed, the young mans only visible asset was that Julius Caesar had adopted him as his son. By making skillful use of this advantage, Octavian managed to win the support of some of Caesars legions. Many of Caesars troops, however, chose to support Mark Antony, \vho had been one of Caesars closest associates. A series of battles over the next few years eliminated all the other contestants for power; by 36 B.C., Rome, and the many territories she had already conquered, were divid- ed between Mark Antony, who controlled the eastern portion, and Octavian, who controlled the West. For a few years, there was an uneasy truce between them. During that time, Antony seems to have paid too much attention to his romance with Cleopatra, while Octavian steadily improved his position. War broke out between the two men in 32 B.C., and the issue was decided by the great naval battle at Actium (31 B.C.), which was won by Octavians forces. The following year, the war ended with the complete triumph of Octavian, and Antony and Cleopatra both committed suicide.
Octavian had now achieved the same position of power that Julius Caesar had attained fifteen years earlier. Caesar had been assassinated, because it had been obvious that he intended to end republican government in Rome and set himself up as a monarch. But by 30 B.C., after many years of civil war and the obvious failure of republican government in Rome, most Romans were willing to accept a benevolent despot, as long as the pretense of democratic rule was continued.
Octavian, though he had been ruthless during his fight to the top, was surprisingly conciliatory once he was established in power. In 27 B.C., to soothe senatorial feelings, he announced that he was restoring the Republic, and he offered to resign all
    his government posts. In fact, however, he retained his position as head of the provinces of Spain, Gaul, and Syria. Since the ma- jority of Roman troops were in these three provinces, the actual power was securely in his hands. The Senate voted him the honorific title of Augustus, but he never assumed the title of king. In theory, Rome was still a republic, and Augustus was no more than princeps (first citizen). In actual practice, the grateful and docile Senate appointed Augustus to whatever positions he
chose, and for the remainder of his life he was effectively a dic- tator. By the time he died, in 14 A.D., Rome had completed the transition from republic to monarchy, and his adopted son suc- ceeded him without difficulty.
Augustus stands out as perhaps the best example in history of a capable, benevolent despot. He was a true statesman, whose conciliatory policies did much to heal the deep divisions resulting from the Roman civil wars.
Augustus ruled Rome for over forty years, and his policies influenced the Empire for many years to come. Under him, Roman armies completed the conquest of Spain, Switzerland, Galatia (in Asia Minor), and a large portion of the Balkans. By the end of his rule, the northern boundary of the Empire was not much different from the Rhine-Danube line which was to be the northern border for most of the next few centuries.
Augustus was an extraordinarily able administrator and played a major role in building up a capable civil service. He revised the tax structure and financial system of the Roman state; he reorganized the Roman army; and he established a permanent navy. He also organized a personal bodyguard, the Praetorian Guard, which in future centuries was to playa great role in selec- ting and deposing emperors.
Under Augustus, an extensive network of excellent roads was constructed throughout the Roman Empire; many public buildings were erected in Rome itself; and the city was greatly beautified. Temples were constructed, and Augustus encouraged observance of and loyalty to the old Roman religion. Laws were passed encouraging marriage and the raising of children.
    From 30 B.C. on, Rome had internal peace under Augustus. The natural result was a greatly increased prosperity. This, in turn, led to a great flourishing of the arts, and the Augustan Age was the Golden Age of Roman literature. Romes greatest poet, Virgil, lived during this period, as did many other writers, including Horace and Livy. Ovid incurred the displeasure of Augustus, and was banished from Rome.
Augustus had no sons, and a nephew and two grandsons died before him; he therefore adopted his stepson, Tiberius, and designated him his successor. But the dynasty (which later in- cluded the infamous rulers Caligula and Nero) soon became ex- tinct. Nevertheless, the period of internal peace that commenced with Augustus, the so-called Pax Romana, was to endure for some two hundred years. During this extended period of peace and prosperity, Roman culture was suffused deeply into the ter- ritories that Augustus and other Roman leaders had conquered.
The Roman Empire is the most celebrated empire of anti- quity, and rightly so. For Rome was both the culmination of an- cient civilization and the principal conduit by which the ideas and cultural achievements of the peoples of the ancient world (Egyptians, Babylonians, Jews, Greeks, and others) have been transmitted to western Europe.
It is interesting to compare Augustus with his granduncle, Julius Caesar. Despite Augustuss good looks, intelligence, strength of character, and military successes, he lacked his predecessors charisma. Julius excited the imagination of his con- temporaries far more than August did, and he has remained more famous ever since. In their actual influence upon history, however, Augustus was by far the more important of the two.
It is also interesting to compare Augustus with Alexander the Great. Both started their careers when quite young. But Augustus had to overcome much tougher competition in order to reach the top. His military ability was not as exceptional as Alex- anders, but it was certainly impressive, and his conquests were to prove much more enduring. That, in fact, is the greatest dif- ference between the two men. Augustus carefully built for the
    future, and as a result, his long-term influence on human history has been considerably larger.
Augustus might also be compared with George Washington. Both of them played important (and somewhat analogous) roles in world history; but in view of the length of Augustuss rule, the success of his policies, and the importance of the Roman Empire in world history, I believe that Augustus should be ranked the
higher of the two.
</string>
    <!--ninteen NICOLAUS COPERNICUS-->
    <string name="ninteen_NICOLAUS_COPERNICUS">The great Polish astronomer Nicolaus Copernicus (Polish name: Mikolaj Kopernik), was born in 1473, in the city of Torun, on the Vistula River, in Poland. He came from a well-to-do family. As a young man, Copernicus studied at the University of Cracow, where he became interested in astronomy. In his mid-twenties he went to Italy, where he studied law and medicine at the Univer- sities of Bologna and Padua, and later received a doctorate in canon law from the University of Ferrara. Copernicus spent most of his adult life on the staff of the cathedral at Frauenburg (Polish: Frombork), where he was a canon. Copernicus was never a professional astronomer, and the great work which has made him famous was accomplished in his spare time.
    During his stay in Italy, Copernicus had become acquainted with the idea of the Greek philosopher, Aristarchus of Samos (third century B.C.), that the earth and the other planets revolved about the sun. Copernicus became convinced of the correctness of this heliocentric hypothesis, and when he was about forty he began to circulate among his friends a short, handwritten manu-
script setting forth in preliminary form his own ideas on the sub- ject. Copernicus spent many years taking the observations and making the calculations that were necessary for the composition of his great book, De revolutionibus orbium coelestium (On the Revolution of the Celestial Spheres), in which he describes his theory in detail, and sets forth the evidence for it.
In 1533, when he was sixty years old, Copernicus delivered a series of lectures in Rome, in which he presented the principal points of his theory, without incurring papal disapproval. However, it was not until he was in his late sixties that Copernicus finally decided to have his book published; and it was not until the day he died, May 24, 1543, that he received the first copy of his book from the printer.
In his book, Copernicus correctly stated that the earth rotates on its axis; that the moon revolves around the earth; and that the earth and the other planets all revolve about the sun.
However, like his predecessors, he badly underestimated the scale of the solar system. Also, he was wrong in believing that the orbits consist of circles or of epicycles. Thus, his theory was not only complicated mathematically, but inexact as well. Never- theless, his book promptly aroused great interest. It also motivated other astronomers, most notably the great Danish astronomer, Tycho Brahe, to make more accurate observations of planetary motions. It was from the observational data ac- cumulated by Tycho that Johannes Kepler was finally able to deduce the correct laws of planetary motion.
Though Aristarchus of Samos had propounded the heliocen- tric hypothesis more than seventeen centuries before Copernicus, it is appropriate that Copernicus has received the bulk of the
credit. Aristarchus had made an inspired guess, but had never
    presented his theory in sufficient detail to make it scientifically useful. When Copernicus worked out the mathematics of the hypothesis in detail, he transformed it into a useful scientific theory-one that could be used for prediction, that could be
    checked against astronomical observations, and that could be meaningfully compared with the older theory that the earth was the center of the universe.
It is clear that the Copernican theory has revolutionized our conception of the universe, and has led to major changes in our whole philosophical outlook. But in evaluating the importance of Copernicus, it should be remembered that astronomy does not have the great range of practical applications that physics, chemistry, and biology do. In principle, one could construct such devices as a television set, an automobile, or a modern chemical factory without the slightest knowledge or application of Coper- nicuss theories. (One could not do so without applying the ideas
of Faraday, Maxwell, Lavoisier, and Newton.)
But to consider only the direct influence on Copernicus on
technology would be to completely miss his true significance. Copernicuss book was the indispensable prologue to the work of both Galileo and Kepler. They in turn were the major predecessors of Newton, and it was their discoveries which enabled Newton to formulate his laws of motion and gravitation. Historically, the publication of De revolutionibus orbium
" coelestium was the starting point of modern astronomy-and, more importantly, the starting point of modern science.
    </string>
    <!--twenty ANTOINE LAURENTLA VOISIER-->
    <string name="twenty_ANTOINE_LAURENTLA_VOISIER">The great French scientist Antoine Laurent Lavoisier was the most important figure in the development of chemistry. At the time of his birth, in Paris, in 1743, the science of chemistry lag- ged far behind physics, mathematics, and astronomy. Large numbers of individual facts had been discovered by chemists, but there was no adequate theoretical framework in which to fit these isolated bits of information. At that time, it was incorrectly believed that air and water were elementary substances. Worse still, there was a complete misunderstanding of the nature of fire. It was believed that all combustible materials contained a hypothetical substance called "phlogiston," and that during combustion the inflammable substance released its phlogiston in- to the air.
In the interval from 1754 to 1774, talented chemists such as Joseph Black, Joseph Priestley, Henry Cavendish, and others had isolated such important gases as oxygen, hydrogen, nitrogen, and
    carbon dioxide. However, since these men accepted the phlogiston theory, they were quite unable to understand the nature or significance of the chemical substances they had discovered. Oxygen, for example, was referred to as dephlogisticated air, i.e., air from which all the phlogiston had been removed. (It was known that a sliver of wood burned better
in oxygen than in ordinary air; presumably, this was because dephlogisticated air could more readily absorb phlogiston from the burning wood.) Obviously, real progress in chemistry could not be made until the fundamentals were correctly understood.
It was Lavoisier who managed to put the pieces of the puz- zle together correctly, and to get chemical theory started on the correct path. In the first place, Lavoisier said, the phlogiston theory is. completely incorrect: there is no such substance as phlogiston. The process of combustion consists of the chemical combination of the burping substance with oxygen. In the second place, water is not an elementary substance at all but a chemical
compound of oxygen and hydrogen. Air is not an elementary substance either, but consists primarily of a mixture of the two gases, oxygen and nitrogen. All of these statements seem quite obvious today. However, they were not at all obvious to Lavoisiers predecessors and contemporaries. Even after Lavoisier formulated his theories and presented the evidence for them, many leading chemists refused to accept his ideas. But
Lavoisiers excellent textbook, Elements of Chemistry (1789), so clearly presented his hypotheses, and so convincingly marshalled the evidence in their behalf, that the younger generation of chemists was quickly convinced.
Having shown that water and air were not chemical elements, Lavoisier included in his book a list of those substances that he did believe to be elementary. Although his list contains a few errors, a modern list of the chemical elements is basically an enlarged version of Lavoisiers table.
Lavoisier had already (in conjunction with Berthollet, Four- croi, and Guyton de Morveau) devised the first well-organized system of chemical nomenclature. In Lavoisiers system (which forms the basis of the one used today), the composition of a chemical is described by its name. The adoption, for the first time, of a uniform system of nomenclature enabled chemists throughout the world to clearly communicate their discoveries to each other.
Lavoisier was the first person to clearly state the principle of conservation of mass in chemical reactions: A chemical reaction might rearrange the elements present in the original substances, but no matter is destroyed thereby, and the end products weigh the same as the original components. Lavoisiers insistence on the importance of carefully weighing the chemicals involved in a reaction helped turn chemistry into an exact science, and prepared the way for much of the subsequent progress in chemistry.
Lavoisier also made some minor contributions to the study of geology, and a major contribution in the field of physiology. By careful experiments (working in conjunction with Laplace), he was able to show that the physiological process of respiration is basically equivalent to a slow combustion. In other words, human beings and other animals derive their energy from a slow, internal burning of organic material, using the oxygen in the air they inhale. That discovery alone-which is perhaps comparable in significance to Harveys discovery of the circulation of the blood-might \vell entitle Lavoisier to a place on this list. Still, Lavoisier is primarily important because his formulation of chemical theory started the science of chemistry firmly on the correct path. He is generally referred to as "the father of modern chemistry," and he richly deserves that title.
Like quite a few other persons on this list, Lavoisier studied law as a young man. Although he received a law degree and was admitted to the French bar, Lavoisier never practiced law. He did, though, engage in much administrative work and public ser- vice. He was active in the French Royal Academy of Sciences. He was also a member of the Ferme Generale, an organization in- volved in the collection of taxes. As a consequence, after the French Revolution in 1789, the Revolutionary government was
    very suspicious of him. Eventually, he was arrested, along with twenty-seven other members of the Ferme Generale. Revolu- tionary justice may not have been too accurate, but it was cer- tainly speedy. On a single day (May 8, 1794), all of the twenty- eight persons were tried, convicted, and guillotined. Lavoisier was survived by his wife, a brilliant woman who had assisted
him in his researches.
At the trial, an appeal was made to spare Lavoisier, citing
his numerous services to his country and to science. The judge re- jected the plea with the curt remark that, "The Republic has no need of geniuses." Somewhat closer to the truth was the remark of his colleague, the great mathematician Lagrange: "It took but a moment to sever that head, though a hundred years may not produce another like it."
    </string>

</resources>